<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>homebrew on Nicola Iarocci</title>
    <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/tags/homebrew/</link>
    <description>Recent content in homebrew on Nicola Iarocci</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <copyright>Produced / Written / Maintained by [Nicola Iarocci](/) since 2010</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 20 Jun 2023 07:05:25 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://nicolaiarocci.com/tags/homebrew/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Homebrew and docfx don&#39;t like each other too</title>
      <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/homebrew-and-docfx-dont-like-each-other-too/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 20 Jun 2023 07:05:25 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nicolaiarocci.com/homebrew-and-docfx-dont-like-each-other-too/</guid>
      <description>Another day another Homebrew incompatibility emerges, this time with docfx, the technical documentation building tool of reference in .NET space. I&amp;rsquo;ve been using docfx for years to build the FatturaElettronica.NET website, and it&amp;rsquo;s always been working without a glitch. Lately, however, my builds have been failing with strange errors I was too lazy to diagnose until today when I decided to grasp the nettle and sort the whole thing out.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Another day another Homebrew incompatibility emerges, this time with <a href="https://dotnet.github.io/docfx/index.html">docfx</a>, the technical documentation building
tool of reference in .NET space. I&rsquo;ve been using docfx for years to build the <a href="https://fatturaelettronicaopensource.org">FatturaElettronica.NET</a> website, and it&rsquo;s
always been working without a glitch. Lately, however, my builds have been failing with strange errors I was too lazy to
diagnose until today when I decided to grasp the nettle and sort the whole thing out.</p>
<p>It took me an embarrassing time to realize that, while successful, my docfx updates (<code>dotnet tool update -g docfx</code>) were
being ignored. An old, Homebrew-installed version of docfx was being executed at my launches —a simple <code>which docfx</code>
revealed the issue. <code>brew uninstall docfx</code> finally set the updated, dotnet-installed version free of its chains, and it
is now merrily churning websites.</p>
<p>A similar issue emerged <a href="/homebrew-and-dotnet-8-preview-dont-like-each-other/">between Homebrew and .NET 8 Preview</a> only a few days ago. Lesson learned I&rsquo;m not installing
dotnet tools via Homebrew anymore. Or maybe, I might stay clear of Homebrew altogether.</p>
<p><em>Subscribe to the <a href="https://nicolaiarocci.substack.com">newsletter</a>, the <a href="https://nicolaiarocci.com/index.xml">RSS feed</a>, or <a href="https://fosstodon.org/@nicola">follow me on Mastodon</a></em></p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Homebrew and .NET 8 Preview don&#39;t like each other</title>
      <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/homebrew-and-dotnet-8-preview-dont-like-each-other/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 Jun 2023 07:05:25 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nicolaiarocci.com/homebrew-and-dotnet-8-preview-dont-like-each-other/</guid>
      <description>Today I learned that .NET 8 Preview could play better with Homebrew (or vice-versa). I&amp;rsquo;m working on a C# 12 presentation for our local developer meetup, and for that, I wanted .NET 8 Preview to run side by side with version 7 on my Mac. As version 7 was initially installed with Homebrew, I also wanted to install version 8 Preview with Homebrew, but that recipe was unavailable. Not perfectly happy with that, I fell back to the stand-alone installer, expecting problems.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Today I learned that .NET 8 Preview could play better with Homebrew (or vice-versa). I&rsquo;m working on a <a href="https://www.meetup.com/it-IT/devromagna/events/293340671/">C# 12 presentation
for our local developer meetup</a>, and for that, I wanted .NET 8 Preview to run side by side with version 7 on my Mac. As
version 7 was initially installed with Homebrew, I also wanted to install version 8 Preview with Homebrew, but that
recipe was unavailable. Not perfectly happy with that, I fell back to the stand-alone installer, expecting
problems.</p>
<p>Installation went well, but then I turned to the command line only to find that <code>dotnet --list-sdks</code> was still and only
showing version 7. Yet, the 8 Preview was sitting there at its canonical location at <code>/usr/local/share/dotnet/sdk</code>,
where the v7 was also listed.</p>
<p>Puzzled, I tried a few things, but the quick fix was to simply <code>brew uninstall --ignore-dependencies dotnet</code> and, boom,
both versions 8 Preview and 7 became immediately available. I suspect that <code>brew uninstall</code> only removed the symlink
from .NET canonical location to the Homebrew cellar, which magically solved the SDK visibility problem.</p>
<p>TL; DR. Homebrew recipes don&rsquo;t play nicely with .NET canonical installer. To make all my SDK versions visible to .NET,
I had to forego the Homebrew installation, which did not uninstall the SDK itself, but simply unlinked it.</p>
<p><em>Subscribe to the <a href="https://nicolaiarocci.substack.com">newsletter</a>, the <a href="https://nicolaiarocci.com/index.xml">RSS feed</a>, or <a href="https://fosstodon.org/@nicola">follow me on Mastodon</a></em></p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>So tired of Homebrew messing up with my stuff</title>
      <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/so-tired-of-homebrew-messing-up-with-my-stuff/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 May 2021 08:05:25 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nicolaiarocci.com/so-tired-of-homebrew-messing-up-with-my-stuff/</guid>
      <description>Pardon me while I&amp;rsquo;m venting out my frustration. I am so tired of Homebrew messing up with my stuff. It used to be the perfect tool for the right job until they decided to auto-brew-update-and-cleanup at every new install. Another day another issue, today with vim not running anymore:
dyld: Library not loaded: /usr/local/opt/lua/lib/liblua.5.3.dylib Referenced from: /user/local/bin/vi Reason: image not found Lua has suddenly gone missing. Ah, but of course. I installed something with Homebrew this morning.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Pardon me while I&rsquo;m venting out my frustration. I am so tired of Homebrew
messing up with my stuff. It used to be the perfect tool for the right job
until they decided to auto-brew-update-and-cleanup at every new install.
Another day another issue, today with vim not running anymore:</p>
<pre><code>dyld: Library not loaded: /usr/local/opt/lua/lib/liblua.5.3.dylib
Referenced from: /user/local/bin/vi
Reason: image not found
</code></pre>
<p>Lua has suddenly gone missing. Ah, but of course. I installed something with
Homebrew this morning. The fix is to <code>brew reinstall vim</code>, which then leads to
the following error:</p>
<pre><code>Error: python@3.9 the bottle needs the Apple Command LIne Tools to be installed.
You can install them, if desired, with:
xcode-select --install
</code></pre>
<p>An <code>xcode-select install</code> and another <code>brew reinstall</code> later, vim is back home.
It&rsquo;s only a minor annoyance —only a few wasted minutes, but the point is, they
didn&rsquo;t need to be wasted. If you&rsquo;re frequently installing stuff via Homebrew,
this is quite a common, unpleasant occurrence (python virtual environments
being hit with alarming frequency).</p>
<p>I know that one can disable automatic cleanups by setting the
<code>HOMEBREW_NO_INSTALL_CLEANUP</code> environment variable. I will end up doing that
out of frustration sooner or later. Again, the point is I should not need to do
that.  It all adds unnecessary friction, especially for someone who&rsquo;s been
religiously running manual cleanups (I concede that an un-maintained brew cache
can grow to <em>very</em> sizable dimensions).</p>
<p>Homebrew is still an essential tool; just not so enjoyable anymore. It&rsquo;s not
like we have a valid alternative at hand, anyway.</p>
<p><em>Subscribe to the <a href="https://nicolaiarocci.substack.com">newsletter</a>, the <a href="https://nicolaiarocci.com/index.xml">RSS feed</a>, or follow @<a href="http://twitter.com/nicolaiarocci">nicolaiarocci</a> on Twitter</em></p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
