<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>Fiction on Nicola Iarocci</title>
    <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/tags/fiction/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Fiction on Nicola Iarocci</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- 0.143.1</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <copyright>Produced / Written / Maintained by Nicola Iarocci since 2010</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 22 Sep 2021 07:05:25 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://nicolaiarocci.com/tags/fiction/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Book Review: Nausea</title>
      <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/book-review-nausea/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Sep 2021 07:05:25 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nicolaiarocci.com/book-review-nausea/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Antoine Roquentin, the protagonist of the novel, is a former adventurer who has
been living for three years in Bouville, a fictional French seaport town,
researching the life of an 18th-century diplomat. During his previous life
around the world, Antoine has seen many places, met many interesting people,
done exciting things. For the last three years, however, he&amp;rsquo;s been alone in
Bouville. He has no friends and no desire to make some or meet anyone. He&amp;rsquo;s
interested in nothing, not even in his work that he keeps neglecting. His days
are mostly spent walking around town, listening to conversations and observing
people around him. A &amp;ldquo;sweeting sickness&amp;rdquo; he calls nausea increasingly impinges
on almost everything he does and enjoys.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Antoine Roquentin, the protagonist of the novel, is a former adventurer who has
been living for three years in Bouville, a fictional French seaport town,
researching the life of an 18th-century diplomat. During his previous life
around the world, Antoine has seen many places, met many interesting people,
done exciting things. For the last three years, however, he&rsquo;s been alone in
Bouville. He has no friends and no desire to make some or meet anyone. He&rsquo;s
interested in nothing, not even in his work that he keeps neglecting. His days
are mostly spent walking around town, listening to conversations and observing
people around him. A &ldquo;sweeting sickness&rdquo; he calls nausea increasingly impinges
on almost everything he does and enjoys.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Something has happened to me, I can&rsquo;t doubt it any more. It came as an
illness does, not like an ordinary certainty, not like anything evident. It
came cunningly, little by little; I felt a little strange, a little put out,
that&rsquo;s all. Once established it never moved, it stayed quiet, and I was able
to persuade myself that nothing was the matter with me, that it was a false
alarm. And now, it&rsquo;s blossoming.</p></blockquote>
<p>He has a relationship with a woman, but it is exclusively carnal: the two
exchange almost no words. Selt-Taught Man, an individual who spends his time at
the local library reading all books in alphabetical order, is one of his few
acquaintances. When Self-Taught Man invites Antoine for lunch, he notes on his
diary: &ldquo;I had as much desire to eat with him as I had to hang myself.&rdquo; Antoine
has no interest in relationships. They take too much effort.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>When you live alone you no longer know what it is to tell a story: the
plausible disappears at the same time as the friends.</p></blockquote>
<p><img alt="Nausea, by Jean Paul Sartre" loading="lazy" src="/images/nausea.jpg#right">
Antoine feels like he never lived but only existed. These days, we would
probably call Antoine&rsquo;s sickness with a different name, depression maybe. If
you ever felt like Antoine, Nausea is going to be a difficult read. If you
didn&rsquo;t, I suspect it will be hard for you to feel any sympathy for the
protagonist. Sartre writes beautifully, with razor-sharp precision. Despite his
attempts to refuse it, he won the Nobel Prize in Literature in 1964. Nausea was
Sartre&rsquo;s debut novel, and he always considered it his best fictional work.
Nausea, by Jean-Paul Sartre, is a challenging but rewarding read. I think
Sartre goes straight amongst the masters at describing the human condition.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
