<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>Homlessness on Nicola Iarocci</title>
    <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/tags/homlessness/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Homlessness on Nicola Iarocci</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- 0.143.1</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <copyright>Produced / Written / Maintained by Nicola Iarocci since 2010</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 12 Jan 2024 15:53:46 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://nicolaiarocci.com/tags/homlessness/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Fabio the tramp</title>
      <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/fabio-the-tramp/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Jan 2024 15:53:46 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nicolaiarocci.com/fabio-the-tramp/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Last night, I was preparing dinner while waiting for Serena to return home when
I received an unexpected call from her: she was in her parked car, petrified as
the car&amp;rsquo;s headlights had illuminated a person lying on the floor of our
building&amp;rsquo;s entrance, right in front of the elevator&lt;sup id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34; class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; role=&#34;doc-noteref&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;. I told her to stay in the
car and rushed down the stairs. When I got to the ground floor, no one was
there; I checked the basement, and it was empty, too. On my way back, I found
Serena entering from the front door. She told me the person had quickly risen
and walked away when the lights turned on in the staircase.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Last night, I was preparing dinner while waiting for Serena to return home when
I received an unexpected call from her: she was in her parked car, petrified as
the car&rsquo;s headlights had illuminated a person lying on the floor of our
building&rsquo;s entrance, right in front of the elevator<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1</a></sup>. I told her to stay in the
car and rushed down the stairs. When I got to the ground floor, no one was
there; I checked the basement, and it was empty, too. On my way back, I found
Serena entering from the front door. She told me the person had quickly risen
and walked away when the lights turned on in the staircase.</p>
<p>I took a few steps outside and saw an aged, bald man on the porch, more or less
twenty meters away. He was standing still, looking back at me. He had nothing
going on, no jacket, scarf, or cap, just a sweater, cargo pants with summer
shorts on top, canvas shoes, and half gloves, and that was it. It must have been
0 or 1 degree Celsius. It was so cold. Since he wasn&rsquo;t fleeing, I approached him
and asked if everything was okay and if he needed any help<sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">2</a></sup>. He nodded and said,
&ldquo;Yes.&rdquo; That broke my heart.</p>
<p>He then told me, &ldquo;My teeth hurt&rdquo;. From what I could see, he was utterly
toothless. I asked if he had entered the building looking for warmth, and he
nodded again. I told him we could get him something warm, and then, if he
allowed us, we would call for help. &ldquo;Yes, he again answered. I told him to wait
a few minutes, and then we went to our apartment to get an old jacket, an
oversized, warm scarf and a woolen cap. &ldquo;He must have run away by now,&rdquo; I
thought as I went down with everything tucked under my arm, but when the
elevator door opened, I found he had made his way into the building again and
was waiting for me. I helped him wear the jacket and wrap his scarf around his
neck. As I called for an ambulance, he laid down again on the floor; all
gathered up to keep what little warmth the new clothes could give within.</p>
<p>We waited about 20 minutes. The ambulance driver made him get up abruptly,
pulling him by the arm and scolding him because &ldquo;you don&rsquo;t go into buildings;
it&rsquo;s forbidden.&rdquo; The nurse wanted to return our clothes because &ldquo;we have
blankets&rdquo;; it took a while to explain that we didn&rsquo;t want them back and that he
would need them the following day anyway when he inevitably ended up back on the
street.</p>
<p>His name is Fabio, and he is 60 years old.</p>
<div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
<hr>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1">
<p>The return spring of the building&rsquo;s front door has been broken for some time. As a result, the door only closes if accompanied, and no one does.&#160;<a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
<li id="fn:2">
<p>Silly questions. I wanted to be reassuring, and I couldn&rsquo;t develop anything better.&#160;<a href="#fnref:2" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
</ol>
</div>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
