<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>events on Nicola Iarocci</title>
    <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/tags/events/</link>
    <description>Recent content in events on Nicola Iarocci</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <copyright>Produced / Written / Maintained by [Nicola Iarocci](/) since 2010</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 31 Jul 2023 07:05:25 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://nicolaiarocci.com/tags/events/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Events 0.5 released</title>
      <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/events-0.5-released/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 31 Jul 2023 07:05:25 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nicolaiarocci.com/events-0.5-released/</guid>
      <description>Today I released Events 0.5. Thanks to Cailean Parker&amp;rsquo;s contribution, we added support for the __getitem__ dunder (aka Python magic method.) This allows the calling of events from strings, thus enabling dynamic events. For instance:
events = Events(tuple(f&amp;#34;on_{i}&amp;#34; for i in range(5))) for i in range(5): events[f&amp;#34;on_{i}&amp;#34;](i) The C# language provides a handy way to declare, subscribe to and fire events. In C#, an event is a &amp;ldquo;slot&amp;rdquo; to which callback functions (event handlers) can be attached - a process referred to as subscribing to an event.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Today I released <a href="https://pypi.org/project/Events/0.5/">Events 0.5</a>. Thanks to <a href="https://github.com/CaileanMParker">Cailean
Parker</a>&rsquo;s contribution, we added support for the <code>__getitem__</code> dunder (aka Python
magic method.) This allows the calling of events from strings, thus enabling dynamic events. For instance:</p>
<div class="highlight"><pre tabindex="0" style="background-color:#fff;-moz-tab-size:4;-o-tab-size:4;tab-size:4;"><code class="language-fallback" data-lang="fallback"><span style="display:flex;"><span>events = Events(tuple(f&#34;on_{i}&#34; for i in range(5)))
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>for i in range(5):
</span></span><span style="display:flex;"><span>    events[f&#34;on_{i}&#34;](i)
</span></span></code></pre></div><p>The C# language provides a handy way to declare, subscribe to and fire events. In C#, an event is a &ldquo;slot&rdquo; to which
callback functions (event handlers) can be attached - a process referred to as subscribing to an event. <em>Events</em> adds
this mechanism to Python. It originated as a side experiment (I was a C# transfugee then) that I later adopted as an
<a href="https://github.com/pyeve/eve">Eve</a> dependency. It slowly got some traction besides my projects. Read more on the project&rsquo;s <a href="https://github.com/pyeve/events">GitHub
page</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>In-person vs. online events</title>
      <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/in-person-vs.-online-events/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 01 May 2022 07:05:25 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nicolaiarocci.com/in-person-vs.-online-events/</guid>
      <description>Last week, thanks to [Andrea Verlicchi][1][^7]&amp;rsquo;s effort, we ran the first in-person [DevRomagna][2] event since 2019. We did some meetups during the pandemic, some in 2020 and a couple in 2022, but they were all online.
In theory, online meetups and DevRomagna are a match made in heaven. The [Romagna region][3] consists of small same-size towns scattered in the vast countryside. To accommodate this, and in an attempt to encourage varied participation, DevRomagna has always been a roaming meetup.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Last week, thanks to [Andrea Verlicchi][1][^7]&rsquo;s effort, we ran the first
in-person [DevRomagna][2] event since 2019. We did some meetups during the
pandemic, some in 2020 and a couple in 2022, but they were all online.</p>
<p>In theory, online meetups and DevRomagna are a match made in heaven. The
[Romagna region][3] consists of small same-size towns scattered in the vast
countryside. To accommodate this, and in an attempt to encourage varied
participation, DevRomagna has always been a roaming meetup. We might be in one
place one month, and then, next month, we will likely move to another town.
With online meetups, attendance doesn&rsquo;t have to commit to a commute saving
time and money and allowing everyone to participate in events that would
otherwise be too far away.</p>
<p>But there&rsquo;s value in commitment. The other day, we gathered in a new cozy
venue ([Ca&rsquo; Vaina][4][^6], a municipality-run youth center and coworking space)
where my friend [Gabriele Santomaggio][5] talked about Kubernetes, service mesh
and isolation techniques he and his colleagues adopt at Vmware. After the talk,
some of us went for dinner in a nearby pizzeria. The pizza was good, and the
craft beer was great. We talked about many things like our jobs, our favorite
developer tools and languages, and all the nerdy stuff you&rsquo;d imagine.
Suggestions for new original presentations were thrown around, which is always
good. Most importantly, I got to know new people, including Ugo, a fellow
[Microsoft MVP][8] from my area whom I somehow managed not to meet in all these
years. With Ugo, we are now planning a few hopefully engaging dotnet-centered
events.</p>
<p>All in all, it was a pleasant, fruitful evening spent with like-minded
individuals. We could have done an online event with, probably, a higher
attendance. I would&rsquo;ve saved some money and time (Imola, the town where the
meetup took place, is a half-hour drive, which includes a highway toll), but
I wouldn&rsquo;t get to meet Ugo at the table or see Gabriele after two years of
pandemic-inflicted hiatus.</p>
<p>More than one interested in the event asked if we would stream it, and my
answer was no for several reasons. I suspect that in-person attendance would
dwindle if we&rsquo;d stream our events, as we&rsquo;d be effectively discouraging active
participation. Also, it wouldn&rsquo;t be fair to the people who make an effort and
come to the venue. Recording the session and streaming them later might be an
option, but this would discourage live participation too. So, for the time
being, whenever possible, DevRomagna will stay true to its roots and remain
a live event. There might be exceptions, like if we have a foreign or far-away
guest or can&rsquo;t find a proper venue.</p>
<p>We&rsquo;re a local meetup, and &ldquo;local&rdquo; hardly conjugates with &ldquo;online.&rdquo;</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Real Life .NET Cross Platform</title>
      <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/real-life-net-cross-platform/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Mar 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nicolaiarocci.com/real-life-net-cross-platform/</guid>
      <description>There is a new episode up at Channel9 TecHeroes. It is called Real Life .NET Cross Platform and it is about developing production-ready, cross-platform applications with today’s .NET. In the interview we talk about SimpleCache, an asynchronous, permanent and cross-platform key-value object cache powered by SQLite3. The project is still a work in progress so there is no NuGet package available yet, but it is quite usable already. The talk slides are also available.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>There is a new episode up at Channel9 TecHeroes. It is called <a href="https://channel9.msdn.com/Shows/TecHeroes/TecHeroes-Real-Life-Net-Cross-Platform">Real Life .NET Cross Platform</a> and it is about developing production-ready, cross-platform applications with today’s .NET. In the interview we talk about <a href="https://github.com/CIR2000/Amica.vNext.SimpleCache">SimpleCache</a>, an asynchronous, permanent and cross-platform key-value object cache powered by SQLite3. The project is still a work in progress so there is no NuGet package available yet, but it is quite usable already. The <a href="https://speakerdeck.com/nicola/real-life-net-cross-platform">talk slides</a> are also available.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>CoderDojo interview at Channel 9</title>
      <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/my-coderdojo-interview-at-chennel-9-techeroes/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Mar 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nicolaiarocci.com/my-coderdojo-interview-at-chennel-9-techeroes/</guid>
      <description>I was recently interviewed at Channel 9 TecHeroes. Topic was CoderDojo, the network of free computer programming clubs for young people. The show is run by Microsoft Italy, so the interview is in Italian. Enjoy the show.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I was recently interviewed at Channel 9 TecHeroes. Topic was CoderDojo, the network of free computer programming clubs for young people. The show is run by Microsoft Italy, so the interview is in Italian. <a href="https://channel9.msdn.com/Shows/TecHeroes/TecHeroes-CoderDojo-Coding-Club-for-Kids">Enjoy the show</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>MongoDB Masters Summit 2013</title>
      <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/mongodb-masters-summit-2013/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Jun 2013 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nicolaiarocci.com/mongodb-masters-summit-2013/</guid>
      <description>I’m just back from the MongoDB Masters Summit hosted by 10Gen in New York City. In just a couple days I was given the opportunity to meet and share knowledge (and fun!) with amazingly talented minds coming from all over the world. I’m back with literally dozen new ideas opportunities and concepts, on which I’ll need to elaborate a little bit. While I cannot comment on the many things the smart minds at 10Gen are working on, rest assured that the future of MongoDB is looking great and brighter than ever.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I’m just back from the <!-- raw HTML omitted -->MongoDB Masters<!-- raw HTML omitted --> Summit hosted by 10Gen in New York City. In just a couple days I was given the opportunity to meet and share knowledge (and fun!) with amazingly talented minds coming from all over the world. I’m back with literally dozen new ideas opportunities and concepts, on which I’ll need to elaborate a little bit. While I cannot comment on the many things the smart minds at 10Gen are working on, rest assured that the future of MongoDB is looking great and brighter than ever.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
