<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>privacy on Nicola Iarocci</title>
    <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/tags/privacy/</link>
    <description>Recent content in privacy on Nicola Iarocci</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 01 Apr 2021 07:05:25 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://nicolaiarocci.com/tags/privacy/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>The Hitchhiker’s Guide to Online Anonymity</title>
      <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/the-hitchhikers-guide-to-online-anonymity/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Apr 2021 07:05:25 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nicolaiarocci.com/the-hitchhikers-guide-to-online-anonymity/</guid>
      <description>This is a maintained technical guide that aims to provide introduction to various online tracking techniques, online id verification techniques and guidance to creating and maintaining (truly) anonymous online identities including social media accounts safely and legally. No pre-requisites besides English reading are required.
At a glance, I suspect most people will be tempted to dismiss The Hitchhiker&amp;rsquo;s Guide to Online Anonymity as borderline paranoia. But make no mistake, it is a great resource.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<blockquote>
<p>This is a maintained technical guide that aims to provide introduction to
various online tracking techniques, online id verification techniques and
guidance to creating and maintaining (truly) anonymous online identities
including social media accounts safely and legally. No pre-requisites besides
English reading are required.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>At a glance, I suspect most people will be tempted to dismiss <a href="https://anonymousplanet.org/index.html">The Hitchhiker&rsquo;s
Guide to Online Anonymity</a> as borderline paranoia. But make no mistake, it
is a great resource. Granted, not everyone on the Internet is interested in
anonymous identities (I am not) or concerned about NSA or the Mossad hunting
them down. People have different threat levels.</p>
<p>Ideally, however, everyone should have a basic understanding of how his/her
activities can be tracked down on the Internet. The Hitchhiker&rsquo;s Guide does
a great job at panning out of all that. Armed with this kind of knowledge, we
can then decide our threat level and act accordingly. The website is also
chocked-full of links to valuable resources.</p>
<p><em>Subscribe to the <a href="https://nicolaiarocci.substack.com">newsletter</a>, the <a href="https://nicolaiarocci.com/index.xml">RSS feed</a>, or follow @<a href="http://twitter.com/nicolaiarocci">nicolaiarocci</a> on Twitter</em></p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
