<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>art on Nicola Iarocci</title>
    <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/tags/art/</link>
    <description>Recent content in art on Nicola Iarocci</description>
    <image>
      <title>Nicola Iarocci</title>
      <url>https://nicolaiarocci.com/images/avatar.png</url>
      <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/images/avatar.png</link>
    </image>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <copyright>Produced / Written / Maintained by [Nicola Iarocci](/) since 2010</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 18 May 2023 07:05:25 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://nicolaiarocci.com/tags/art/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Tiny electronic desktop sculptures</title>
      <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/tiny-electronic-desktop-sculptures/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 18 May 2023 07:05:25 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nicolaiarocci.com/tiny-electronic-desktop-sculptures/</guid>
      <description>Adorable, functional, often internet-connected desktop bots like those below are hand-crafted by Mohit Bhoite in San Francisco, California.
It pleasantly surprised me that they&amp;rsquo;re built as a purely artistic expression. All sculptures (as Mohit rightfully refers to them) are unique and not for sale. Check them all out on [his website][1] ([via][2]).</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Adorable, functional, often internet-connected desktop bots like those below are hand-crafted by Mohit Bhoite in San
Francisco, California.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" src="/images/bhoite-sculptures-01.jpg" alt=""  />

<img loading="lazy" src="/images/bhoite-sculptures-02.jpg" alt=""  />

It pleasantly surprised me that they&rsquo;re built as a purely artistic expression. All sculptures (as Mohit rightfully refers
to them) are unique and not for sale. Check them all out on [his website][1] <em>([via][2])</em>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Book Review: Proud tobea Flyer</title>
      <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/book-review-proud-tobea-flyer/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 28 Aug 2021 07:05:25 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nicolaiarocci.com/book-review-proud-tobea-flyer/</guid>
      <description>I happened across this book by pure chance. After having ice cream in our favourite place in Milano Marittima, my wife and I visited a small street market with all kinds of booths. Of course, there was a used book stand toward which I immediately gravitated. A quick scan revealed nothing of interest, so I moved along. But Serena, who arrived at the booth moments after I left, knew more. A simple, no-frills, cardboard-covered book which carried a giant PROUD 2BEA FLYER title on the spine caught her attention.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I happened across this book by pure chance. After having ice cream in our
favourite place in Milano Marittima, my wife and I visited a small street
market with all kinds of booths. Of course, there was a used book stand toward
which I immediately gravitated. A quick scan revealed nothing of interest, so
I moved along. But Serena, who arrived at the booth moments after I left, knew
more. A simple, no-frills, cardboard-covered book which carried a giant PROUD
2BEA FLYER title on the spine caught her attention. As she opened it and
flipped through the pages, she immediately knew this was a unique item I would
love to have, so she bought it (for cheap!) along with another one, then let it
slip into a shopping bag, and then reached an unaware me.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" src="/images/proudtobeaflyer1.jpg#right" alt="Proud 2bea flyer sample 1"  />

When I spotted the book lying in the bag, I inquired about it. Serena took it
out of the bag and handed it over to me with a smile. Imagine my surprise,
amazement and gratitude when I started browsing through hundreds of beautiful
works of art, all in the form of club flyers from all ages and musical genres.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>In what can best be described a well of hip Club Culture Graphics, Proud
2 B a Flyer rounds up the most exciting party announcements made for the
street. Before the explosion of popular musical forms in the past 40 years
art associated with music has been in corporate hands, with music companies
and commercial artists, but the club flyer has changed all that. The
evolution of the club flyer mirrors the musical movements that have used its
simple direct from to capture the imagination of their audiences. The early
techno scene employed flyers to great effect and diverse musical scenes
caught on quickly. Proud 2BEA Flyer brilliantly documents the flyer stylings
of the electronica scene and also includes special sections featuring Jazz,
Hip Hop and Brazilian music. Other fascinating selections are found in
chapters such as Drawing, Series, Unusual Shapes and Regular Nights. (<a href="https://www.hoepli.it/libro/proud-2bea-flyer/9788886416474.html">source</a>)</p>
</blockquote>
<p><img loading="lazy" src="/images/proudtobeaflyer2.jpg#right" alt="Proud 2bea flyer sample 2"  />

And indeed, this is an excellent collection of inspiring, mesmerizing works[^1].
No text, just flyers. I have never been much of a  clubbing person, but
I always followed the music, of course, and was fascinated by the graphical
world around it. This book brings back memories of an age now gone when there
were no smartphones, and you only happened to know about an event when and if
you were lucky enough to be in the right place at the right time, to have
a chance to come across one of these street flyers.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
