<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>travel on Nicola Iarocci</title>
    <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/tags/travel/</link>
    <description>Recent content in travel on Nicola Iarocci</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <copyright>Produced / Written / Maintained by [Nicola Iarocci](/) since 2010</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 23 Aug 2021 07:05:25 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://nicolaiarocci.com/tags/travel/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Travel is no cure for the mind</title>
      <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/travel-is-no-cure-for-the-mind/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Aug 2021 07:05:25 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nicolaiarocci.com/travel-is-no-cure-for-the-mind/</guid>
      <description>I stumbled upon a personal growth article this weekend, and that&amp;rsquo;s odd because I tend to stay clear from such things. Yet I found it quite relevant, so much that I thought I would [share it][1] (the delivery is also amusing, which is something new for this kind of content).
It’s just another day… and you’re just doing what you need to do. You’re getting things done, and the day moves forward in this continuous sequence of checklists, actions, and respites.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I stumbled upon a personal growth article this weekend, and that&rsquo;s odd because
I tend to stay clear from such things. Yet I found it quite relevant, so much
that I thought I would [share it][1] (the delivery is also amusing, which is
something new for this kind of content).</p>
<blockquote>
<p>It’s just another day… and you’re just doing what you need to do. You’re
getting things done, and the day moves forward in this continuous sequence of
checklists, actions, and respites. But at various moments of your routine,
you pause and take a good look at your surroundings. The scenes of your
everyday life. The blur of this all-too-familiar film. And you can’t help but
to wonder… If there is more to it all. For some reason — this country, this
city, this neighborhood, this particular street — is the place you are living
a majority of your life in. And it is this thought that allows a daydream to
seep in. You start thinking of all the other places you could be in this
world. Or more accurately, all the places you’d rather be in. Somewhere more
exciting. Somewhere new. Somewhere that can provide experiences that are
foreign to you.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>While I agree with the article, I&rsquo;d also mention that travel or putting some
distance from the Box of Daily Experience, as the author calls it, is a great
way to appreciate what we leave behind; to re-evaluate it from a different
perspective.</p>
<p>As I read the article, I kept thinking, this is not particularly original;
I read something like this before. Then, by the end of the piece, a note tells
us that the text is, in fact, an adaptation of Seneca&rsquo;s letter to Lucilius on
the subject of travel. Seneca&rsquo;s moral letters to Lucilius are just pure
awesomeness.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
