<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>apennine mountains on Nicola Iarocci</title>
    <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/tags/apennine-mountains/</link>
    <description>Recent content in apennine mountains on Nicola Iarocci</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- 0.121.1</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <copyright>Produced / Written / Maintained by Nicola Iarocci since 2010</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 16 Nov 2024 09:06:23 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://nicolaiarocci.com/tags/apennine-mountains/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>From Corniolo to Passo Braccina via Valpisella</title>
      <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/from-corniolo-to-passo-braccina-via-valpisella/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 16 Nov 2024 09:06:23 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nicolaiarocci.com/from-corniolo-to-passo-braccina-via-valpisella/</guid>
      <description>I took a daily hike in my beloved Apennine Mountains a few weeks ago. One of my favourite motorcycling routes is the narrow, engaging, panoramic road that unites Corniolo in the Bidente Valley with Marradi and the Mugello area via the Braccina Pass. I always wanted to return and hike through it; the moment had come.
One of my favourite motorcycling routes is the narrow, engaging, panoramic road that unites Corniolo in the Bidente Valley with Marradi and the Mugello area via the Braccina Pass.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I took a daily hike in my beloved Apennine Mountains a few weeks ago. One of my favourite motorcycling routes is the narrow, engaging, panoramic road that unites Corniolo in the Bidente Valley with Marradi and the Mugello area via the Braccina Pass. I always wanted to return and hike through it; the moment had come.</p>
<p>One of my favourite motorcycling routes is the narrow, engaging, panoramic road that unites Corniolo in the Bidente Valley with Marradi and the Mugello area via the Braccina Pass. I always wanted to return and hike through it; finally, the moment had come.</p>
<p>It was an excellent circular tour that, to the merits of moderation-it is not too long, nor too strenuous, the ascent is always gradual, etc. - also combines the variety of the environment, shading from mixed mid-altitude broadleaf forests (hornbeams, oaks, ash, cherry, maple) to coniferous reforestations that in this case, with increasing age and size, have taken on a certain dignity.</p>
<p><a href="https://forlicesena.anpi.it/valpisella/">Valpisella</a> is a rural stone building dating back to 1872 and later reclaimed as a vacation home by the volunteer work of ANPI partisans. When I arrived, I could hear people enjoying their lunch inside. It&rsquo;s a nice place; unfortunately, I forgot to take a picture.</p>
<p>If hiked at a brisk pace, it might take only half a day, but with a few well-deserved stops and savouring the myriad details that the various seasons can offer, it fills the whole day without difficulty.</p>
<p>The Corniolo/Braccina route marked my first winter hike of the season. I recently realized that, to me, daily hikes are more accessible in the winter. In summer, I&rsquo;m usually too busy between motorcycling trips with the <a href="https://tomccitalia.org/">Club</a>, family matters, holidays and, since we live close by, going to the beach.</p>
<p>GPS track is available <a href="https://www.outdooractive.com/en/route/hiking-route/da-corniolo-al-passo-braccina-via-valpisella/284294599/">here</a>.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" src="/images/corniolo-braccina1.jpg" alt="From Corniolo to Passo Braccina"  />

<img loading="lazy" src="/images/corniolo-braccina3.jpg" alt="From Corniolo to Passo Braccina"  />

<img loading="lazy" src="/images/corniolo-braccina2.jpg" alt="From Corniolo to Passo Braccina"  />
</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Toschi Hermitage</title>
      <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/the-toschi-hermitage/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 02 Jun 2024 12:26:25 +0200</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nicolaiarocci.com/the-toschi-hermitage/</guid>
      <description>I went on a motorcycle and hiking trip yesterday. It was a glorious day, albeit windy, which helped keep the temperature chill. Mixing hiking with motorcycling is something I love, as it combines two of my hobbies. However, it requires some careful planning. I still want to wear full safety gear on the bike but not take any of that with me as I walk in the wilderness, where I&amp;rsquo;ll be in hiking gear instead.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I went on a motorcycle and hiking trip yesterday. It was a glorious day, albeit windy, which helped keep the temperature chill.  Mixing hiking with motorcycling is something I love, as it combines two of my hobbies. However, it requires some careful planning. I still want to wear full safety gear on the bike but not take any of that with me as I walk in the wilderness, where I&rsquo;ll be in hiking gear instead.</p>
<p>The loop tour from the Montone River Valley reaches the watershed ridge overlooking the Acquacheta basin and then the main Apennine ridge at over 1,000 meters. From an environmental point of view, it is worth noting the constant presence of woods, first of oak and hornbeam, then of beech; the latter, with recent conversions to tall trees from coppice, have largely regained an appearance closer to naturalness. From a historical point of view, the itinerary is characterized by access to the very ancient (11th century) Hermitage of the Toschi or Tusci, currently being restored to be used as a farm and accommodation facility that gives hospitality to hikers, still very suggestive for its superb isolation and position set among the meadows at the top of the valley of Fosso Pian di Soia.</p>
<p>I risked losing the path when, just near the Hermitage, I spotted a hare a few steps away. She scampered unhurriedly away under my gaze as I was walking and not paying too much attention to the path, which seemed obvious. I missed a detour, and I recovered shortly after. Just before the hare, I kicked a harmless snake who got more scared than I did. It ran away, disappearing into knee-high grass.</p>
<p>When I returned to the bike, since it was still early, I decided to go up to the Muraglione Pass, descend to Tuscany, and return via the Tre Faggi Pass, Permilcuore and Predappio. It always strikes me to see tourists (alas, many motorcyclists) stopping at the cemetery in Predappio, presumably to visit Mussolini&rsquo;s grave.</p>
<p>I published a short <a href="https://vimeo.com/952806475">video</a> on Vimeo<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1</a></sup>; GPX track and some photos are available <a href="https://www.outdooractive.com/en/route/hiking-route/province-of-florence/eremo-deitoschi/293755434/?share=%7Ezywxwsim%244osseuny">here</a>.</p>

<div style="padding:56.25% 0 0 0;position:relative;"><iframe src="https://player.vimeo.com/video/952806475?badge=0&amp;autopause=0&amp;player_id=0&amp;app_id=58479" frameborder="0" allow="autoplay; fullscreen; picture-in-picture; clipboard-write" style="position:absolute;top:0;left:0;width:100%;height:100%;" title="Eremo dei Toschi"></iframe></div><script src="https://player.vimeo.com/api/player.js"></script>

<figure>
    <img loading="lazy" src="/images/eremo-dei-toschi2.jpg"
         alt="Beech forests are a characteristic feature of this area of the Apennines"/> <figcaption>
            <p>Beech forests are a characteristic feature of this area of the Apennines</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<figure>
    <img loading="lazy" src="/images/eremo-dei-toschi1.jpg"
         alt="By now, at the end of the tour, the clearing with the Toschi Hermitage stands directly in front of us."/> <figcaption>
            <p>By now, at the end of the tour, the clearing with the Toschi Hermitage stands directly in front of us.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
<hr>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1">
<p>It&rsquo;s embedded, but I discovered that email subscribers don&rsquo;t get to see embedded resources.&#160;<a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
</ol>
</div>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>From Bocconi to the Twin Mountains</title>
      <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/from-bocconi-to-the-twin-mountains/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 18 Mar 2024 15:30:33 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nicolaiarocci.com/from-bocconi-to-the-twin-mountains/</guid>
      <description>Yesterday I went for a walk in the mountains. This tour starts from Bocconi (on the road to Muraglione Pass) and the nice humpback bridge that is just below the village (I think it&amp;rsquo;s called &amp;ldquo;della Brusia&amp;rdquo;).
Ponte della Brusia, Bocconi (FC)
It is a nice hike, with the ascent that becomes quite challenging in the final part, towards the ridge tops, which, once reached, you&amp;rsquo;ll follow for a long time, partially on a forest road, before plunging back downhill, initially following a lovely descending ridge da makes most of the descent quite pleasant.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Yesterday I went for a walk in the mountains. This tour starts from
<a href="https://maps.app.goo.gl/BSJnhQBuqgXFN2sA8">Bocconi</a> (on the road to Muraglione
Pass) and the nice humpback bridge that is just below the village (I think it&rsquo;s
called &ldquo;della Brusia&rdquo;).</p>
<figure>
    <img loading="lazy" src="/images/bocconi3.jpg"
         alt="Ponte della Brusia, Bocconi (FC)"/> <figcaption>
            <p>Ponte della Brusia, Bocconi (FC)</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>It is a nice hike, with the ascent that becomes quite challenging in the final
part, towards the ridge tops, which, once reached, you&rsquo;ll follow for a long
time, partially on a forest road, before plunging back downhill, initially
following a lovely descending ridge da makes most of the descent quite pleasant.
During the ascent, several detours were necessary to get around the landslides
that originated during the infamous May floods (there are still several traffic
lights on the roadway leading up from Forlì, all due to the restoration works
following the flood). Hats off to the volunteers who maintain the trail: they
have had to work hard this year. At some point, they had to &lsquo;dug out&rsquo; complete
new sections to get around the more enormous landslides.</p>
<p>Primroses, wild saffron, and buttercup suggest that, yes, we are indeed entering
spring. All of this botanic expertise is due to
<a href="https://plantnet.org/en/">PlantNet</a>, the app I installed the other day, which
works well, except that it has to be online, which is only rarely possible on
the trail. Fortunately, it can also be used on previously taken photos, which I
did once I was back in Bocconi. I also installed an app to recognize birdsong;
it&rsquo;s called <a href="https://merlin.allaboutbirds.org">Merlin Bird ID</a>, received a lot
of praise, and should work offline, but I have yet to try it.</p>
<figure>
    <img loading="lazy" src="/images/bocconi1.jpg"
         alt="As is often the case in the Apennines, rural ruins are encountered on the trail."/> <figcaption>
            <p>As is often the case in the Apennines, rural ruins are encountered on the trail.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>The best moment was the twenty or so minutes I spent lying down to rest at the
highest point before embarking on the descent. I listened to the silence that
silence was not: the sounds of the forest, the birds, the wind, the heat of the
sun on my skin. My mind wanted to divert to new paths, and I tended to fall
asleep several times, but I consciously tried to bring my mind back to
listening. A meditation exercise that restored my energy levels: I felt
recharged and rested when I got up.</p>
<figure>
    <img loading="lazy" src="/images/bocconi2.jpg"
         alt="A warm day for mid-March, and breezy with partly cloudy skies."/> <figcaption>
            <p>A warm day for mid-March, and breezy with partly cloudy skies.</p>
        </figcaption>
</figure>

<p>At the start, be careful not to take the trail in reverse (as I initially did):
after crossing the beautiful humpback bridge known as the Brusia, do not take
the trail directly in front of you, but turn sharply left, walk about 30 meters
above the Montone river, then take the trail to the right, marked &ldquo;Valbura&rdquo;.</p>
<p>GPX track and some photos <a href="https://www.outdooractive.com/en/route/hiking-route/province-of-forli-cesena/da-bocconi-verso-i-monti-gemelli/284291423/">here</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Monte Tiravento</title>
      <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/monte-tiravento/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 19 Feb 2024 10:02:48 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nicolaiarocci.com/monte-tiravento/</guid>
      <description>Yesterday, I went on a hiking trip to Monte Tiravento. This majestic loop tour is uncommon compared to the classic woody image of the Parco Nazionale del Foreste Casentinesi, as it takes place mainly on aerial and partly even barren ridges, resulting in magnificent views. Compared to other variants I did in the past, this one starts at a high altitude, offering lower elevation differences.
It is inadvisable on the hottest summer days when the nearby forests offer more cover from the scorching sun, but it is a real treat throughout the rest of the year.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Yesterday, I went on a hiking trip to Monte Tiravento. This majestic loop tour
is uncommon compared to the classic woody image of the Parco Nazionale del
Foreste Casentinesi, as it takes place mainly on aerial and partly even barren
ridges, resulting in magnificent views. Compared to other variants I did in the
past, this one starts at a high altitude, offering lower elevation differences.</p>
<p>It is inadvisable on the hottest summer days when the nearby forests offer more
cover from the scorching sun, but it is a real treat throughout the rest of the
year.</p>
<p>Reasons for environmental interest, other than in individual uncommon botanical
species (at least red juniper and turkey oak), lie mainly in the wild valleys
overlooked by what is the &ldquo;turnaround&rdquo; as well as the highest point of the
itinerary, Monte Tiravento (and even the name testifies to the splendid
isolation of the site) and in the beautiful ruin of the medieval Montalto Tower.
A final appendage to see monumental oaks further embellishes the hike. I met
several groups on the trail, and we&rsquo;re in February, so I&rsquo;d expect these ridges
to be crowded in spring and autumn.</p>
<p>For GPS track, photos, and stats <a href="https://www.outdooractive.com/en/route/hiking-route/province-of-forli-cesena/monte-tiravento/287243288/">click here</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Rio Petroso</title>
      <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/rio-petroso/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 29 Jan 2024 09:44:15 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nicolaiarocci.com/rio-petroso/</guid>
      <description>Wet, cold, and foggy winter day in the plains, I knew it would be splendid in the highlands. At the last minute and even a little late by my usual safety standards, I packed my backpack and dashed into the hills. To avoid being late or having to return in the dark, I didn&amp;rsquo;t even stop eating, munching on two bars as I walked, but it was worth it.
Rio Petroso is a rather complex and articulated circular tour, with frequent environmental changes, configuring itself among the most arid of the entire Park territory; I wouldn&amp;rsquo;t do this route at the height of summer.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Wet, cold, and foggy winter day in the plains, I knew it would be splendid in
the highlands. At the last minute and even a little late by my usual safety
standards, I packed my backpack and dashed into the hills. To avoid being late
or having to return in the dark, I didn&rsquo;t even stop eating, munching on two bars
as I walked, but it was worth it.</p>
<p>Rio Petroso is a rather complex and articulated circular tour, with frequent
environmental changes, configuring itself among the most arid of the entire Park
territory; I wouldn&rsquo;t do this route at the height of summer.</p>
<p>Another peculiarity of this hike is the dense presence of ruined houses,
precious testimonies of the glorious Apennine civilization history that lasted
until the late 1960s, with the departure of the population to the valley floors
or, more often than not, the plains.</p>
<p>The geological peculiarity is constituted by the so-called &ldquo;Verghereto marls&rdquo;
(named after the typical locality where they, in fact, overbearingly
characterize the landscape), which appear especially along the ridge of Rio
Petroso: they give rise to a barren environment, with erosion phenomena
reminiscent of those of gullies but with, in addition, an almost exotic
suggestion in their lunar nudity.</p>
<p>When I got to the car, I realized I had forgotten the headlights on. It&rsquo;s a good
thing I hurried on the route (and recently changed the battery), or I would have
been stuck there, 10 km from civilization, with no phone signal—an adventure I
gladly spared myself.</p>
<p>GPS track, map, pics and all the frills are <a href="https://out.ac/IPx3WT">here</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The wilderness of Poggio Montironi</title>
      <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/the-wilderness-of-poggio-montironi/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Dec 2023 07:05:25 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nicolaiarocci.com/the-wilderness-of-poggio-montironi/</guid>
      <description>Yesterday was a beautiful, sunny, cold winter Sunday. I felt like going out and enjoying nature, so I took a solo hike in the Foreste Casentinesi National Park, about an hour&amp;rsquo;s drive from home.
This one marks my very first technology-assisted hiking adventure. It may seem weird for someone who&amp;rsquo;s been hiking for so long, is a notorious geek and is a professional computer programmer to have never used technology before.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Yesterday was a beautiful, sunny, cold winter Sunday. I felt like going out and
enjoying nature, so I took a solo hike in the Foreste Casentinesi National Park,
about an hour&rsquo;s drive from home.</p>
<p>This one marks my very first technology-assisted hiking adventure. It may seem
weird for someone who&rsquo;s been hiking for so long, is a notorious geek and is a
professional computer programmer to have never used technology before. A trail
map and sometimes a compass were all I was used to, and deliberately. I wanted
to avoid technology in this aspect of my life. I welcomed the orientation
challenges and superbly looked down at the crowds of phone-smartwatch-compulsive
hikers I met on the route. Alas, 2023 was the year I surrendered my motorcycling
habits to intercom systems and GPS navigation, and that spoiled me. In a couple
of situations yesterday, the app spared me some trouble by warning me of the
wrong direction I was going. Nothing major. I would&rsquo;ve realized the error and
backtracked, but being these the shortest and coldest days of the year, I
appreciated not risking getting caught by dusk. Also, I found that I can turn on
voice-assisted navigation as I do on my motorcycle, and that&rsquo;s nice (albeit
surreal - walking alone in the wilderness, miles from anybody, with a voice
coming out of nowhere and whispering when I should take turns on the trail): it
avoids looking at the cellphone all the time so I can stay focused on the
experience even more, I suspect, than before when the don&rsquo;t-get-lost alarm bell
was constantly ringing in the back of my head.</p>
<p>And then, of course, there&rsquo;s the selfish and ego-boosting pleasure of sharing
your achievement with the masses. I mean, <a href="https://out.ac/IPVine">look at this
beauty</a>!</p>
<p>The Poggio Montironi hike was an excellent circular tour, advisable all year
round and especially suggestive in winter because of the barren and scenic ridge
(perhaps too sunny in midsummer) that culminates with the more than 1,000 meters
of Poggio Montironi. Near the destination stands an always-open bivouac that can
be useful as shelter. At the same time, the ancient castle of Spescia, reduced
to ruins but with considerable environmental value, on the return ridge gives
the hike additional reasons for interest.</p>
<p>Caution on the descent: Two or three turns could be more noticeable, but they
are well reported in the GPX track. A fallen tree (surmountable) interrupts the
trail near the ford of the Rio Sasso.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>I met with the wolves</title>
      <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/i-met-with-the-wolves/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Oct 2021 07:05:25 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nicolaiarocci.com/i-met-with-the-wolves/</guid>
      <description>I sit under a wild apple tree at the edge of the clearing. Like a plant, I absorb the mild October sun. At the same time, I attentively listen to the sounds of the forest. Suddenly I hear a stomping of dry leaves about twenty meters ahead of me, slightly to my right. A wolf emerges out of the thicket. He stops for a moment, glances around, then starts crossing the clearing.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I sit under a wild apple tree at the edge of the clearing. Like a plant,
I absorb the mild October sun. At the same time, I attentively listen to the
sounds of the forest. Suddenly I hear a stomping of dry leaves about twenty
meters ahead of me, slightly to my right. A wolf emerges out of the thicket. He
stops for a moment, glances around, then starts crossing the clearing. A few
moments and another wolf appears. After a brief pause, he follows his pal. They
parade right in front of me, sinuous, silent, and feral. They do not see or
hear me, and yet I am right there, by their side, in plain sight<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1</a></sup>. It is all
over in a few seconds. The couple leaves the clearing and disappears into the
forest. I stand sitting there, shocked and in complete awe.</p>
<p>Incredibly, the scene above is real. It happened to me last Sunday, in the wild
Apennines, in a place I&rsquo;ve been visiting for years. I&rsquo;ve seen a lot of animals
there: wild boar, deer, badgers, foxes. I knew wolves frequent the area but
meeting them, in the plain day? No way. I dreamed about it, of course, but
never expected it would really happen.  I had goosebumps, and I still have them
now as I write this. I keep telling myself it&rsquo;s impossible. And yet, I have
photos on my cellphone. In the heat of the moment, I somehow managed to snap
a couple. My family confirms the wolves. It was not a dream.</p>
<div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
<hr>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1">
<p>In hindsight, I think that having been sitting there motionless and not producing any sound for a long time did the trick. By pure luck, I also happened to be downwind to them.
[rss]: <a href="https://nicolaiarocci.com/index.xml">https://nicolaiarocci.com/index.xml</a>
[tw]: <a href="http://twitter.com/nicolaiarocci">http://twitter.com/nicolaiarocci</a>
[nl]: <a href="https://buttondown.email/nicolaiarocci">https://buttondown.email/nicolaiarocci</a>&#160;<a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
</ol>
</div>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
