<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>windows11 on Nicola Iarocci</title>
    <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/tags/windows11/</link>
    <description>Recent content in windows11 on Nicola Iarocci</description>
    <image>
      <title>Nicola Iarocci</title>
      <url>https://nicolaiarocci.com/images/avatar.png</url>
      <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/images/avatar.png</link>
    </image>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <copyright>Produced / Written / Maintained by [Nicola Iarocci](/) since 2010</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 11 Dec 2021 07:05:25 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://nicolaiarocci.com/tags/windows11/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Migrating a Windows 10 VM to Windows 11 in Parallels Desktop: a story of TPM chips and BIOS upgrades</title>
      <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/migrating-a-windows-10-vm-to-windows-11-in-parallels-desktop-a-story-of-tpm-chips-and-bios-upgrades/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 11 Dec 2021 07:05:25 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nicolaiarocci.com/migrating-a-windows-10-vm-to-windows-11-in-parallels-desktop-a-story-of-tpm-chips-and-bios-upgrades/</guid>
      <description>This weekend assignment was to upgrade a couple of old Windows 10 VMs to Windows 11 in Parallels Desktop 17. I couldn&amp;rsquo;t do that right away because Windows Update was complaining about the lack of the TPM chip. A little research revealed that TPM chips only work on UEFI BIOS. To check which BIOS version was being used in my VMs, I used the msinfo32 (System Information) application. It showed the BIOS to be of &amp;ldquo;Legacy&amp;rdquo; type.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>This weekend assignment was to upgrade a couple of old Windows 10 VMs to
Windows 11 in Parallels Desktop 17. I couldn&rsquo;t do that right away because
Windows Update was complaining about the lack of the TPM chip. A little
research revealed that TPM chips only work on UEFI BIOS.  To check which BIOS
version was being used in my VMs, I used the msinfo32 (System Information)
application. It showed the BIOS to be of &ldquo;Legacy&rdquo; type. So my task was now to
switch it to UEFI.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" src="/images/windows10-bios-legacy-mode.png" alt="Windows 10 BIOS in Legacy  mode"  />
</p>
<p>I looked high and low with little luck. Parallels the product is incredible.
Not so much its documentation and online support.  At some point, I landed in
the Parallels forums, a vast ocean of scarcely useful threads from which
I usually try to stay the hell away. The Parallels personnel there has
a long-standing tendency to copy &amp; paste ready-made and irrelevant solutions.
Users are left to their own, and, luckily, one of them posted the <a href="https://forum.parallels.com/threads/process-for-converting-from-legacy-to-uefi-in-prep-for-win-11.354888/">perfect
solution</a> to my Legacy-to-UEFI BIOS migration problem. I am reposting it
here, with minor edits, for future reference (my future self <a href="https://nicolaiarocci.com/learn-in-public/">will be
grateful</a>):</p>
<ol>
<li>Back up your VM</li>
<li>Boot into your Windows 10 VM as usual</li>
<li>While holding down Shift key: Start -&gt; Power -&gt; Restart</li>
<li>Select Troubleshoot, then Advanced options</li>
<li>Select Command Prompt</li>
<li>Log in with your account and Microsoft password (not your pin)</li>
<li>Type: <code>mbr2gpt /validate</code> and hit return; this will check your hard disk</li>
<li>If there&rsquo;s a problem, type: <code>mbr2gpt /validate /allowFullOS</code> and hit return</li>
<li>Type <code>mbr2gpt /convert</code> and hit return. It will convert the MBR disk partition scheme to GUID. It might complain about WinRE or something, but generally, if it says &ldquo;conversion was a success,&rdquo; you can type <code>exit</code> and hit return to kill the command prompt and return to the advanced menu</li>
<li>Choose &ldquo;Turn off PC.&rdquo; You don&rsquo;t want to restart Windows yet</li>
<li>Find your VM file in the Finder, right-click on it, and choose: &ldquo;Show Package Contents.&rdquo;</li>
<li>Find the config.pvs file and open it with a text editor</li>
<li>Search for the section <code>&lt;Bios dyn_lists=&quot;&quot;&gt;</code></li>
<li>Change <code>&lt;EfiEnabled&gt;</code> from 0 to 1</li>
<li>Change <code>&lt;EfiSecureBoot&gt;</code> from 0 to 1</li>
<li>Save the file</li>
<li>Open the VM Configuration, go to the Hardware tab, click the &ldquo;+&rdquo;, and add the TPM Chip</li>
</ol>
<p>At this point you can run Windows 10 as you usually would. At fist launch,
right after the login, I got a critical error and a hard restart (the original
poster reported the same experience.) After that, the VM is stable. A quick
msinfo32 check confirms that the VM is now on UEFI BIOS.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" src="/images/windows10-bios-uefi-mode.png" alt="Windows 10 BIOS in UEFI mode"  />
</p>
<p>Should Windows Update still complain, that&rsquo;s probably because of the CPU
limitation check. You can disable it:</p>
<ol>
<li>Open the Registry Editor</li>
<li>Navigate to <code>HKEY_LOCAL_MACHINE\SYSTEM\Setup\MoSetup</code></li>
<li>Search for <code>AllowUpgradesWithUnsupportedTPMOrCPU</code></li>
<li>Change its value to 1</li>
<li>Restart the VM</li>
</ol>
<p>Personally, I did not need to alter the registry, and I got <em>very</em> old VMs to
upgrade. At the time of this writing, Windows 11 installation is at 94% and
I am confident it will be successful.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
