<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>happiness on Nicola Iarocci</title>
    <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/tags/happiness/</link>
    <description>Recent content in happiness on Nicola Iarocci</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 12 May 2021 07:05:25 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://nicolaiarocci.com/tags/happiness/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>The Grim Secret of Nordic Happiness</title>
      <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/the-grim-secret-of-nordic-happiness/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 12 May 2021 07:05:25 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nicolaiarocci.com/the-grim-secret-of-nordic-happiness/</guid>
      <description>For decades Scandinavian countries have been renowned for their educational systems, low levels of corruption, sustainable economy, social justice, overall quality of life. According to Jukka Savolainen on Slate, the reason why Finns have now been dominating the World Happiness Report four years in a row has little to do with these factors and more with their life expectations.
Savolainen perspective is interesting because he is a Finn living in the US.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>For decades Scandinavian countries have been renowned for their educational
systems, low levels of corruption, sustainable economy, social justice, overall
quality of life. According to <a href="https://slate.com/news-and-politics/2021/04/finland-happiness-lagom-hygge.html">Jukka Savolainen on Slate</a>, the reason why
Finns have now been dominating the World Happiness Report four years in a row
has little to do with these factors and more with their life expectations.</p>
<p>Savolainen perspective is interesting because he is a Finn living in the US. He
experienced the Scandinavian system first hand, then moved to a (very)
different culture.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>The Nordic ethos stands in particularly stark contrast to the American
culture characterized by &ldquo;extreme emphasis upon the accumulation of wealth as
a symbol of success,&rdquo; as observed by the sociologist Robert K. Merton in the
1930s.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>In comparing the different lifestyles, he also touches on the social
differences. Scandinavian people are not famous for their openness or the
quality of their small talk, that&rsquo;s for sure. I do admire their low-aspirations
attitude, which is well described in the article.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Moreover, they embrace a cultural orientation that sets realistic limits to
one&rsquo;s expectations for a good life. [&hellip;] People are socialized to believe
that what they have is as good as it gets—or close enough. This mindset
explains why Finns are the happiest people in the world despite living in
small apartments, earning modest incomes—with even more limited purchasing
power thanks to high prices and taxes—and, unlike Iceland, having never even
made it to the World Cup!</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I have always been fascinated by the North. When I went to Stockholm to present
at Pycon Sweden, I fell in love with the city. I was lucky, though. We were in
May, and the weather was beautiful all week. Daylight lasted until midnight. To
my enthusiasm, the locals objected I should come back in the winter season to
really appreciate what living in the North entails. As a Mediterranean guy,
I imagine I might soon feel the long for warmer climates and still, the dream
of moving North persists.</p>
<p><em>Subscribe to the <a href="https://nicolaiarocci.substack.com">newsletter</a>, the <a href="https://nicolaiarocci.com/index.xml">RSS feed</a>, or follow @<a href="http://twitter.com/nicolaiarocci">nicolaiarocci</a> on Twitter</em></p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
