<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>Reading on Nicola Iarocci</title>
    <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/tags/reading/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Reading on Nicola Iarocci</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- 0.143.1</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <copyright>Produced / Written / Maintained by Nicola Iarocci since 2010</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 22 Nov 2025 09:42:44 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://nicolaiarocci.com/tags/reading/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>People who no longer read as much as they used to</title>
      <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/people-who-no-longer-read-as-much-as-they-used-to/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 22 Nov 2025 09:42:44 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nicolaiarocci.com/people-who-no-longer-read-as-much-as-they-used-to/</guid>
      <description>&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The theory that people no longer read as much as they used to is put forward by people who no longer read as much as they used to.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ndash; &lt;a href=&#34;https://open.substack.com/pub/bastonate/p/sei-consigli-per-non-fare-un-soldo&#34;&gt;Francesco Farabegoli&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<blockquote>
<p>The theory that people no longer read as much as they used to is put forward by people who no longer read as much as they used to.</p></blockquote>
<p>&ndash; <a href="https://open.substack.com/pub/bastonate/p/sei-consigli-per-non-fare-un-soldo">Francesco Farabegoli</a></p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Three Good Books I Read in 2021</title>
      <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/three-good-books-i-read-in-2021/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 31 Dec 2021 07:05:25 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nicolaiarocci.com/three-good-books-i-read-in-2021/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This year I&amp;rsquo;ve read twenty-one books or 5903 pages. That&amp;rsquo;s fewer books than
last year (28 / 8064), the year before (25 / 8394), and the one before that (30
/ 8447). Heck, I must look back at 2014 to score a win in my very own yearly
reading challenge. What surprises me is not much the number of books but the
pages I read, which constitutes a &lt;a href=&#34;https://twitter.com/nicolaiarocci/status/1214857647314362368&#34;&gt;more relevant metric&lt;/a&gt;. Over the previous
three years, that number stayed firmly over 8k while dropping to 6k this year.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>This year I&rsquo;ve read twenty-one books or 5903 pages. That&rsquo;s fewer books than
last year (28 / 8064), the year before (25 / 8394), and the one before that (30
/ 8447). Heck, I must look back at 2014 to score a win in my very own yearly
reading challenge. What surprises me is not much the number of books but the
pages I read, which constitutes a <a href="https://twitter.com/nicolaiarocci/status/1214857647314362368">more relevant metric</a>. Over the previous
three years, that number stayed firmly over 8k while dropping to 6k this year.</p>
<p><img alt="My goodreads books stats for 2021" loading="lazy" src="/images/books-stats-2021-goodreads.png"></p>
<p>Should I be concerned? I don&rsquo;t know. No doubt I&rsquo;ve been super busy at work,
often feeling exhausted in the evening when I tend to read more. I suspect I&rsquo;ve
also been watching more TV than usual, probably due to the evening fatigue and
because I want to spend more time with Serena. The fact that I read more
non-fiction might play a role too. Fiction tends to be more addictive and more
inviting to the weary mind. We&rsquo;ll see what happens next year.</p>
<p>These are three books I especially enjoyed reading in 2021:</p>
<ul>
<li>
<p><em><a href="/book-review-we-have-always-lived-in-the-castle/">We Have Always Lived in the Castle</a></em>. This little Shirley Jackson
masterpiece stands out from my (admittedly small) 2021 fiction selection. Quoting
my own words from the review: &ldquo;This book is brilliant because it takes the canonical
witch/haunted house theme and flips it over, instantly reversing the
perspective. The story is told from within the house. Village folks are the bad
guys. Those who seem to be motivated by good intentions only fulfill their ego
or strive to behave with good manners, as society expects them to do. We cannot
help but feel at least a drop of compassion and sympathy for the devil.&rdquo;</p>
</li>
<li>
<p><em><a href="/book-review-endurance-shackletons-incredible-voyage/">Endurance. Shackleton&rsquo;s Incredible Voyage</a></em>. I&rsquo;ve read three maritime adventure
books this year, all excellent works. Alfred Lansing&rsquo;s report on Shackleton&rsquo;s
expedition is my pick because the story is outstanding and powerfully told.
&ldquo;Alfred Lansing has reconstructed all these events with great care, drawing
mainly on the many diaries kept by the crew and interviewing the few survivors
still alive. [&hellip;] the result is always smooth and dry, never yielding to
hyperbole or exaltation, always close to the facts, which on the other hand,
certainly do not need enrichment.&rdquo;</p>
</li>
<li>
<p><em><a href="/book-review-consider-the-lobster/">Consider the Lobster</a></em>. David Foster Wallace is one of my favorite authors and
this book does not delude. &ldquo;You may not have a strong interest in lobsters or
pornography, but the essays in this book are terrific.&rdquo;</p>
</li>
</ul>
<p>Honorable mention goes to  <em><a href="/book-review-about-the-meaning-of-life/">About the Meaning of Life</a></em>, <em><a href="/book-review-king-and-emperor-a-new-life-of-charlemagne/">King and
Emperor: A New Life of Charlemagne</a></em>, and <em><a href="/book-review-nomadland/">Nomadland</a></em>. See my <a href="/books-i-have-read/">Books
I Have Read</a> page for the list of books I read in 2021 and before.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Five Good Books I Read in 2020</title>
      <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/five-good-books-i-read-in-2020/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 04 Jan 2021 07:05:25 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nicolaiarocci.com/five-good-books-i-read-in-2020/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Here are five books I read in 2020 that I would recommend. I read several fine
books last year, so please check out my &lt;a href=&#34;https://nicolaiarocci.com/books-i-have-read/&#34;&gt;reading history&lt;/a&gt; if you are unsatisfied
with this selection.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mani%3A_Travels_in_the_Southern_Peloponnese&#34;&gt;Mani: Travels in the Southern Peloponnese&lt;/a&gt;, by &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Patrick_Leigh_Fermor&#34;&gt;Patrick Leigh
Fermor&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;. I love Patrick Leigh Fermor. Over the years, I read almost
everything he wrote. He has been described as &amp;ldquo;a cross between Indiana Jones,
James Bond, and Graham Greene,&amp;rdquo; and for a good reason. He bridges the genres of
adventure story, travel writing, and memoir to reveal an ancient world living
alongside the twentieth century. Here he carries the reader with him on his
journeys among the Greeks of the mountains, exploring their history and
time-honored lore. The Mani, at the tip of Greece&amp;rsquo;s-and Europe&amp;rsquo;s-southernmost
peninsula, is one of the most isolated regions of the world. Cut off from the
rest of the country by the high range of the Taygetus and hemmed in by the
Aegean and Ionian seas, it is a land where the past is still very much a part
of its people&amp;rsquo;s daily lives.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Here are five books I read in 2020 that I would recommend. I read several fine
books last year, so please check out my <a href="https://nicolaiarocci.com/books-i-have-read/">reading history</a> if you are unsatisfied
with this selection.</p>
<p><em><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mani%3A_Travels_in_the_Southern_Peloponnese">Mani: Travels in the Southern Peloponnese</a>, by <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Patrick_Leigh_Fermor">Patrick Leigh
Fermor</a></em>. I love Patrick Leigh Fermor. Over the years, I read almost
everything he wrote. He has been described as &ldquo;a cross between Indiana Jones,
James Bond, and Graham Greene,&rdquo; and for a good reason. He bridges the genres of
adventure story, travel writing, and memoir to reveal an ancient world living
alongside the twentieth century. Here he carries the reader with him on his
journeys among the Greeks of the mountains, exploring their history and
time-honored lore. The Mani, at the tip of Greece&rsquo;s-and Europe&rsquo;s-southernmost
peninsula, is one of the most isolated regions of the world. Cut off from the
rest of the country by the high range of the Taygetus and hemmed in by the
Aegean and Ionian seas, it is a land where the past is still very much a part
of its people&rsquo;s daily lives.</p>
<p><em>Bonus tip</em>. The book that got me hooked with Patrick Leigh Fermor is <em><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/A_Time_of_Gifts">A Time of
Gifts</a></em>, a memoir of the first part of his journey on foot across Europe,
from the Hook of Holland to Constantinople in 1933/34. A fascinating read.</p>
<p><em><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/In_Search_of_Lost_Time#Volume_One:_Swann's_Way">Swann&rsquo;s Way</a>, by <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Marcel_Proust">Marcel Proust</a></em>. This is the first volume of Marcel
Proust&rsquo;s <em>In Search of Lost Time</em>, arguably the twentieth century&rsquo;s finest novel.
Indeed, while reading the first part, a boy&rsquo;s impressions of his family and
neighbors, all brought dazzling back to life years later by the taste of
a madeleine, I could appreciate why Marcel Proust is considered the best writer
of all time. The second part, the short novel <em>Swann in Love</em>, &ldquo;an incomparable
study of sexual jealousy,&rdquo; which follows, is also excellent. I have to admit
I kept postponing this book basically for all my life, as I was intimidated by
its fame. I am glad I finally got to read it as a mature adult but make no
mistake, this book is a must-read, in due time, for any avid reader.</p>
<p><em><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Master_and_Margarita">The Master and Margarita</a>, by <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mikhail_Bulgakov">Mikhail Bulgakov</a></em>. An audacious
revision of Faust and Pontius Pilate&rsquo;s stories, <em>The Master and Margarita</em> is
recognized as one of the essential classics of modern Russian literature. I was
surprised by both the audacity and modernity of the story and Bulgakov&rsquo;s own
writing style. Of all the scenes, those that probably impressed me the most
were Satan&rsquo;s ball and Margarita&rsquo;s flight. <em>The Master and Margarita</em> is a true
masterpiece. With <em>Swann&rsquo;s Way</em>, it sits right there at the top of my classics
stack.</p>
<p><em><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Helgoland_(book)">Helgoland</a>, by <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Carlo_Rovelli">Carlo Rovelli</a></em>. Carlo Rovelli is a theoretical
physicist and writer. His work is mainly in quantum gravity, where he is among
the founders of the loop quantum gravity theory. In this book, Rovelli
recounts the story of what has been acknowledged as the most radical scientific
revolution of modern times: quantum physics. In June 1925, in Helgoland, a bare
and windswept isle in the North Sea, a 23 years old Werner Heisenberg started
it all. Since then, in almost one century, quantum physics revealed many
controversial if not disturbing new ideas, most of them confirmed over time,
leading to all kinds of technological innovations. I don&rsquo;t think this book has
been translated to languages other than Italian as of yet. By googling a little
bit around, I found English translations announced by Penguin and other
editors.</p>
<p><em><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/De_Brevitate_Vitae_%28Seneca%29">De Brevitate Vitae (On the Shortness of Life)</a>, by <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Seneca_the_Younger">Seneca</a></em>. I am
impressed by this short book. I expected it to be a challenging, hard descent
into the ancient philosopher&rsquo;s mind. It was a joyful read instead. Even today,
Seneca&rsquo;s writings offer potent insights into the art of living, the importance
of reason and morality and continue to provide profound guidance to many
through their eloquence, lucidity, and timeless wisdom.</p>
<h2 id="on-a-more-personal-note">On a more personal note</h2>
<p>I strive to read good books. Of course, defining what makes a good book is is
very subjective. In my case, good books challenge my understanding of the world
in which I live. That might sound too broad (and ambitious) of a goal, and
probably it is. I tend to read all kinds of different books: novels, essays,
classics, with non-fiction gravitating towards topics such as history, science,
and, only more recently, economy and finance. As you might have guessed from
the list above, lately, I have been reading classics a lot. I don&rsquo;t read too
many programming or computer science books. Not these days anyway. As I get
older, I prefer to distance myself from the topics I focus on at work all day
long.</p>
<p>Reading is my zen mode. I do other activities that achieve similar results,
such as walking, hiking, motorcycling and working out, but reading, I come to
recognize, reigns supreme. It&rsquo;s been with me since I was a kid and, also,
compared to the other activities, it is very affordable in terms of time and
effort.</p>
<p>I read 28 books in 2020. It appears I have performed slightly below my recent
average. I once <a href="https://twitter.com/nicolaiarocci/status/1214857647314362368?s=20">commented on Twitter</a> that &ldquo;the number of books per year&rdquo;
does not make for a useful metric. At the very least, it doesn&rsquo;t tell the whole
story. Take 2018 and 2019. In 2018 I read 30 books; in 2019 I only read 25. It
sounds like a steep decline until we look at the &ldquo;pages read per year&rdquo; metric.
As it turns out, I actually read more in 2019 than in 2018 (8394 vs. 8322. Ok,
it&rsquo;s more of a tie.)</p>
<p><em>Enjoyed this post? Subscribe to the <a href="https://buttondown.email/nicolaiarocci">newsletter</a> or follow @<a href="http://twitter.com/nicolaiarocci">nicolaiarocci</a> on Twitter.</em></p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
