<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>spotify on Nicola Iarocci</title>
    <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/tags/spotify/</link>
    <description>Recent content in spotify on Nicola Iarocci</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <copyright>Produced / Written / Maintained by [Nicola Iarocci](/) since 2010</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 03 Dec 2022 07:05:25 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://nicolaiarocci.com/tags/spotify/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>My Music in 2022 according to Spotify</title>
      <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/my-music-in-2022-according-to-spotify/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 03 Dec 2022 07:05:25 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nicolaiarocci.com/my-music-in-2022-according-to-spotify/</guid>
      <description>Wrapped by Spotify, the 2022 edition just landed in my mailbox. This year I listened to twenty-four different genres. My favorite was Indie Jazz, followed by Hip Hop, Jazz, Electronica and Rock. I am a little puzzled about that Hip Hop in second place. In total, I spent 14143 minutes listening to music, 80 percent more than other listeners in Italy did.
My favorite track was Fear Of The Dawn by Jack White, followed by The Beginning by Native Soul, Sorcery by The Toxic Avenger, Spirals by Django Django, and Boy From Michigan by John Grant.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Wrapped by Spotify, the 2022 edition just landed in my mailbox. This year I
listened to twenty-four different genres. My favorite was Indie Jazz, followed
by Hip Hop, Jazz, Electronica and Rock. I am a little puzzled about that Hip
Hop in second place. In total, I spent 14143 minutes listening to music, 80
percent more than other listeners in Italy did.</p>
<p>My favorite track was <a href="https://open.spotify.com/track/4v6soAl2R4sJB6Iyt2aiHw?si=5101c8519ddb4a2b">Fear Of The Dawn</a> by Jack White, followed by <a href="https://open.spotify.com/track/3FoXWHV24HO9rpcwkYa9lF?si=773fe3def78c4423">The
Beginning</a> by Native Soul, <a href="https://open.spotify.com/track/4HWC8Ymr2TlkTo97ttMiIq?si=10862b9eee7b496c">Sorcery</a> by The Toxic Avenger, <a href="https://open.spotify.com/track/3Uxjvj6TXr742JOFa7qYn6?si=074fa76aa8c64b8b">Spirals</a> by
Django Django, and <a href="https://open.spotify.com/track/2LRiyKKJf2RTuFx31DEU6E?si=57c827fd08b2499b">Boy From Michigan</a> by John Grant.</p>
<p>My favorite artists have been Max Gazzè (a recent rediscovery-and reappraisal),
Rosalía, Accademia Bizantina, Subsonica and Jack White. Again, color me a
little surprised. I like Max Gazzè, but I&rsquo;d swear I listened to many other
artists for at least the same amount of time, if not (way) more. But what do I
know? One cannot beat the algorithm, right?</p>
<p>My “music personality,” as Spotify calls it, would be that of a “serious
relationship: you carefully select the music and artists you listen to but have
a lot of affection to give. If you like an artist, then it’s serious.” Which I
have to admit is kind of my general attitude, not just toward music. Here&rsquo;s my
top 101 (not a typo) for 2022:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://open.spotify.com/playlist/37i9dQZF1F0sijgNaJdgit?si=834dd8504bf3430b">My Top Songs of 2022</a></li>
</ul>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>How I stopped Spotify from draining both my RAM and CPU</title>
      <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/how-i-stopped-spotify-from-draining-both-my-ram-and-cpu/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 05 Sep 2022 07:05:25 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nicolaiarocci.com/how-i-stopped-spotify-from-draining-both-my-ram-and-cpu/</guid>
      <description>A few days ago, I was browsing my Twitter feed when a suggestion from my friend @flaper87 caught my attention:
On my &amp;ldquo;comfortably old&amp;rdquo; MacBook Pro1, Spotify has been an absolute hog. The simple act of opening it will require three hundred MBs. That&amp;rsquo;s a remarkable amount of memory for staying idle and doing nothing useful. Let it play for a few hours, and have fun glancing at CPU and RAM usage ramping up like there&amp;rsquo;s no tomorrow.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>A few days ago, I was browsing my Twitter feed when a <a href="https://twitter.com/flaper87/status/1564899493572710400">suggestion</a> from my
friend <a href="https://twitter.com/flaper87">@flaper87</a> caught my attention:</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" src="/images/flaper87-on-spotifyd.png" alt=""  />
</p>
<p>On my &ldquo;comfortably old&rdquo; MacBook Pro<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1</a></sup>, Spotify has been an absolute hog. The
simple act of opening it will require three hundred MBs. That&rsquo;s a remarkable
amount of memory for staying idle and doing nothing useful. Let it play for
a few hours, and have fun glancing at CPU and RAM usage ramping up like there&rsquo;s
no tomorrow. Just for the record, here&rsquo;s Spotify memory usage at launch:</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" src="/images/spotify-memory-usage.png" alt=""  />
</p>
<p>So what exactly is <a href="https://github.com/Spotifyd/spotifyd">spotifyd</a>? An open source Spotify client
running as a UNIX daemon.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Spotifyd streams music just like the official client, but is more lightweight
and supports more platforms. Spotifyd also supports the Spotify Connect
protocol, which makes it show up as a device that can be controlled from the
official clients<sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">2</a></sup>.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Slow Saturday morning, I decided to give the spotifyd/spotify-tui combo a try.
Setting up spotifyd on a Mac with homebrew is as simple as typing <code>brew install spotifyd</code> and then <code>brew services start spotifyd</code> to let it run as a service,
or one can opt to launch it as a stand-alone with <code>spotifyd --no-daemon</code>.</p>
<p>As I quickly learned, on a Mac, you need to edit the default configuration file
to update a couple of settings, as reported on the wiki. Namely, I had to set
<code>backend = 'portaudio'</code> and <code>volume_controller = 'softvol'</code>. While at it,
I also set <code>use_keyring = true</code> to avoid storing my Spotify password in the
file. Here&rsquo;s my current configuration settings:</p>
<pre><code>[global]
username = &quot;&lt;USERNAME&gt;&quot;
use_keyring = true

# On Linux, set both values to 'alsa'
backend = &quot;portaudio&quot;          
volume_controller = &quot;softvol&quot;  

bitrate = 320
volume_normalisation = true
normalisation_pregain = -10

# If set to true, audio data does NOT get cached.
no_audio_cache = false
cache_path = &quot;&lt;USER_LIBRARY&gt;/Application Support/Spotify/PersistentCache/Storage&quot;
</code></pre>
<p>One minor annoyance that doesn&rsquo;t prevent the server from running as intended
and is only noticeable when I run spotifyd as a stand-alone app is a recurring
and rather obscure &ldquo;No route to host&rdquo; warning message. There&rsquo;s an <a href="https://github.com/Spotifyd/spotifyd/issues/1026">open
ticket</a> about it. Other than that, spotifyd has been bliss. Most remarkably,
this is the memory usage after a few hours of non-stop streaming:</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" src="/images/spotifyd-memory-usage.png" alt=""  />
</p>
<p>Quite an achievement, considering that we started at 300+ MBs.</p>
<p>I also installed <a href="https://github.com/Rigellute/spotify-tui">spotify-tui</a> in an attempt to use it as a replacement for
the official client. As much as I&rsquo;d love to use it (I love its UI/UX), I can&rsquo;t
say I&rsquo;m happy with it. It sometimes reports a server disconnect when, in fact,
the underlying spotifyd service is running fine (and I can connect and play
with it from the official client). Secondly, it is sluggish sometimes. Further
investigation revealed that the project is <a href="https://github.com/Rigellute/spotify-tui/issues/1000">not actively maintained</a>. For
the time being, I&rsquo;m connecting to spotifyd from the official iPhone app. I get
the lightweight service with the added benefit that I don&rsquo;t have to switch
windows when I want to interact with Spotify.</p>
<div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
<hr>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1">
<p>mid-2012. Yes, I know. It&rsquo;s due for replacement later this year, when the M2 MacBook Pro 14&quot; is announced.&#160;<a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
<li id="fn:2">
<p>Spotifyd requires a Spotify Premium account.
[rss]: <a href="https://nicolaiarocci.com/index.xml">https://nicolaiarocci.com/index.xml</a>
[tw]: <a href="http://twitter.com/nicolaiarocci">http://twitter.com/nicolaiarocci</a>
[nl]: <a href="https://buttondown.email/nicolaiarocci">https://buttondown.email/nicolaiarocci</a>&#160;<a href="#fnref:2" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
</ol>
</div>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
