<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>bash on Nicola Iarocci</title>
    <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/tags/bash/</link>
    <description>Recent content in bash on Nicola Iarocci</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <copyright>Produced / Written / Maintained by [Nicola Iarocci](/) since 2010</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 23 Aug 2023 07:05:25 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://nicolaiarocci.com/tags/bash/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>rsync with a different user</title>
      <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/rsync-with-a-different-user/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Aug 2023 07:05:25 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nicolaiarocci.com/rsync-with-a-different-user/</guid>
      <description>Today I learned how to rsync with a user different than the one connected to the remote. Why would one want to do such a thing? The data I need to download from that server is owned by &amp;lsquo;backup,&amp;rsquo; a different, service-only user. I wanted to avoid going the change-permissions slippery route and allow my user direct access to the data.
Looking at the rsync documentation, I learned about the nifty --rsync-path=PROGRAM option:</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Today I learned how to rsync with a user different than the one connected to the remote. Why would one want to do such a
thing? The data I need to download from that server is owned by &lsquo;backup,&rsquo; a different, service-only user. I wanted to
avoid going the change-permissions slippery route and allow my user direct access to the data.</p>
<p>Looking at the rsync documentation, I learned about the nifty <code>--rsync-path=PROGRAM</code> <a href="https://download.samba.org/pub/rsync/rsync.1#opt--rsync-path">option</a>:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Use this to specify what program is to be run on the remote machine to start-up rsync. Often used when rsync is not in
the default remote-shell&rsquo;s path (e.g. &ndash;rsync-path=/usr/local/bin/rsync).</p>
</blockquote>
<p>The example caught my attention. I could perhaps leverage this option to perform a user switch before executing rsync
(now performed on the remote machine). As further research confirmed, it <a href="https://unix.stackexchange.com/a/546296">can be done</a>:</p>
<pre tabindex="0"><code>rsync --rsync-path &#39;sudo -u backup rsync&#39; -a --delete host:source destination
</code></pre><p>It didn&rsquo;t work immediately because my user was not a sudoer, but that was an easy fix:</p>
<pre tabindex="0"><code>cat &gt; /etc/sudoers.d/myuser &lt;&lt; EOF
myuser ALL=(ALL) NOPASSWD:/usr/bin/rsync
EOF
</code></pre><p>As you can see, not only must the user be a sudoer, but it also needs to be able to sudo with no password. One last
minor issue was that &lsquo;backup&rsquo;, being a service user, had no shell access. That was another easy fix:</p>
<pre tabindex="0"><code>sudo usermod -s /bin/bash backup
</code></pre><p>Now my rsync-with-a-different-user command works like a charm. I do have some mild security concerns, though. My user is
a sudoer (can only sudo rsync, though<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1</a></sup>), and &lsquo;backup&rsquo; now has shell access. As password logins are turned off, and
SSH keys-only access is allowed to the machine (and I&rsquo;m the only person holding those keys), everything&rsquo;s still
reasonably safe. Are there better ways? Please let me know.</p>
<p><em>Subscribe to the [newsletter][nl], the [RSS feed][rss], or [follow me on Mastodon][m]</em></p>
<div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
<hr>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1">
<p>Thanks to Sebastian on Mastodon for <a href="https://fosstodon.org/@DarkMetatron@rollenspiel.social/110939139075153024">pointing out</a> that I should limit the sudoer to just rsync itself. I updated the post accordingly. By the way, this is why I love posting TILs in public.
[rss]: <a href="https://nicolaiarocci.com/index.xml">https://nicolaiarocci.com/index.xml</a>
[m]: <a href="https://fosstodon.org/@nicola">https://fosstodon.org/@nicola</a>
[nl]: <a href="https://nicolaiarocci.substack.com">https://nicolaiarocci.substack.com</a>&#160;<a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
</ol>
</div>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
