<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>music on Nicola Iarocci</title>
    <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/tags/music/</link>
    <description>Recent content in music on Nicola Iarocci</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 30 May 2023 07:05:25 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://nicolaiarocci.com/tags/music/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Daft Punk&#39;s Infinity Repeating music video</title>
      <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/daft-punks-infinity-repeating-music-video/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 May 2023 07:05:25 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nicolaiarocci.com/daft-punks-infinity-repeating-music-video/</guid>
      <description>Julian Casablancas (The Strokes, The Voidz) says Infinity Repeating is &amp;ldquo;the last Daft Punk song, ever.&amp;rdquo; The song was recorded in 2013 as a demo and left unpublished until it was included in the 10th-anniversary edition of Random Access Memories released a few weeks ago.
The video is a highly addictive masterpiece. Digging into the comments on YouTube, I found that someone attempted a reconstruction of all the citations included. I&amp;rsquo;m especially fond of the 8-16-32-bit graphics animation section.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Brad Mehldau plays I am the Walrus</title>
      <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/brad-mehldau-plays-i-am-the-walrus/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Feb 2023 07:05:25 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nicolaiarocci.com/brad-mehldau-plays-i-am-the-walrus/</guid>
      <description>Brad Mehldau plays Lennon/McCartney&amp;rsquo;s I Am the Walrus, from his upcoming album, Your Mother Should Know: Brad Mehldau Plays the Beatles.
Subscribe to the newsletter, the RSS feed, or follow me on Mastodon</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>My Music in 2022 according to Spotify</title>
      <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/my-music-in-2022-according-to-spotify/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 03 Dec 2022 07:05:25 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nicolaiarocci.com/my-music-in-2022-according-to-spotify/</guid>
      <description>Wrapped by Spotify, the 2022 edition just landed in my mailbox. This year I listened to twenty-four different genres. My favorite was Indie Jazz, followed by Hip Hop, Jazz, Electronica and Rock. I am a little puzzled about that Hip Hop in second place. In total, I spent 14143 minutes listening to music, 80 percent more than other listeners in Italy did.
My favorite track was Fear Of The Dawn by Jack White, followed by The Beginning by Native Soul, Sorcery by The Toxic Avenger, Spirals by Django Django, and Boy From Michigan by John Grant.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Jonny Greenwood pretended to play the keyboard when he first joined Radiohead</title>
      <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/jonny-greenwood-pretended-to-play-the-keyboard-when-he-first-joined-radiohead/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 21 Feb 2022 07:05:25 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nicolaiarocci.com/jonny-greenwood-pretended-to-play-the-keyboard-when-he-first-joined-radiohead/</guid>
      <description>Kottke reports this juicy excerpt from Jonny Greenwood&amp;rsquo;s interview at npr:
Thom [Yorke]&amp;rsquo;s band had a keyboard player — [whom] I think they didn&amp;rsquo;t get on with because he played his keyboard so loud. And so when I got the chance to play with them, the first thing I did was make sure my keyboard was turned off &amp;hellip; I must have done months of rehearsals with them with this keyboard, and they didn&amp;rsquo;t know that I&amp;rsquo;d already turned it off.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Modulations - History of Electronic Music</title>
      <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/modulations-history-of-electronic-music/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Feb 2022 07:05:25 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nicolaiarocci.com/modulations-history-of-electronic-music/</guid>
      <description>I stumbled upon Modulations, a documentary on &amp;ldquo;the evolution of electronic music and its many genres. How the wide range of styles and scenes formed through experimentations on sound formation.&amp;rdquo; This short film (75 minutes) is packed with guest stars of all calibers1, some of them genuinely pivotal to the evolution of electronic music. Indeed, the uninitiated mind gets to know a lot of details and amenities on the first decade or so of electronic music.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Lay Back and Keep Smiling</title>
      <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/lay-back-and-keep-smiling/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 23 Jan 2022 07:05:25 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nicolaiarocci.com/lay-back-and-keep-smiling/</guid>
      <description>Tomorrow we&amp;rsquo;re releasing a major project on which we&amp;rsquo;ve been working non-stop for two and a half years. No matter how many years in the trenches, release day always makes me a bit nervous. Experience does help. I know there will be problems, and we will solve them. Some customers will complain, and those will be the most vocal. The vast majority of them will appreciate the effort, enjoy the features, and stay silent.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Is Old Music Killing New Music?</title>
      <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/is-old-music-killing-new-music/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 20 Jan 2022 07:05:25 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nicolaiarocci.com/is-old-music-killing-new-music/</guid>
      <description>I had a hunch that old songs were taking over music streaming platforms—but even I was shocked when I saw the most recent numbers. According to MRC Data, old songs now represent 70% of the US music market. Those who make a living from new music—especially that endangered species known as the working musician—have to look at these figures with fear and trembling. But the news gets worse.
I can&amp;rsquo;t say I can relate as my kids of ages 21, 18, and 16 do their best to stay clear from the music I like, but anyways, Ted Gioia&amp;rsquo;s latest piece on recent music trends is super-interesting.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Book Review: Language of the Spirit, An Introduction to Classical Music</title>
      <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/book-review-language-of-the-spirit-an-introduction-to-classical-music/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 Oct 2021 07:05:25 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nicolaiarocci.com/book-review-language-of-the-spirit-an-introduction-to-classical-music/</guid>
      <description>In this introduction to classical music, Jan Swafford explains the different musical periods and their differences. Each period has its introductory chapter, followed by chapters dedicated to the most influential composers of the era. The choice is comprehensive and well cared for, with the most relevant names well-investigated both in biography and works. For each composer, Swafford also offers some listening suggestions. Biographies thicken as we get into the contemporary era.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Five Minutes to Make You Love Classical Music</title>
      <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/five-minutes-to-make-you-love-classical-music/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 25 Feb 2021 07:05:25 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nicolaiarocci.com/five-minutes-to-make-you-love-classical-music/</guid>
      <description>I already mentioned what background music (or sounds) I like when I am coding. In that list, I included classical music. I know classical is not exactly a favorite. Not in my field, at least. I suspect the vast majority of people disregard it in advance, not really knowing what they&amp;rsquo;re missing out on, just because, well, you know, it&amp;rsquo;s dinosaurs stuff. If you are among them, you should reconsider and repent your sins.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>What I listen to while programming</title>
      <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/what-i-listen-to-while-programming/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Feb 2021 07:05:25 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nicolaiarocci.com/what-i-listen-to-while-programming/</guid>
      <description>What music do you listen to while programming?1 For me, it&amp;rsquo;s usually jazz, classical, electronic, lots of it, or nothing. There are some specialized websites and podcasts I sometimes recur to, like [Music for Programming][1]. Several Spotify playlists I dig a lot, [Every Day I&amp;rsquo;m Nerdin&amp;rsquo;][2] being one of them. What can I say? I am musically omnivore.
However, I recently discovered something different: the [Field Recordings podcast][3]. &amp;ldquo;A podcast where audio-makers stand silently in fields (or things that could be broadly interpreted as fields).</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
