<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>music on Nicola Iarocci</title>
    <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/tags/music/</link>
    <description>Recent content in music on Nicola Iarocci</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <copyright>Produced / Written / Maintained by [Nicola Iarocci](/) since 2010</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 29 Feb 2024 10:44:26 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://nicolaiarocci.com/tags/music/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Astral Gold by Dean McPhee</title>
      <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/astral-gold-by-dean-mcphee/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 29 Feb 2024 10:44:26 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nicolaiarocci.com/astral-gold-by-dean-mcphee/</guid>
      <description>Thanks to Giovanni Ansaldo&amp;rsquo;s convincing review on yesterday&amp;rsquo;s issue of Il Mondo podcast, my first Bandcamp purchase1 is the recently released Astral Gold album by Dean McPhee, a British guitarist who combines folk with experimental music and jazz using his telecaster guitar to create endless landscapes.
As the title suggests, McPhee&amp;rsquo;s latest album is a journey into outer space. The album consists of six instrumental pieces, all captivating, enjoyable, and cohesive; they all serve as each other&amp;rsquo;s natural continuation.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Thanks to Giovanni Ansaldo&rsquo;s convincing review on yesterday&rsquo;s issue of
<a href="https://www.internazionale.it/ilmondo">Il Mondo</a> podcast, my first Bandcamp
purchase<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1</a></sup> is the recently released <a href="https://deanmcphee.bandcamp.com/album/astral-gold">Astral
Gold</a> album by Dean McPhee, a
British guitarist who combines folk with experimental music and jazz using his
telecaster guitar to create endless landscapes.</p>
<p>As the title suggests, McPhee&rsquo;s latest album is a journey into outer space. The
album consists of six instrumental pieces, all captivating, enjoyable, and
cohesive; they all serve as each other&rsquo;s natural continuation. Along with the
sound of his guitar, the musician uses tape loops, small percussion sounds, and
a few synthesizers here and there. The result is a hypnotic moonscape
reminiscent of 2001: A Space Odyssey<sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">2</a></sup>.</p>
<p>The album avoids easy psychedelia and opts for a more meditative approach while
meeting expectations perfectly. Sometimes, it sounds like Brian Eno&rsquo;s early
ambient phase and the more dilated Tangerine Dream. Dean McPhee has created an
otherworldly experience with just a few elements; minimalism is key.</p>
<iframe style="border: 0; width: 100%; height: 42px;"
    src="https://bandcamp.com/EmbeddedPlayer/album=1583034048/size=small/bgcol=333333/linkcol=ffffff/artwork=none/transparent=true/"
    seamless><a href="https://deanmcphee.bandcamp.com/album/astral-gold"></a></iframe>
<div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
<hr>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1">
<p>Look <a href="/sick-and-tired-of-spotifys-music-consuming-model/">here</a> for my
recent Spotify tirade and how I decided to return to purchased music.&#160;<a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
<li id="fn:2">
<p>On a lateral note, this music would fit perfectly as an EVE Online
soundtrack. I vividly remember my space pirate days in that game, exploring far
away and unknown solar systems, looking for prey while listening to Jón Hallur Haraldsson&rsquo;s
incredibly immersive <a href="https://archive.org/details/eve-online-soundtrack">original
soundtrack</a> (McPhee is on
another level, and the two genres don&rsquo;t compare, but hey.)&#160;<a href="#fnref:2" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
</ol>
</div>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Sick and tired of Spotify&#39;s music-consuming model</title>
      <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/sick-and-tired-of-spotifys-music-consuming-model/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 Feb 2024 11:26:29 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nicolaiarocci.com/sick-and-tired-of-spotifys-music-consuming-model/</guid>
      <description>I&amp;rsquo;m growing sick and tired of Spotify&amp;rsquo;s music-consuming model. There are many compelling and sometimes conflicting reasons, most perfectly outlined in The day I canceled my Spotify subscription on Raed&amp;rsquo;s blog.
I used to cherish music, I used to religiously collect, catalog and enjoy every album on my iPod. I could navigate the endless folders and find that exact song that I needed for that precise moment. Spotify killed that, I listen to what it suggests and just accept that it will go away when it decides to rotate it out.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I&rsquo;m growing sick and tired of Spotify&rsquo;s music-consuming model. There are many
compelling and sometimes conflicting reasons, most perfectly outlined in <em><a href="https://blog.raed.dev/posts/goodbye_spotify">The
day I canceled my Spotify
subscription</a></em> on Raed&rsquo;s blog.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>I used to cherish music, I used to religiously collect, catalog and enjoy
every album on my iPod. I could navigate the endless folders and find that exact
song that I needed for that precise moment. Spotify killed that, I listen to
what it suggests and just accept that it will go away when it decides to rotate
it out. Spotify trained me not to look too hard, to let the flow be, and if that
awesome song is gone or removed, don’t worry, we still have a million more.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>And also:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>The main screen is littered with podcasts I don’t care about, nor have I ever
listened to. It keeps pushing playlists that feel generic, bland, more based on
demographics than my years of consistent listening history. And there is nothing
I can do about it.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I can&rsquo;t cancel my subscription yet, as I would risk being lynched (we&rsquo;re on the
family plan), so I&rsquo;m experimenting with digital purchases of selected music that
I know I want to keep for the long run and that I deem worth sustaining
directly. The current plan is to buy it on Bandcamp, immediately download it,
and then listen to it, probably on Doppler. I will also drop a quick review on
my website (if it is not exciting enough to share here, it&rsquo;s probably not worth
buying in the first place.) I&rsquo;ve been gathering old-style music sources lately
(I primarily follow music critics and websites I respect and listen to live
stations like <a href="/nts-radio/">NTS</a>, Radio Paradise, and Bandcamp Radio). For the
time being, Spotify will stay and serve as a secondary discovery agent.</p>
<p>Yes, I will spend more on music, and it&rsquo;s okay. I won&rsquo;t buy everything I listen
to anyway; the idea is to only invest in the true gems. In a way, this all looks
like going back to old and brick-and-mortar music shop days but actualized, and
I like it a lot.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>NTS Radio</title>
      <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/nts-radio/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 13 Jan 2024 10:53:40 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nicolaiarocci.com/nts-radio/</guid>
      <description>NTS Radio is a family of like-minded and passionate individuals, dedicated to supporting exciting music and culture through online radio and events. NTS uncovers the best of the musical past, celebrates the present and cultivates the future of the underground music scene, and prides itself on being open-minded and experimental. (source)
I&amp;rsquo;m certainly a latecomer, but NTS Radio is the bomb. I have not opened Spotify (whose algorithm I find dull and repetitive) in the last week, not even once.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<blockquote>
<p>NTS Radio is a family of like-minded and passionate individuals, dedicated to
supporting exciting music and culture through online radio and events. NTS
uncovers the best of the musical past, celebrates the present and cultivates the
future of the underground music scene, and prides itself on being open-minded
and experimental. <em>(<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/NTS_Radio">source</a>)</em></p>
</blockquote>
<p>I&rsquo;m certainly a latecomer, but <a href="https://www.nts.live">NTS Radio</a> is the bomb. I
have not opened Spotify (whose algorithm I find dull and repetitive) in the last
week, not even once. I go straight to NTS to find the best and most diverse
music from all genres, played by DJs and independent radio stations worldwide.
Absolute banger.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Daft Punk&#39;s Infinity Repeating music video</title>
      <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/daft-punks-infinity-repeating-music-video/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 May 2023 07:05:25 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nicolaiarocci.com/daft-punks-infinity-repeating-music-video/</guid>
      <description>Julian Casablancas (The Strokes, The Voidz) says Infinity Repeating is &amp;ldquo;the last Daft Punk song, ever.&amp;rdquo; The song was recorded in 2013 as a demo and left unpublished until it was included in the 10th-anniversary edition of Random Access Memories released a few weeks ago.
The video is a highly addictive masterpiece. Digging into the comments on YouTube, I found that someone attempted a reconstruction of all the citations included. I&amp;rsquo;m especially fond of the 8-16-32-bit graphics animation section.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Julian Casablancas (The Strokes, The Voidz) says Infinity Repeating is &ldquo;the last Daft Punk song, ever.&rdquo; The song was
recorded in 2013 as a demo and left unpublished until it was included in the 10th-anniversary edition of Random Access
Memories released a few weeks ago.</p>
<p>
<div style="position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;">
  <iframe src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/imBlPXbAv6E" style="position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;" allowfullscreen title="YouTube Video"></iframe>
</div>

<!-- raw HTML omitted -->
The video is a highly addictive masterpiece. Digging into the comments on YouTube, I found that someone attempted a
reconstruction of <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=imBlPXbAv6E&amp;lc=UgzaNoEwyYOxNyc53cB4AaABAg">all the citations included</a>. I&rsquo;m especially fond of the 8-16-32-bit graphics animation section.
Another thing I learned is that Thomas Bangalter, formerly one-half of Daft Punk, <a href="https://www.latimes.com/entertainment-arts/story/2023-04-04/daft-punk-member-thomas-bangalter-terrified-ai">said</a> that his fear of artificial
intelligence was a factor in why the group split in 2021.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Brad Mehldau plays I am the Walrus</title>
      <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/brad-mehldau-plays-i-am-the-walrus/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 06 Feb 2023 07:05:25 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nicolaiarocci.com/brad-mehldau-plays-i-am-the-walrus/</guid>
      <description>Brad Mehldau plays Lennon/McCartney&amp;rsquo;s I Am the Walrus, from his upcoming album, Your Mother Should Know: Brad Mehldau Plays the Beatles.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Brad Mehldau plays Lennon/McCartney&rsquo;<em>s I Am the Walrus</em>, from his upcoming
album, <em>Your Mother Should Know: Brad Mehldau Plays the Beatles</em>.</p>
<p>
<div style="position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;">
  <iframe src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/lGvl6IdBJiA" style="position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;" allowfullscreen title="YouTube Video"></iframe>
</div>

<!-- raw HTML omitted --></p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>My Music in 2022 according to Spotify</title>
      <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/my-music-in-2022-according-to-spotify/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 03 Dec 2022 07:05:25 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nicolaiarocci.com/my-music-in-2022-according-to-spotify/</guid>
      <description>Wrapped by Spotify, the 2022 edition just landed in my mailbox. This year I listened to twenty-four different genres. My favorite was Indie Jazz, followed by Hip Hop, Jazz, Electronica and Rock. I am a little puzzled about that Hip Hop in second place. In total, I spent 14143 minutes listening to music, 80 percent more than other listeners in Italy did.
My favorite track was Fear Of The Dawn by Jack White, followed by The Beginning by Native Soul, Sorcery by The Toxic Avenger, Spirals by Django Django, and Boy From Michigan by John Grant.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Wrapped by Spotify, the 2022 edition just landed in my mailbox. This year I
listened to twenty-four different genres. My favorite was Indie Jazz, followed
by Hip Hop, Jazz, Electronica and Rock. I am a little puzzled about that Hip
Hop in second place. In total, I spent 14143 minutes listening to music, 80
percent more than other listeners in Italy did.</p>
<p>My favorite track was <a href="https://open.spotify.com/track/4v6soAl2R4sJB6Iyt2aiHw?si=5101c8519ddb4a2b">Fear Of The Dawn</a> by Jack White, followed by <a href="https://open.spotify.com/track/3FoXWHV24HO9rpcwkYa9lF?si=773fe3def78c4423">The
Beginning</a> by Native Soul, <a href="https://open.spotify.com/track/4HWC8Ymr2TlkTo97ttMiIq?si=10862b9eee7b496c">Sorcery</a> by The Toxic Avenger, <a href="https://open.spotify.com/track/3Uxjvj6TXr742JOFa7qYn6?si=074fa76aa8c64b8b">Spirals</a> by
Django Django, and <a href="https://open.spotify.com/track/2LRiyKKJf2RTuFx31DEU6E?si=57c827fd08b2499b">Boy From Michigan</a> by John Grant.</p>
<p>My favorite artists have been Max Gazzè (a recent rediscovery-and reappraisal),
Rosalía, Accademia Bizantina, Subsonica and Jack White. Again, color me a
little surprised. I like Max Gazzè, but I&rsquo;d swear I listened to many other
artists for at least the same amount of time, if not (way) more. But what do I
know? One cannot beat the algorithm, right?</p>
<p>My “music personality,” as Spotify calls it, would be that of a “serious
relationship: you carefully select the music and artists you listen to but have
a lot of affection to give. If you like an artist, then it’s serious.” Which I
have to admit is kind of my general attitude, not just toward music. Here&rsquo;s my
top 101 (not a typo) for 2022:</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://open.spotify.com/playlist/37i9dQZF1F0sijgNaJdgit?si=834dd8504bf3430b">My Top Songs of 2022</a></li>
</ul>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Jonny Greenwood pretended to play the keyboard when he first joined Radiohead</title>
      <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/jonny-greenwood-pretended-to-play-the-keyboard-when-he-first-joined-radiohead/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 21 Feb 2022 07:05:25 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nicolaiarocci.com/jonny-greenwood-pretended-to-play-the-keyboard-when-he-first-joined-radiohead/</guid>
      <description>Kottke reports this juicy excerpt from Jonny Greenwood&amp;rsquo;s interview at npr:
Thom [Yorke]&amp;rsquo;s band had a keyboard player — [whom] I think they didn&amp;rsquo;t get on with because he played his keyboard so loud. And so when I got the chance to play with them, the first thing I did was make sure my keyboard was turned off &amp;hellip; I must have done months of rehearsals with them with this keyboard, and they didn&amp;rsquo;t know that I&amp;rsquo;d already turned it off.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Kottke <a href="https://kottke.org/22/02/jonny-greenwood-pretended-to-play-the-keyboard-when-he-first-joined-radiohead">reports</a> this juicy excerpt from Jonny Greenwood&rsquo;s interview at npr:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Thom [Yorke]&rsquo;s band had a keyboard player — [whom] I think they didn&rsquo;t get on
with because he played his keyboard so loud. And so when I got the chance to
play with them, the first thing I did was make sure my keyboard was turned
off &hellip; I must have done months of rehearsals with them with this keyboard,
and they didn&rsquo;t know that I&rsquo;d already turned it off.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>They made quite a racket, quite a noise. It was all guitars and distortion
— and so I would pretend to play for weeks on end and Thom would say, &ldquo;I
can&rsquo;t quite hear what you&rsquo;re doing, but I think you&rsquo;re adding a really
interesting texture, because I can tell when you&rsquo;re not playing.&rdquo; And I&rsquo;m
thinking, &ldquo;No, you can&rsquo;t, because I&rsquo;m really not playing.&rdquo; And I&rsquo;d go home in
the evening and work out how to actually play chords and cautiously over the
next few months, I would start turning this keyboard up. And that&rsquo;s how
I started in with Radiohead.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Full interview is available <a href="https://www.npr.org/2022/02/07/1078802881/radiohead-jonny-greenwood-the-power-of-the-dog">here</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Modulations - History of Electronic Music</title>
      <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/modulations-history-of-electronic-music/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Feb 2022 07:05:25 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nicolaiarocci.com/modulations-history-of-electronic-music/</guid>
      <description>I stumbled upon Modulations, a documentary on &amp;ldquo;the evolution of electronic music and its many genres. How the wide range of styles and scenes formed through experimentations on sound formation.&amp;rdquo; This short film (75 minutes) is packed with guest stars of all calibers1, some of them genuinely pivotal to the evolution of electronic music. Indeed, the uninitiated mind gets to know a lot of details and amenities on the first decade or so of electronic music.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I stumbled upon <a href="https://youtu.be/icpDt6aQDww">Modulations</a>, a documentary on &ldquo;the evolution of electronic
music and its many genres. How the wide range of styles and scenes formed
through experimentations on sound formation.&rdquo; This short film (75 minutes) is
packed with guest stars of all calibers<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1</a></sup>, some of them genuinely pivotal to the
evolution of electronic music. Indeed, the uninitiated mind gets to know a lot
of details and amenities on the first decade or so of electronic music.</p>
<p>Perhaps it attempts to fit too much information into a tight timeline:
many guests, genres, places. There&rsquo;s a lot to unpack, and, inevitably, a lot is
left out. A series (like the excellent Hip-Hop Evolution recently aired on
Netflix) could better cover all the material. Unfortunately, Modulations was
released in 1998, when such an option wasn&rsquo;t even in the books. And this takes
us to my second qualm with this production: it of course doesn&rsquo;t cover the
recent years, let&rsquo;s say from early 2000s up to today. A second part would be
grand.</p>

<div style="position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;">
  <iframe src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/icpDt6aQDww" style="position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;" allowfullscreen title="YouTube Video"></iframe>
</div>

<div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
<hr>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1">
<p>A partial list I digged out includes the likes of John Cage, Afrika Bambaataa, Juan Atkins, Bundy Brown, DJ Spooky, Future Sound of London, Fumiya Tanaka, Hardfloor, Kodwo Eshun, Teo Macero, Christian Marclay, Giorgio Moroder, Robert Moog, Mixmaster Morris, Orbital, Prodigy, Simon Reynolds, Ed Rush, Karlheinz Stockhausen, Tetsu Inoue and Westbam.
[rss]: <a href="https://nicolaiarocci.com/index.xml">https://nicolaiarocci.com/index.xml</a>
[tw]: <a href="http://twitter.com/nicolaiarocci">http://twitter.com/nicolaiarocci</a>
[nl]: <a href="https://buttondown.email/nicolaiarocci">https://buttondown.email/nicolaiarocci</a>&#160;<a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
</ol>
</div>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Lay Back and Keep Smiling</title>
      <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/lay-back-and-keep-smiling/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 23 Jan 2022 07:05:25 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nicolaiarocci.com/lay-back-and-keep-smiling/</guid>
      <description>Tomorrow we&amp;rsquo;re releasing a major project on which we&amp;rsquo;ve been working non-stop for two and a half years. No matter how many years in the trenches, release day always makes me a bit nervous. Experience does help. I know there will be problems, and we will solve them. Some customers will complain, and those will be the most vocal. The vast majority of them will appreciate the effort, enjoy the features, and stay silent.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Tomorrow we&rsquo;re releasing a major project on which we&rsquo;ve been working non-stop
for two and a half years. No matter how many years in the trenches, release day
always makes me a bit nervous. Experience does help. I know there will be
problems, and we will solve them. Some customers will complain, and those will
be the most vocal. The vast majority of them will appreciate the effort, enjoy
the features, and stay silent. That&rsquo;s how it works. We&rsquo;ll do just fine.</p>
<p>As you can imagine, it&rsquo;s a working weekend for me. While hacking in the early
morning, I listened to <a href="https://open.spotify.com/playlist/1WjnPw3PbQJOsEpEgJsz5f?si=53a83f9c31484310">The Mildlife Very Fantastic Playlist</a> when a curious
tune caught my attention<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1</a></sup>. I glanced over to Spotify, and my eyes fell on
the most appropriate CD cover for launch day ever.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" src="/images/laidback-keepsmiling.jpg" alt="Laid Back&amp;hellip;Keep Smiling"  />
</p>
<p>Whatever happens tomorrow, lay back and keep smiling.</p>
<div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
<hr>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1">
<p>Track #8, <em>Fly Away / Walking in the Sunshine</em>
[rss]: <a href="https://nicolaiarocci.com/index.xml">https://nicolaiarocci.com/index.xml</a>
[tw]: <a href="http://twitter.com/nicolaiarocci">http://twitter.com/nicolaiarocci</a>
[nl]: <a href="https://buttondown.email/nicolaiarocci">https://buttondown.email/nicolaiarocci</a>&#160;<a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
</ol>
</div>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Is Old Music Killing New Music?</title>
      <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/is-old-music-killing-new-music/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 20 Jan 2022 07:05:25 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nicolaiarocci.com/is-old-music-killing-new-music/</guid>
      <description>I had a hunch that old songs were taking over music streaming platforms—but even I was shocked when I saw the most recent numbers. According to MRC Data, old songs now represent 70% of the US music market. Those who make a living from new music—especially that endangered species known as the working musician—have to look at these figures with fear and trembling. But the news gets worse.
I can&amp;rsquo;t say I can relate as my kids of ages 21, 18, and 16 do their best to stay clear from the music I like, but anyways, Ted Gioia&amp;rsquo;s latest piece on recent music trends is super-interesting.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<blockquote>
<p>I had a hunch that old songs were taking over music streaming platforms—but
even I was shocked when I saw the most recent numbers. According to MRC Data,
old songs now represent 70% of the US music market. Those who make a living
from new music—especially that endangered species known as the working
musician—have to look at these figures with fear and trembling. But the news
gets worse.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I can&rsquo;t say I can relate as my kids of ages 21, 18, and 16 do their best to
stay clear from the music I like, but anyways, Ted Gioia&rsquo;s <a href="https://tedgioia.substack.com/p/is-old-music-killing-new-music">latest piece</a> on
recent music trends is super-interesting.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Book Review: Language of the Spirit, An Introduction to Classical Music</title>
      <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/book-review-language-of-the-spirit-an-introduction-to-classical-music/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 Oct 2021 07:05:25 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nicolaiarocci.com/book-review-language-of-the-spirit-an-introduction-to-classical-music/</guid>
      <description>In this introduction to classical music, Jan Swafford explains the different musical periods and their differences. Each period has its introductory chapter, followed by chapters dedicated to the most influential composers of the era. The choice is comprehensive and well cared for, with the most relevant names well-investigated both in biography and works. For each composer, Swafford also offers some listening suggestions. Biographies thicken as we get into the contemporary era.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>In this introduction to classical music, Jan Swafford explains the different
musical periods and their differences. Each period has its introductory
chapter, followed by chapters dedicated to the most influential composers of
the era. The choice is comprehensive and well cared for, with the most relevant
names well-investigated both in biography and works. For each composer,
Swafford also offers some listening suggestions. Biographies thicken as we get
into the contemporary era. Here, some are limited to just a page or two while
others, obviously those of the author&rsquo;s preferred composers, remain as thorough
as those of the older periods.</p>
<p>The introductory chapters to various musical eras (Baroque, Classical,
Romantic, Modernism and beyond) were, for me, the most interesting ones. In
these chapters, Swafford explains the changes in society, technology and taste
that influenced the musical styles, themselves a revelation of the spirit of
the time. In this sense, Language of the Spirit is not just a classical music
book but also a historical essay, often sharp and full of intriguing
information on the periods crossed.</p>
<p>The author&rsquo;s effort in using simple language, understandable even to the
uninitiated, is evident, and the goal is well achieved, for the most part.
Sometimes, however, albeit very rarely, it goes into the technical, where
someone like me, who lacks a solid background, might struggle.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" src="/images/language-of-the-spirit.jpg#right" alt="Language of the Spirit: An Introduction to Classical Music"  />

The recommended listenings are excellent. For every single one, I wanted to
stop reading and listen to it. That&rsquo;s the approach recommended by the author,
but I never managed, too eager to finish the chapter. I then tried to make
a Spotify playlist out of them, failing miserably because of my pedantry;
I only wanted the suggested executions, often missing on Spotify.</p>
<p>Language of the Spirit is a recommended introduction to classical music and its
history. It allows the reader to collect a phenomenal list of composers and
their works while, at the same time, delving into the momentous changes faced
by (mainly European) society over the last few centuries.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Five Minutes to Make You Love Classical Music</title>
      <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/five-minutes-to-make-you-love-classical-music/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 25 Feb 2021 07:05:25 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nicolaiarocci.com/five-minutes-to-make-you-love-classical-music/</guid>
      <description>I already mentioned what background music (or sounds) I like when I am coding. In that list, I included classical music. I know classical is not exactly a favorite. Not in my field, at least. I suspect the vast majority of people disregard it in advance, not really knowing what they&amp;rsquo;re missing out on, just because, well, you know, it&amp;rsquo;s dinosaurs stuff. If you are among them, you should reconsider and repent your sins.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I already <a href="/what-i-listen-to-while-programming">mentioned</a> what background music (or sounds) I like when I am
coding. In that list, I included classical music. I know classical is not
exactly a favorite. Not in my field, at least. I suspect the vast majority of
people disregard it in advance, not really knowing what they&rsquo;re missing out on,
just because, well, you know, it&rsquo;s dinosaurs stuff. If you are among them, you
should reconsider and repent your sins. But have no worries, and rejoice, for
I am here to save your soul.</p>
<p>Zachary Woolfe, The New York Times&rsquo;s classical music editor, has been working
on <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/interactive/2020/arts/music/five-minutes-love-music.html">Five Minutes To Make You Love Classical Music</a>. This remarkable project aims
at &ldquo;hooking readers on classical music, five minutes at a time.&rdquo;</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Once a month online, about 15 musicians, pop-culture figures and Times
writers and editors each select the piece they would play for a friend tied
to a theme, be it an instrument, composer, genre or voice type. The series
aims to make classical music accessible to readers as a Top 40 track [&hellip;].
You don&rsquo;t need to know the difference between a cadenza and a concerto. &ldquo;It&rsquo;s
about pure pleasure and exploration.&rdquo; (<a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2021/02/03/insider/five-minutes-love-classical-music.html">source</a>)</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I find this project interesting for many reasons, the main one being the
variance of choices and themes. Picks are often excellent and not obvious. This
is, I think, because of the wide range of people involved with the selections.
You may have Yo-Yo Ma suggest a Concerto for the Cello installment, and then
Mark Hamill or Condoleeza Rice propose a listening for the Mozart segment. How
about Cecilia Bartoli for Baroque music?</p>
<p>Mind you, I am not a classical music expert. I just try and like to listen to
good music, regardless of the genre. I am probably the ideal target for
a project like this, which explains why I keep coming back. My favorite?
Probably <a href="https://www.nytimes.com/2020/06/03/arts/music/five-minutes-classical-music-cello.html">Five Minutes That Will Make You Love the Cello</a>, although I am
having a hard time accepting that Bach&rsquo;s Suite No. 1 is not included in the
selection (Suite No. 5 is, though.)</p>
<p>Official NYT playlists for the series are available on Spotify and, I presume,
other platforms. I know because I wasted a couple hours building my own before
finding out.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>What I listen to while programming</title>
      <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/what-i-listen-to-while-programming/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Feb 2021 07:05:25 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nicolaiarocci.com/what-i-listen-to-while-programming/</guid>
      <description>What music do you listen to while programming?1 For me, it&amp;rsquo;s usually jazz, classical, electronic, lots of it, or nothing. There are some specialized websites and podcasts I sometimes recur to, like [Music for Programming][1]. Several Spotify playlists I dig a lot, [Every Day I&amp;rsquo;m Nerdin&amp;rsquo;][2] being one of them. What can I say? I am musically omnivore.
However, I recently discovered something different: the [Field Recordings podcast][3]. &amp;ldquo;A podcast where audio-makers stand silently in fields (or things that could be broadly interpreted as fields).</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>What music do you listen to while programming?<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1</a></sup> For me, it&rsquo;s usually jazz,
classical, electronic, lots of it, or nothing. There are some specialized
websites and podcasts I sometimes recur to, like [Music for Programming][1].
Several Spotify playlists I dig a lot, [Every Day I&rsquo;m Nerdin&rsquo;][2] being one of
them. What can I say? I am musically omnivore.</p>
<p>However, I recently discovered something different: the [Field Recordings
podcast][3]. &ldquo;A podcast where audio-makers stand silently in fields (or things
that could be broadly interpreted as fields).&rdquo; I am told it was launched last
year, just about when the COVID lockdowns started, by acclaimed UK audio artist
and producer Eleanor McDowall. It&rsquo;s free, updated daily with submissions coming
from all over the world, and holds many treasures. Most episodes are short, I&rsquo;d
say around the 5 minutes mark, with some notable exceptions like [The Sound of
2020][4], &ldquo;A slow weave of some of 2020&rsquo;s Field Recordings in chronological
order&rdquo;. One of my favorites has got to be the &ldquo;[Inside the log burner][5]&rdquo;
episode by Chris Attaway (Devoran, Cornwall, UK, January 2021):</p>
<blockquote>
<p>&ldquo;I was prepping a fire in our log burner on a cold, blustery day here in
Devoran, Cornwall and the wind whistling through the vents was really creepy!
So I stuck my Zoom inside and recorded it for a bit. It was like it had its
own little atmosphere and weather inside!&rdquo;</p>
</blockquote>
<p>At my desk churning out code, I hit play, and that stove is instantly
teleported here, right by my side. I can almost feel its warmth. Indeed,
there&rsquo;s something cathartic about listening to these sound fragments from all
over the world.</p>
<div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
<hr>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1">
<p>As I write this, news of the passing of Chick Corea hit me. Today his <em>Plays</em> album is on repeat.
[5]: <a href="https://fieldrecordings.xyz/2021/01/12/inside-the-log-burner-devoran-cornwall-in-january-2021-by-chris-attaway/">https://fieldrecordings.xyz/2021/01/12/inside-the-log-burner-devoran-cornwall-in-january-2021-by-chris-attaway/</a>
[4]: <a href="https://fieldrecordings.xyz/2020/12/14/the-sound-of-2020/">https://fieldrecordings.xyz/2020/12/14/the-sound-of-2020/</a>
[3]: <a href="https://fieldrecordings.xyz/">https://fieldrecordings.xyz/</a>
[2]: <a href="https://open.spotify.com/playlist/1itC2kKqIqun8OU05J5G8v?si=iYtyuKAfT4ejArv1aaT4FQ">https://open.spotify.com/playlist/1itC2kKqIqun8OU05J5G8v?si=iYtyuKAfT4ejArv1aaT4FQ</a>
[1]: <a href="http://www.musicforprogramming.net/">http://www.musicforprogramming.net/</a>
[rss]: <a href="https://nicolaiarocci.com/index.xml">https://nicolaiarocci.com/index.xml</a>
[tw]: <a href="http://twitter.com/nicolaiarocci">http://twitter.com/nicolaiarocci</a>
[nl]: <a href="https://buttondown.email/nicolaiarocci">https://buttondown.email/nicolaiarocci</a>&#160;<a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
</ol>
</div>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
