<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>history on Nicola Iarocci</title>
    <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/tags/history/</link>
    <description>Recent content in history on Nicola Iarocci</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <copyright>Produced / Written / Maintained by [Nicola Iarocci](/) since 2010</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 30 Apr 2023 07:05:25 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://nicolaiarocci.com/tags/history/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Quoting Cicero</title>
      <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/quoting-cicero/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 30 Apr 2023 07:05:25 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nicolaiarocci.com/quoting-cicero/</guid>
      <description>Not to know what happened before one was born is always to be a child.
I found this Cicero quote on Lapham&amp;rsquo;s Quarterly&amp;rsquo;s about page. A little research dug out the supposedly original version found in Orator Ad M. Brutum (46 BC). It goes like this:
To be ignorant of what occurred before you were born is to remain always a child. For what is the worth of human life, unless it is woven into the life of our ancestors by the records of history?</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<blockquote>
<p>Not to know what happened before one was born is always to be a child.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I found this Cicero quote on <em>Lapham&rsquo;s Quarterly</em>&rsquo;s <a href="https://www.laphamsquarterly.org/about">about page</a>. A little <a href="https://en.wikiquote.org/wiki/Cicero">research</a> dug out the supposedly
original version found in <em>Orator Ad M. Brutum</em> (46 BC). It goes like this:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>To be ignorant of what occurred before you were born is to remain always a child. For what is the worth of human life,
unless it is woven into the life of our ancestors by the records of history?</p>
</blockquote>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The indictment against Sparta</title>
      <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/the-indictment-against-sparta/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Aug 2022 07:05:25 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nicolaiarocci.com/the-indictment-against-sparta/</guid>
      <description>Bret Devereaux has long been my go-to source for all things ancient and military history. One thing I somehow missed reading from his incredibly resourceful website is the This Isn&amp;rsquo;t Sparta series. He recently published a three-year-anniversary series retrospective which promptly surfaced on my RSS feed, giving me a chance to catch up over the holidays. The whole thing is a very long read, with some installments more engaging than others but overall very enjoyable, eye-opening, and information dense.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><a href="https://acoup.blog/">Bret Devereaux</a> has long been my go-to source for all things ancient and
military history. One thing I somehow missed reading from his incredibly
resourceful website is the <a href="https://acoup.blog/2019/08/16/collections-this-isnt-sparta-part-i-spartan-school/">This Isn&rsquo;t Sparta</a> series. He recently published
a three-year-anniversary series retrospective which promptly surfaced on my
RSS feed, giving me a chance to catch up over the holidays. The whole thing is
a very long read, with some installments more engaging than others but overall
very enjoyable, eye-opening, and information dense. In the just-published
retrospective, Bret writes:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>The series was thus intended to be set against the general public hagiography
of Sparta and its intended audience was what I’ve heard termed the ‘Sparta
Bro’ – the person for whom the Spartans represent a positive example (indeed,
often the pinnacle) of masculine achievement, often explicitly connected to
roles in law enforcement, military service and physical fitness (the
regularity with which that last thing is included is striking and suggests to
me the profound unseriousness of the argument). [&hellip;] In that light, I think
the series holds up fairly well.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>As a former 100% Sparta Bro, I qualified for the target audience. Paraphrasing
Marx, one could say that ignorance is the opium of the people. Take 300 the
movie.  I&rsquo;m glad I saw it as entirely ignorant of Sparta&rsquo;s &lsquo;real&rsquo; prowess, or
most fun would have been spoiled.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Book Review: King and Emperor, A New Life of Charlemagne</title>
      <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/book-review-king-and-emperor-a-new-life-of-charlemagne/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 31 Oct 2021 07:05:25 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nicolaiarocci.com/book-review-king-and-emperor-a-new-life-of-charlemagne/</guid>
      <description>In this scholarly biography by Janet L. Nelson, Charlemagne is stripped back from the years of mythologizing and idolizing that have occurred since his death. He is presented as distinctly human, and this book is the first time I have felt I could reasonably understand Charlemagne as the man he was, not the man he has since been painted to be. Moreover, Nelson is excellent in her discussions of Charlemagne&amp;rsquo;s wives and their roles.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>In this scholarly biography by Janet L. Nelson, Charlemagne is stripped back
from the years of mythologizing and idolizing that have occurred since his
death. He is presented as distinctly human, and this book is the first time
I have felt I could reasonably understand Charlemagne as the man he was, not
the man he has since been painted to be. Moreover, Nelson is excellent in her
discussions of Charlemagne&rsquo;s wives and their roles. For example, the
commonplace assumption that Fastrada was a cruel person is questioned, and she
emerges as a capable companion and queen instead.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" src="/images/king-and-emperor.jpg#right" alt="Kind and Emperor: A New Life of Charlemagne"  />

Nelson is firm in her dissection of the source material. However, it can be
a challenge to weave critical discussion of sources and fluid narrative, and at
times this book leans a little on the dry side. Nelson does not speculate; she
instead focuses on what we know or can be reasonably inferred from the sources.
The downside is that some of the more exciting episodes from Charlemagne&rsquo;s life
are glossed over: the 792AD rebellion of Charlemagne&rsquo;s eldest son, Pippin,
receives only three pages of discussion, whereas Charlemagne&rsquo;s canal-building
project, which follows, receives double that. Personally, as a general reader
rather than a historian, I would have preferred more on the &ldquo;interesting bits&rdquo;
of Charlemagne&rsquo;s reign, but a more academic reader may not mind.</p>
<p>Overall, this is an excellent biography, and I would recommend it to an
informed reader. The scholarly attention to sources might deter the casual
reader, but the motivated ones will take profit from the effort.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Book Review. Eight Days in May: The Final Collapse of the Third Reich</title>
      <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/book-review.-eight-days-in-may-the-final-collapse-of-the-third-reich/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 18 Jul 2021 07:05:25 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nicolaiarocci.com/book-review.-eight-days-in-may-the-final-collapse-of-the-third-reich/</guid>
      <description>Volker Ullrich&amp;rsquo;s Eight Days in May describes the period from April 30, 1945, the day of Hitler&amp;rsquo;s suicide, to May 8, the day of signing the German capitulation, with significant jumps backwards in time and some hops in the future. We&amp;rsquo;re covering only eight days, and the dictator dies on day one. What essential events might ever have happened in such a short period? Well, many pivotal ones, as this well-researched work shows us.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Volker Ullrich&rsquo;s Eight Days in May describes the period from April 30, 1945,
the day of Hitler&rsquo;s suicide, to May 8, the day of signing the German
capitulation, with significant jumps backwards in time and some hops in the
future. We&rsquo;re covering only eight days, and the dictator dies on day one. What
essential events might ever have happened in such a short period? Well, many
pivotal ones, as this well-researched work shows us.</p>
<p>The book is merciless towards Hitler&rsquo;s heirs and not accommodating at all
towards Germans of that age in general. Reading the behaviors and things said
in those days is gruesome. Under track are the horrible consequences of war and
concentration camps. The resulting picture is that of the supreme horrors and
mistakes that humanity can reach.</p>
<p>The text focuses on the protagonists of those days, the Nazi hierarchs (not
just the most infamously well known) and their Allies and Red Army
counterparts. There are few notable exceptions, like the story of Marlene
Dietrich, already a Hollywood star, who served as an American army officer and
returned to Germany to look for her sister lost in the fog of war. To her
dismay, she found that her sister had prospered, cooperating and taking advance
of the Nazi regime. Marlene bought her sisters&rsquo; silence, and for the rest of
her life, fiercely negated the very own existence of a sister.</p>
<p>I found the part on the German population and its shocked, instinctive reaction
to the regime&rsquo;s fall particularly informative. The immediate turncoat of most,
along with the lying denial of knowing anything about the atrocities.The
disturbing (George Orwell&rsquo;s word), immediate sympathy for the Allies. Also, the
eulogy for the few who courageously conducted a desperate, clandestine and
seemingly hopeless resistance within the Reich. It is especially relevant that
the author is German.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" src="/images/eight-days-in-may.jpg#right" alt="Eight Days in May book cover"  />

This book leaves me stunned. It is always painful to read about that historical
period. The millions of deaths. The suffering. The atrocities. We need to keep
going back, walk the way over and over, never to forget, never to repeat. To
that end, Eight Days in May is a book everyone should read.</p>
<p>By May 8, 1945, Germany was a humiliated, devastated country. Most major cities
were annihilated, the economy had collapsed, and millions of people were
reduced to hunger. The contrast with today&rsquo;s Germany is mind-blowing. With the
help of the winning countries, sure, but predominantly and undoubtedly thanks
to grit and desire for rebirth, Germany resurged from the catastrophe as
a modern country and a sought-out model for democracy, economy, justice, and
reception of diverse cultures.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
