<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>history on Nicola Iarocci</title>
    <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/tags/history/</link>
    <description>Recent content in history on Nicola Iarocci</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 30 Apr 2023 07:05:25 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://nicolaiarocci.com/tags/history/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Quoting Cicero</title>
      <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/quoting-cicero/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 30 Apr 2023 07:05:25 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nicolaiarocci.com/quoting-cicero/</guid>
      <description>Not to know what happened before one was born is always to be a child.
I found this Cicero quote on Lapham&amp;rsquo;s Quarterly&amp;rsquo;s about page. A little research dug out the supposedly original version found in Orator Ad M. Brutum (46 BC). It goes like this:
To be ignorant of what occurred before you were born is to remain always a child. For what is the worth of human life, unless it is woven into the life of our ancestors by the records of history?</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The indictment against Sparta</title>
      <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/the-indictment-against-sparta/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Aug 2022 07:05:25 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nicolaiarocci.com/the-indictment-against-sparta/</guid>
      <description>Bret Devereaux has long been my go-to source for all things ancient and military history. One thing I somehow missed reading from his incredibly resourceful website is the This Isn&amp;rsquo;t Sparta series. He recently published a three-year-anniversary series retrospective which promptly surfaced on my RSS feed, giving me a chance to catch up over the holidays. The whole thing is a very long read, with some installments more engaging than others but overall very enjoyable, eye-opening, and information dense.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Book Review: King and Emperor, A New Life of Charlemagne</title>
      <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/book-review-king-and-emperor-a-new-life-of-charlemagne/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 31 Oct 2021 07:05:25 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nicolaiarocci.com/book-review-king-and-emperor-a-new-life-of-charlemagne/</guid>
      <description>In this scholarly biography by Janet L. Nelson, Charlemagne is stripped back from the years of mythologizing and idolizing that have occurred since his death. He is presented as distinctly human, and this book is the first time I have felt I could reasonably understand Charlemagne as the man he was, not the man he has since been painted to be. Moreover, Nelson is excellent in her discussions of Charlemagne&amp;rsquo;s wives and their roles.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Book Review. Eight Days in May: The Final Collapse of the Third Reich</title>
      <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/book-review.-eight-days-in-may-the-final-collapse-of-the-third-reich/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 18 Jul 2021 07:05:25 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nicolaiarocci.com/book-review.-eight-days-in-may-the-final-collapse-of-the-third-reich/</guid>
      <description>Volker Ullrich&amp;rsquo;s Eight Days in May describes the period from April 30, 1945, the day of Hitler&amp;rsquo;s suicide, to May 8, the day of signing the German capitulation, with significant jumps backwards in time and some hops in the future. We&amp;rsquo;re covering only eight days, and the dictator dies on day one. What essential events might ever have happened in such a short period? Well, many pivotal ones, as this well-researched work shows us.</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
