<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>space on Nicola Iarocci</title>
    <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/tags/space/</link>
    <description>Recent content in space on Nicola Iarocci</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 01 May 2023 07:05:25 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://nicolaiarocci.com/tags/space/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>The religious aspects of the corporate space race</title>
      <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/the-religious-aspects-of-the-corporate-space-race/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 May 2023 07:05:25 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nicolaiarocci.com/the-religious-aspects-of-the-corporate-space-race/</guid>
      <description>A fascinating article surfaced on Nautilus last week. Mary-Jane Rubenstein, a professor of religion and science in society at Wesleyan University, shares her concerns about the technical strides and aspirations of Elon Musk&amp;rsquo;s SpaceX, the company&amp;rsquo;s mission to enable thousands of people to live on Mars, and the ethics of terraforming the planet to be more like Earth. What&amp;rsquo;s intriguing, though, is Rubenstein&amp;rsquo;s thoughts about the religious underpinnings of the United States space program and how even modern science is still hostage to imperialistic Christian ideas.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Sun in high resolution</title>
      <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/the-sun-in-high-resolution/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Apr 2022 07:05:25 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nicolaiarocci.com/the-sun-in-high-resolution/</guid>
      <description>The Sun as seen by Solar Orbiter in extreme ultraviolet light from a distance of roughly 75 million kilometres. The image is a mosaic of 25 individual images taken on 7 March by the high resolution telescope of the Extreme Ultraviolet Imager (EUI) instrument. Taken at a wavelength of 17 nanometers, in the extreme ultraviolet region of the electromagnetic spectrum, this image reveals the Sun’s upper atmosphere, the corona, which has a temperature of around a million degrees Celsius.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Go James Webb</title>
      <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/go-james-webb/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 10 Jan 2022 07:05:25 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nicolaiarocci.com/go-james-webb/</guid>
      <description>It&amp;rsquo;s now old news that the James Webb Telescope was successfully launched on Christmas Day. But last Saturday marked another historic moment for this incredible human artifact:
After a quarter-century of effort by tens of thousands of people, more than $10 billion in taxpayer funding, and some 350 deployment mechanisms that had to go just so, the James Webb Space Telescope fully unfurled its wings. The massive spacecraft completed its final deployments, and, by God, the process went smoothly.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the incredible opportunities offered by Starship</title>
      <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/on-the-incredible-opportunities-offered-by-starship/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Dec 2021 07:05:25 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nicolaiarocci.com/on-the-incredible-opportunities-offered-by-starship/</guid>
      <description>Space-junkie me is back, this time reading about the innumerable opportunities that SpaceX&amp;rsquo;s Starship will offer once it becomes operational, hopefully no later than this year or the next. In his Science Upside for Starship, the exceptionally knowledgeable Casey Handmer makes a case for Starship relevance in the future of space exploration by listing an astounding number of reasonable use-cases for the vessel.
I think it is relatively straightforward to think of cool things to do with SpaceX Starships, so recent posts have focused on trying to understand the more mixed consequences for incumbent industrial organizations that are not ideally positioned to exploit the coming advances.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Earth Restored</title>
      <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/earth-restored/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 25 Apr 2021 07:05:25 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nicolaiarocci.com/earth-restored/</guid>
      <description>Only 24 people have journeyed far enough to see the whole Earth against the black of space. The images they brought back changed our world. Here is a selection of the most beautiful photographs of Earth — iconic images and unknown gems — digitally restored to their full glory.
Toby Ord&amp;rsquo;s recent Earth Restored project is a must-see.
Subscribe to the newsletter, the RSS feed, or follow @nicolaiarocci on Twitter</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Perseverance made it to Mars on twenty-year-old hardware</title>
      <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/perseverance-made-it-to-mars-on-twenty-year-old-hardware/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 19 Feb 2021 07:05:25 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nicolaiarocci.com/perseverance-made-it-to-mars-on-twenty-year-old-hardware/</guid>
      <description>I&amp;rsquo;m a space junkie. So tonight, like all the other space junkies on the planet, I watched in awe as Perseverance seamlessly and beautifully landed on the surface of Mars. This is a phenomenal achievement. Of course, I will eagerly follow her1 progress.
As I was following the live broadcast, I wondered: What kind of hardware and software runs all this incredible technology? It was launched in 2020, so it must be some cutting-edge stuff.</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
