<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>writing on Nicola Iarocci</title>
    <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/tags/writing/</link>
    <description>Recent content in writing on Nicola Iarocci</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <copyright>Produced / Written / Maintained by [Nicola Iarocci](/) since 2010</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 09 Dec 2022 07:05:25 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://nicolaiarocci.com/tags/writing/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Writing is Magic</title>
      <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/writing-is-magic/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 09 Dec 2022 07:05:25 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nicolaiarocci.com/writing-is-magic/</guid>
      <description>I find, more often than not, that I understand something much less well when I sit down to write about it than when I&amp;rsquo;m thinking about it in the shower. In fact, I find that I change my own mind on things a lot when I try write them down. It really is a powerful tool for finding clarity in your own mind. Once you have clarity in your own mind, you&amp;rsquo;re much more able to explain it to others.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<blockquote>
<p>I find, more often than not, that I understand something much less well when
I sit down to write about it than when I&rsquo;m thinking about it in the shower.
In fact, I find that I change my own mind on things a lot when I try write
them down. It really is a powerful tool for finding clarity in your own mind.
Once you have clarity in your own mind, you&rsquo;re much more able to explain it
to others.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>More <a href="https://brooker.co.za/blog/2022/11/08/writing.html">here</a>.</p>
<p><em>Subscribe to the <a href="https://buttondown.email/nicolaiarocci">newsletter</a>, the <a href="https://nicolaiarocci.com/index.xml">RSS feed</a>, or follow @<a href="http://twitter.com/nicolaiarocci">nicolaiarocci</a> on Twitter</em></p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On Programming and Writing</title>
      <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/on-programming-and-writing/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 May 2021 07:05:25 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nicolaiarocci.com/on-programming-and-writing/</guid>
      <description>My brilliant friend Salvatore Sanfilippo (otherwise known as antirez of Redis fame) has an interesting write-up on his website. How similar is programming to prose writing? After getting his own feet wet with novel writing, he is convinced that the two activities share many common traits.
One year ago I paused my programming life and started writing a novel, with the illusion that my new activity was deeply different than the previous one.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>My brilliant friend Salvatore Sanfilippo (otherwise known as antirez of Redis
fame) has an interesting write-up on <a href="http://antirez.com/news/135">his website</a>. How similar is
programming to prose writing? After getting his own feet wet with novel
writing, he is convinced that the two activities share many common traits.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>One year ago I paused my programming life and started writing a novel, with
the illusion that my new activity was deeply different than the previous one.
A river of words later, written but more often rewritten, I’m pretty sure of
the contrary: programming big systems and writing novels have many common
traits and similar processes.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>It is a worthy read. I especially appreciate his conclusions on what
programming can actually learn from writing:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>I believe programming, in this regard, can learn something from writing: when
writing the first core of a new system, when the original creator is still
alone, isolated, able to do anything, she should pretend that this first core
is her only bullet. During the genesis of the system she should rewrite this
primitive kernel again and again, in order to find the best possible design. My
hypothesis is that this initial design will greatly inform what will happen
later: growing organically something that has a good initial structure will
result in a better system, even after years of distance from the original
creation, and even if the original core was just a tiny faction of the future
mass the system would eventually assume.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I suspect that his line of reasoning might be influenced by some sort
of confirmation bias<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1</a></sup>.  We are inclined to notice similarities between our
own activities, especially so when we perform them passionately. While common
patterns emerge naturally, differences, even remarkable ones, tend to go
unnoticed.</p>
<p><em>Subscribe to the <a href="https://buttondown.email/nicolaiarocci">newsletter</a>, the <a href="https://nicolaiarocci.com/index.xml">RSS feed</a>, or follow @<a href="http://twitter.com/nicolaiarocci">nicolaiarocci</a> on Twitter</em></p>
<div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
<hr>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1">
<p>The term <em>confirmation bias</em> is probably misused in this context. I am sure there is a better definition; it just eludes me and my own ignorance.&#160;<a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
</ol>
</div>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
