<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>docfx on Nicola Iarocci</title>
    <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/tags/docfx/</link>
    <description>Recent content in docfx on Nicola Iarocci</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <copyright>Produced / Written / Maintained by [Nicola Iarocci](/) since 2010</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 20 Jun 2023 07:05:25 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://nicolaiarocci.com/tags/docfx/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Homebrew and docfx don&#39;t like each other too</title>
      <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/homebrew-and-docfx-dont-like-each-other-too/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 20 Jun 2023 07:05:25 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nicolaiarocci.com/homebrew-and-docfx-dont-like-each-other-too/</guid>
      <description>Another day another Homebrew incompatibility emerges, this time with docfx, the technical documentation building tool of reference in .NET space. I&amp;rsquo;ve been using docfx for years to build the FatturaElettronica.NET website, and it&amp;rsquo;s always been working without a glitch. Lately, however, my builds have been failing with strange errors I was too lazy to diagnose until today when I decided to grasp the nettle and sort the whole thing out.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Another day another Homebrew incompatibility emerges, this time with <a href="https://dotnet.github.io/docfx/index.html">docfx</a>, the technical documentation building
tool of reference in .NET space. I&rsquo;ve been using docfx for years to build the <a href="https://fatturaelettronicaopensource.org">FatturaElettronica.NET</a> website, and it&rsquo;s
always been working without a glitch. Lately, however, my builds have been failing with strange errors I was too lazy to
diagnose until today when I decided to grasp the nettle and sort the whole thing out.</p>
<p>It took me an embarrassing time to realize that, while successful, my docfx updates (<code>dotnet tool update -g docfx</code>) were
being ignored. An old, Homebrew-installed version of docfx was being executed at my launches —a simple <code>which docfx</code>
revealed the issue. <code>brew uninstall docfx</code> finally set the updated, dotnet-installed version free of its chains, and it
is now merrily churning websites.</p>
<p>A similar issue emerged <a href="/homebrew-and-dotnet-8-preview-dont-like-each-other/">between Homebrew and .NET 8 Preview</a> only a few days ago. Lesson learned I&rsquo;m not installing
dotnet tools via Homebrew anymore. Or maybe, I might stay clear of Homebrew altogether.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
