<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>movies on Nicola Iarocci</title>
    <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/tags/movies/</link>
    <description>Recent content in movies on Nicola Iarocci</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <copyright>Produced / Written / Maintained by [Nicola Iarocci](/) since 2010</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 30 Dec 2023 10:08:07 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://nicolaiarocci.com/tags/movies/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Movie review: The Vast of the Night</title>
      <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/movie-review-the-vast-of-the-night/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 30 Dec 2023 10:08:07 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nicolaiarocci.com/movie-review-the-vast-of-the-night/</guid>
      <description>Yesterday evening, we watched &amp;ldquo;The Vast of the Night&amp;rdquo;, and what a pleasant surprise it was.
One night, in a small New Mexico town, a girl who works at a local radio station and an older reporter boy listen to a recording of some strange noises. Through the radio and its listeners, throughout a single night, they uncover a series of sighting stories that, from clue to clue and radio testimony to radio testimony, bring them close to uncovering something big.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Yesterday evening, we watched &ldquo;<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Vast_of_Night">The Vast of the
Night</a>&rdquo;, and what a pleasant
surprise it was.</p>
<p>One night, in a small New Mexico town, a girl who works at a local radio station
and an older reporter boy listen to a recording of some strange noises. Through
the radio and its listeners, throughout a single night, they uncover a series of
sighting stories that, from clue to clue and radio testimony to radio testimony,
bring them close to uncovering something big.</p>
<p>It has a distinctive retro soundtrack, and its beauty is the pleasure of the
stories told. At the center of everything always remains the mystery the two
protagonists try to investigate in one night, approaching the truth from
testimony to testimony. A good part of the film lies in the classic elements of
science fiction, namely the discovery (perhaps) of something from another
planet; another part, however, is the creation of the overwhelming sense of
excitement of two people from a small provincial town who increasingly feel they
are part of something important.</p>
<p>The photography, lighting, and camerawork are stellar:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>At the midpoint, Patterson wows with a tracking shot that seems to race a
half-mile down a quiet street, take a left-hook through a parking lot, sprint
through an ongoing basketball game, and zip up the crowded bleachers before
plunging out of a window. It&rsquo;s effective razzle-dazzle that will probably get
the young Oklahoman hired to make something 20 times The Vast of Night&rsquo;s budget.
Yet, the ambition behind it is just as impressive – as is the crew&rsquo;s creativity
at spinning financial limitations into magic.&quot; <br>
&ndash;Amy Nicholson, <a href="https://variety.com/2019/film/reviews/the-vast-of-night-review-1203335505/">Variety</a>.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>&ldquo;The Vast of the Night&rdquo; is a small, independent, character-driven debut film that
perfectly captures America&rsquo;s province life in the 50s and cleverly leverages
those atmospheres. Inventive and charming, it is also a homage to The Twilight
Zone, The War Of The Worlds (the radio station name is WOTW), and others.</p>
<p>Serena found it slow, especially at the beginning. I can understand that: the
first twenty minutes are a long walk-and-talk between the two protagonists, but
oh boy, look the world-building (and camera work) happening right there!</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
