<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>milesdavis on Nicola Iarocci</title>
    <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/tags/milesdavis/</link>
    <description>Recent content in milesdavis on Nicola Iarocci</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 27 Jun 2021 07:05:25 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://nicolaiarocci.com/tags/milesdavis/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>A Beginner&#39;s Guide to Miles Davis</title>
      <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/a-beginners-guide-to-miles-davis/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 27 Jun 2021 07:05:25 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nicolaiarocci.com/a-beginners-guide-to-miles-davis/</guid>
      <description>Sam Enright assembled a friendly Beginner&amp;rsquo;s Guide to Miles Davis. If you&amp;rsquo;ve always been curious about jazz but never really managed to get into it, then this resource might serve as a good starting point. I cannot say I&amp;rsquo;m one hundred per cent aligned with his choices, but we&amp;rsquo;re close. One remarkable statement I concur with is this one:
Jazz is so interesting to me because of its fusion of intricate underlying structure with improvisation and spontaneity.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Sam Enright assembled a friendly <a href="https://samenright.com/2021/06/06/a-beginners-guide-to-miles-davis/">Beginner&rsquo;s Guide to Miles Davis</a>. If
you&rsquo;ve always been curious about jazz but never really managed to get into it,
then this resource might serve as a good starting point. I cannot say I&rsquo;m one
hundred per cent aligned with his choices, but we&rsquo;re close. One remarkable
statement I concur with is this one:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Jazz is so interesting to me because of its fusion of intricate underlying
structure with improvisation and spontaneity. As Ken Burns put it, jazz is
“familiar, but brand new every night”. Moreover, I enjoy the intellectual
demandingness of jazz as a genre. Jazz musicians seem to be the most
thoughtful and intelligent of any genre. Many of the more Avant Garde songs
mentioned in this post don’t sound good unless you’re really concentrating.
Some of it sounds cacophonous to a newcomer. This is why jazz is considerably
more difficult to get into than other genres and has a lack of listenership
among the youth.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Sam put a lot of effort into his selection, and it shows. Should his list be
overwhelming for you, my shortcut advice would be: listen to Kind of Blue,
especially the first two tracks, So What and Freddie Freeloader. If they don&rsquo;t
move you, I am sorry, you&rsquo;re probably not a jazz person.</p>
<p><em>Subscribe to the <a href="https://nicolaiarocci.substack.com">newsletter</a>, the <a href="https://nicolaiarocci.com/index.xml">RSS feed</a>, or follow @<a href="http://twitter.com/nicolaiarocci">nicolaiarocci</a> on Twitter</em></p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
