<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>games on Nicola Iarocci</title>
    <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/tags/games/</link>
    <description>Recent content in games on Nicola Iarocci</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <copyright>Produced / Written / Maintained by [Nicola Iarocci](/) since 2010</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 21 Mar 2021 07:05:25 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://nicolaiarocci.com/tags/games/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>My Pusher of Digital Memorabilia</title>
      <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/my-pusher-of-digital-memorabilia/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 21 Mar 2021 07:05:25 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nicolaiarocci.com/my-pusher-of-digital-memorabilia/</guid>
      <description>If you are a grumpy old geek like me, you are probably a sucker for vintage computer games too. I don&amp;rsquo;t play games. Not anymore. I still enjoy reading about them, though. I guess it&amp;rsquo;s mostly nostalgia. I also believe that the mid-80s up to the mid-90s really was the golden age of computer games. In my book, innovation started with Infocom&amp;rsquo;s text adventures and soft-ended with Origin&amp;rsquo;s Ultima Online. After that, it&amp;rsquo;s been a constant evolution.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>If you are a grumpy old geek like me, you are probably a sucker for vintage
computer games too. I don&rsquo;t play games. Not anymore. I still enjoy reading
about them, though. I guess it&rsquo;s mostly nostalgia. I also believe that the
mid-80s up to the mid-90s really was the golden age of computer games. In my
book, innovation started with Infocom&rsquo;s text adventures and soft-ended with
Origin&rsquo;s Ultima Online. After that, it&rsquo;s been a constant evolution. &ldquo;Harder,
better, faster, stronger&rdquo;, yes, but hardly a revolution.</p>
<p>My pusher of digital memorabilia is Jimmy Maher, also known as [The Digital
Antiquarian][5]. One month ago, he wrote a [fantastic article][3] on Origin&rsquo;s
Ultima VIII Pagan. Then, just the other day, he doubled down with a [terrific
piece][4] on Looking Glass&rsquo; System Shock. Both are games I played fervidly<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1</a></sup>.</p>
<p>Maher is not kind to Pagan:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>But then, for the eighth game in the mainline Ultima series, Origin decided
to try something just a little bit different. They made a game in which you
played a thoughtless jerk moving on rails through a linear series of events;
in which you never went to Britannia at all, but stayed instead on
a miserable hellhole of a world called Pagan; in which you spent the whole
game adventuring alone (after all, who would want to adventure with a jerk
like you?); in which the core mechanics were jumping between pedestals like
Super Mario and pounding your enemies over the head with your big old hammer.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>It hurts to admit it, but he&rsquo;s exactly right. Nonetheless, I enjoyed exploring
Pagan&rsquo;s world. When I later joined the Ultima Online Beta, it was amazing to
see that the same graphic engine and all of Pagan&rsquo;s art were recycled.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" src="/images/system-shock.jpg#right" alt="System Shock"  />

System Shock was a game I loved. I found it to be revolutionary. Games like
this one were precisely the kind of entertainment I strived for: immersive
simulations.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>[&hellip;] Moving through said spaces, picking up bits and pieces of the horrible
events which have unfolded there, quickly becomes highly unnerving. The sense
of embodied realism that clings to every aspect of the game is key to the
sense of genuine, oppressive fear it creates in its player. Tellingly,
Looking Glass liked to call System Shock a “simulation,” even though it
simulates nothing that has ever existed in the real world. The word is rather
shorthand for its absolute commitment to the truth — fictional truth, yes,
but truth nevertheless — of the world it drops you into.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I have always been a System Shock guy more than a DOOM person. I really like
how Maher compares the two games and the software companies that produced them,
more or less in the same time-span<sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">2</a></sup>.</p>
<p>In Maher&rsquo;s reconstructions, what I find to be more appealing is not the games
themselves with their mechanics but rather the history behind them. How the
dev-team conceived and then developed their projects.</p>
<p>After so many years, I am thankful to Maher for bringing these two games back
to memory. Now, I am impatiently waiting for his Ultima Online installment.
I know it <em>must</em> be on his list, right?</p>
<div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
<hr>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1">
<p>In my library, I keep the original Pagan box as a relic, along with Ultima VII Serpent Island and a few other titles from around that age:  Spectrum Holobyte&rsquo;s Falcon 3.0, Command and Conquer, Dune II Battle for Arrakis, Ultima Online: Charter Edition, and a few others.&#160;<a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
<li id="fn:2">
<p>By the way, if you haven&rsquo;t already, I strongly advise you to read <em>Masters of Doom: How Two Guys Created an Empire and Transformed Pop Culture</em> by David Kushner.
[3]: <a href="https://www.filfre.net/2021/02/ultima-viii-or-how-to-destroy-a-gaming-franchise-in-one-easy-step/">https://www.filfre.net/2021/02/ultima-viii-or-how-to-destroy-a-gaming-franchise-in-one-easy-step/</a>
[4]: <a href="https://www.filfre.net/2021/03/system-shock/">https://www.filfre.net/2021/03/system-shock/</a>
[5]: <a href="https://www.filfre.net/">https://www.filfre.net/</a>&#160;<a href="#fnref:2" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
</ol>
</div>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
