<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>jazz on Nicola Iarocci</title>
    <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/tags/jazz/</link>
    <description>Recent content in jazz on Nicola Iarocci</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <copyright>Produced / Written / Maintained by [Nicola Iarocci](/) since 2010</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 25 Apr 2023 07:05:25 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://nicolaiarocci.com/tags/jazz/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>The Interstellar Style of Sun Ra</title>
      <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/the-interstellar-style-of-sun-ra/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Apr 2023 07:05:25 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nicolaiarocci.com/the-interstellar-style-of-sun-ra/</guid>
      <description>Pitchfork has a great piece on Sun Ra and his legacy. It&amp;rsquo;s worth reading if you&amp;rsquo;re a fan, even more so if you know nothing about him.
But what Sun Ra had done, and done best, was reminding earthlings everywhere that he wasn’t mortal. He was a signifier of a life beyond the reality of this one. He was a visual reassurance of the presence of another world. He brought the cosmos to the streets, and, most importantly, he was a reminder that one does not have to subscribe to the status quo—musically, stylistically, politically, ideologically.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Pitchfork has a great piece on Sun Ra and his legacy. It&rsquo;s worth reading if you&rsquo;re a fan, even more so if you know
nothing about him.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>But what Sun Ra had done, and done best, was reminding earthlings everywhere that he wasn’t mortal. He was a
signifier of a life beyond the reality of this one. He was a visual reassurance of the presence of another world. He
brought the cosmos to the streets, and, most importantly, he was a reminder that one does not have to subscribe to
the status quo—musically, stylistically, politically, ideologically.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>More <a href="https://pitchfork.com/features/from-the-pitchfork-review/9866-the-interstellar-style-of-sun-ra/">here</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A stunning visualization of John Coltrane&#39;s &#39;Giant Steps&#39; solo</title>
      <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/a-stunning-visualization-of-john-coltranes-giant-steps-solo/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Aug 2022 07:05:25 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nicolaiarocci.com/a-stunning-visualization-of-john-coltranes-giant-steps-solo/</guid>
      <description>Open Culture [shared][1] a &amp;ldquo;jaw-dropping visualization of John Coltrane&amp;rsquo;s &amp;lsquo;Giant Steps&amp;rsquo; solo.&amp;rdquo;
Indeed, it is stunning, beautiful and valuable. A visualization like this makes music much more accessible. Quoting Open Culture:
Coltrane’s complexity is daunting for the most accomplished musicians. How much more so for non-musicians? It can seem like “you need a doctorate of music to go anywhere near his recordings,” Nicholson writes. But “nothing could be further from the truth.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Open Culture [shared][1] a &ldquo;jaw-dropping visualization of John Coltrane&rsquo;s &lsquo;Giant
Steps&rsquo; solo.&rdquo;</p>
<p>
<div style="position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;">
  <iframe src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/Pxw4AQLVLis" style="position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;" allowfullscreen title="YouTube Video"></iframe>
</div>

<!-- raw HTML omitted -->
Indeed, it is stunning, beautiful and valuable. A visualization like this makes
music much more accessible. Quoting Open Culture:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Coltrane’s complexity is daunting for the most accomplished musicians. How
much more so for non-musicians? It can seem like “you need a doctorate of
music to go anywhere near his recordings,” Nicholson writes. But “nothing
could be further from the truth.” With its dancing lines and circles,
Brother’s visualization gives us another way to appreciate the “sheer joy of
music making and the power and energy of his playing” that inspires students,
serious fans, and newcomers alike through “universal values that still speak
to us now.”</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I suddenly want all my music visualized like this.</p>
<p>My nerdiness alarm immediately went off, and I wanted to know more, so I dug
a little. Open Culture presentation is remarkable, but what&rsquo;s mind-boggling is
the author&rsquo;s [in-depth article][2] on the fractal structure of the solo. It&rsquo;s
all about fractals, baby!</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Chet Baker, born to be cool</title>
      <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/chet-baker-born-to-be-cool/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 29 Nov 2021 07:05:25 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nicolaiarocci.com/chet-baker-born-to-be-cool/</guid>
      <description>A great piece of writing on jazz has recently been posted on The Smart Set. In [Born to be cool][1], Matthew Duffus writes about jazz trumpeter Chet Baker, reporting about his troubled life, musical prowess, influence, and legacy. Some facts are well known, like the reception and then the competition with trumpet legends such as Miles Davis and Dizzy Gillespie; other tidbits are less known (to me at least). On Baker legacy:</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>A great piece of writing on jazz has recently been posted on The Smart Set. In
[Born to be cool][1], Matthew Duffus writes about jazz trumpeter Chet Baker,
reporting about his troubled life, musical prowess, influence, and legacy. Some
facts are well known, like the reception and then the competition with trumpet
legends such as Miles Davis and Dizzy Gillespie; other tidbits are less known
(to me at least). On Baker legacy:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>As I hope this makes clear, with Baker, music is only part of the story. In
order to fully grasp his significance within popular culture, we must also
look at the mythos surrounding him and the often less salacious truth that
lies beneath that dramatic surface. It is only by looking concurrently at
Baker’s music and image that we can truly understand why he has endured
despite the existence of more technically-gifted trumpeters and impressive
vocalists. Many such musicians came to the fore throughout his tumultuous
lifetime, but few have captured the public’s attention or endured in the way
that Baker has. For all of his limited range, not to mention the dramatic
loss of the youthful good looks that are at the root of his image, he managed
to make a living as a musician for decades and has persisted in the popular
imagination and jazz fans’ collections almost 35 years after his death.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I&rsquo;ve always listened to Barker with little attention, knowing and researching
little about the artist and his music. This article fills a hole. Also, I am
grateful to Duffus for letting me discover a gem like Live in Tokyo, an album
recorded on stage less than a year before his premature, tragic death and then
released posthumously. I am listening to it as I write this note, and man isn&rsquo;t
it just great.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A Beginner&#39;s Guide to Miles Davis</title>
      <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/a-beginners-guide-to-miles-davis/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 27 Jun 2021 07:05:25 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nicolaiarocci.com/a-beginners-guide-to-miles-davis/</guid>
      <description>Sam Enright assembled a friendly [Beginner&amp;rsquo;s Guide to Miles Davis][1]. If you&amp;rsquo;ve always been curious about jazz but never really managed to get into it, then this resource might serve as a good starting point. I cannot say I&amp;rsquo;m one hundred per cent aligned with his choices, but we&amp;rsquo;re close. One remarkable statement I concur with is this one:
Jazz is so interesting to me because of its fusion of intricate underlying structure with improvisation and spontaneity.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Sam Enright assembled a friendly [Beginner&rsquo;s Guide to Miles Davis][1]. If
you&rsquo;ve always been curious about jazz but never really managed to get into it,
then this resource might serve as a good starting point. I cannot say I&rsquo;m one
hundred per cent aligned with his choices, but we&rsquo;re close. One remarkable
statement I concur with is this one:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Jazz is so interesting to me because of its fusion of intricate underlying
structure with improvisation and spontaneity. As Ken Burns put it, jazz is
“familiar, but brand new every night”. Moreover, I enjoy the intellectual
demandingness of jazz as a genre. Jazz musicians seem to be the most
thoughtful and intelligent of any genre. Many of the more Avant Garde songs
mentioned in this post don’t sound good unless you’re really concentrating.
Some of it sounds cacophonous to a newcomer. This is why jazz is considerably
more difficult to get into than other genres and has a lack of listenership
among the youth.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Sam put a lot of effort into his selection, and it shows. Should his list be
overwhelming for you, my shortcut advice would be: listen to Kind of Blue,
especially the first two tracks, So What and Freddie Freeloader. If they don&rsquo;t
move you, I am sorry, you&rsquo;re probably not a jazz person.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Real Book (of Jazz)</title>
      <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/the-real-book-of-jazz/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 08 Apr 2021 07:05:25 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nicolaiarocci.com/the-real-book-of-jazz/</guid>
      <description>What a fascinating read. It sits right at the intersection of two of my (too many) vicious interests: Jazz music and books.
Since the mid-1970s, almost every jazz musician has owned a copy of the same book. It has a peach-colored cover, a chunky, 1970s-style logo, and a black plastic binding. It’s delightfully homemade-looking—like it was printed by a bunch of teenagers at a Kinkos. And inside is the sheet music for hundreds of common jazz tunes—also known as jazz “standards”—all meticulously notated by hand.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>What a fascinating read. It sits right at the intersection of two of my (too
many) vicious interests: Jazz music and books.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Since the mid-1970s, almost every jazz musician has owned a copy of the same
book. It has a peach-colored cover, a chunky, 1970s-style logo, and a black
plastic binding. It’s delightfully homemade-looking—like it was printed by
a bunch of teenagers at a Kinkos. And inside is the sheet music for hundreds
of common jazz tunes—also known as jazz “standards”—all meticulously notated
by hand. It’s called the Real Book.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>But if you were going to music school in the 1970s, you couldn’t just buy
a copy of the Real Book at the campus bookstore. Because the Real Book… was
illegal. The world’s most popular collection of Jazz music was a totally
unlicensed publication. It was a self-published book created without
permission from music publishers or songwriters. It was duplicated at
photocopy shops and sold on street corners, out of the trunks of cars, and
under the table at music stores where people used secret code words to make
the exchange. The full story of how the Real Book came to be this bootleg
bible of jazz is a complicated one. It’s a story about what happens when an
insurgent, improvisational art form like Jazz gets codified and becomes
something that you can learn from a book.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>The whole story, both as text or podcast, is available [here][1].</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
