<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>dfw on Nicola Iarocci</title>
    <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/tags/dfw/</link>
    <description>Recent content in dfw on Nicola Iarocci</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <copyright>Produced / Written / Maintained by [Nicola Iarocci](/) since 2010</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 22 Jan 2023 07:05:25 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://nicolaiarocci.com/tags/dfw/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>This is Water by David Foster Wallace</title>
      <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/this-is-water-by-david-foster-wallace/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 22 Jan 2023 07:05:25 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nicolaiarocci.com/this-is-water-by-david-foster-wallace/</guid>
      <description>Slow Sunday morning, while surfing the YouTube ocean, I stumbled upon the audio recording of David Foster Wallace&amp;rsquo;s This is Water speech. Any DFW fan knows about the commencement speech he famously gave at Kenyon College in 2005, and I&amp;rsquo;m probably one of the few who hadn&amp;rsquo;t yet listened to it. So this morning, I hit the play button and was blown away by it. Unsurprisingly, I guess, as the speech was met with universal acclaim.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Slow Sunday morning, while surfing the YouTube ocean, I stumbled upon the audio
recording of David Foster Wallace&rsquo;s This is Water speech. Any DFW fan knows
about the commencement speech he famously gave at Kenyon College in 2005, and
I&rsquo;m probably one of the few who hadn&rsquo;t yet listened to it. So this morning, I
hit the play button and was blown away by it. Unsurprisingly, I guess, as the
speech was met with universal acclaim.</p>
<p>I suspect my being an adult father of three kids played a role, as I was
nodding all the time, often feeling emotional about it. Anyway, <a href="https://youtu.be/DCbGM4mqEVw">here&rsquo;s the
YouTube recording</a> I&rsquo;m talking about, and <a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20080213082423/http://www.marginalia.org/dfw_kenyon_commencement.html">here&rsquo;s a transcription</a> I dug
out of the Internet Archive.</p>
<p>Spoiler warning, I&rsquo;m now going to quote <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/This_Is_Water">Wikipedia</a>, where I found a good
summarization of the themes covered:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>The speech covers subjects including the difficulty of empathy, the
unimportance of being well-adjusted, and the apparent lonesomeness of adult
life. It suggests that higher education&rsquo;s overall purpose is to consciously
choose how to perceive others, think about meaning, and act appropriately in
everyday life. Wallace argues that the true freedom acquired through
education is the ability to be fully conscious and sympathetic. Authors
Robert K. Bolger and Scott Korb have said that Wallace used the speech to
outline his spiritual philosophy and the methods he used to find peace when
wrestling with anxiety and depression.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I also learned on Wikipedia that the speech&rsquo;s themes were expanded in Wallace&rsquo;s
novel <em>The Pale King</em>, posthumously published in 2011. With all its
intimidating size, the Pale King has been sitting on my nightstand (aka reading
list) for ages. Maybe it&rsquo;s time to deal with it.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quoting David Foster Wallace</title>
      <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/quoting-david-foster-wallace/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 31 Mar 2022 06:05:25 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nicolaiarocci.com/quoting-david-foster-wallace/</guid>
      <description>Because here’s something else that’s true. In the day-to-day trenches of adult life, there is actually no such thing as atheism. There is no such thing as not worshipping. Everybody worships. The only choice we get is what to worship. And an outstanding reason for choosing some sort of God or spiritual-type thing to worship-be it J.C. or Allah, be it Yahweh or the Wiccan mother-goddess or the Four Noble Truths or some infrangible set of ethical principles-is that pretty much anything else you worship will eat you alive.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<blockquote>
<p>Because here’s something else that’s true. In the day-to-day trenches of
adult life, there is actually no such thing as atheism. There is no such
thing as not worshipping. Everybody worships. The only choice we get is what
to worship. And an outstanding reason for choosing some sort of God or
spiritual-type thing to worship-be it J.C. or Allah, be it Yahweh or the
Wiccan mother-goddess or the Four Noble Truths or some infrangible set of
ethical principles-is that pretty much anything else you worship will eat you
alive. If you worship money and things-if they are where you tap real meaning
in life-then you will never have enough. Never feel you have enough. It’s the
truth.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>Worship your own body and beauty and sexual allure and you will always feel
ugly, and when time and age start showing, you will die a million deaths
before they finally plant you. On one level, we all know this stuff
already-it’s been codified as myths, proverbs, clichés, bromides, epigrams,
parables: the skeleton of every great story. The trick is keeping the truth
up-front in daily consciousness. Worship power-you will feel weak and afraid,
and you will need ever more power over others to keep the fear at bay.
Worship your intellect, being seen as smart-you will end up feeling stupid,
a fraud, always on the verge of being found out. And so on.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>&ndash;David Foster Wallace in &ldquo;<a href="https://web.archive.org/web/20080213082423/http://www.marginalia.org/dfw_kenyon_commencement.html">This is Water</a>&rdquo; (<a href="https://macwright.com/2022/03/29/recently.html">via</a>)</p>
</blockquote>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Book Review: Consider the Lobster</title>
      <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/book-review-consider-the-lobster/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Dec 2021 07:05:25 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nicolaiarocci.com/book-review-consider-the-lobster/</guid>
      <description>I found a Consider the Lobster review on Goodreads that almost precisely matches my thoughts on DFW and the book. Hence, given the lazy Christmas-break mood I am in right now, I am conceding myself the right to copy-paste and edit David&amp;rsquo;s review right away.
I know of nobody else who writes as thoughtfully and intelligently as DFW. That he manages to write so informatively, with humor and genuine wit, on almost any subject under the sun is mind-blowing – it&amp;rsquo;s also why I am willing to forgive his occasional stylistic excesses.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I found a Consider the Lobster <a href="https://www.goodreads.com/review/show/14143044">review</a> on Goodreads that almost precisely
matches my thoughts on DFW and the book. Hence, given the lazy Christmas-break
mood I am in right now, I am conceding myself the right to copy-paste and edit
David&rsquo;s review right away.</p>
<hr>
<p>I know of nobody else who writes as thoughtfully and intelligently as DFW. That
he manages to write so informatively, with humor and genuine wit, on almost any
subject under the sun is mind-blowing – it&rsquo;s also why I am willing to forgive
his occasional stylistic excesses. (Can you spell &lsquo;footnote&rsquo;?) You may not have
a strong interest in lobsters or pornography, but the essays in question are
terrific. The reporting on Ziegler and McCain is outstanding, heartbreakingly
so, because it makes the relative shallowness of most reporting painfully
evident.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" src="/images/consider-the-lobster.jpg#right" alt="Consider the Lobster"  />

Yes, I know all about his weaknesses - the digressions, the rampant footnote
abuse, the flaunting of his extraordinary erudition. I know all this, and
I don&rsquo;t care. Because when he is in top form, there&rsquo;s nobody else I would
instead read. The man is hilarious; I think he&rsquo;s a mensch, and I don&rsquo;t believe
he parades his erudition to prove how smart he is. I think he can&rsquo;t help
himself - it&rsquo;s a consequence of his wide-ranging curiosity. At heart, he&rsquo;s
a geek but a charming, hyper-articulate geek. Who is almost frighteningly
bright.</p>
<hr>
<p>If you have never read DFW, my advice would be to start with his non-fiction,
which is way more accessible than his fiction (with the notable exception of
The Brook of the System, which was my first adored DFW reading.)</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
