<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>dfw on Nicola Iarocci</title>
    <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/tags/dfw/</link>
    <description>Recent content in dfw on Nicola Iarocci</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 22 Jan 2023 07:05:25 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://nicolaiarocci.com/tags/dfw/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>This is Water by David Foster Wallace</title>
      <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/this-is-water-by-david-foster-wallace/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 22 Jan 2023 07:05:25 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nicolaiarocci.com/this-is-water-by-david-foster-wallace/</guid>
      <description>Slow Sunday morning, while surfing the YouTube ocean, I stumbled upon the audio recording of David Foster Wallace&amp;rsquo;s This is Water speech. Any DFW fan knows about the commencement speech he famously gave at Kenyon College in 2005, and I&amp;rsquo;m probably one of the few who hadn&amp;rsquo;t yet listened to it. So this morning, I hit the play button and was blown away by it. Unsurprisingly, I guess, as the speech was met with universal acclaim.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Quoting David Foster Wallace</title>
      <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/quoting-david-foster-wallace/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 31 Mar 2022 06:05:25 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nicolaiarocci.com/quoting-david-foster-wallace/</guid>
      <description>Because here’s something else that’s true. In the day-to-day trenches of adult life, there is actually no such thing as atheism. There is no such thing as not worshipping. Everybody worships. The only choice we get is what to worship. And an outstanding reason for choosing some sort of God or spiritual-type thing to worship-be it J.C. or Allah, be it Yahweh or the Wiccan mother-goddess or the Four Noble Truths or some infrangible set of ethical principles-is that pretty much anything else you worship will eat you alive.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Book Review: Consider the Lobster</title>
      <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/book-review-consider-the-lobster/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Dec 2021 07:05:25 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nicolaiarocci.com/book-review-consider-the-lobster/</guid>
      <description>I found a Consider the Lobster review on Goodreads that almost precisely matches my thoughts on DFW and the book. Hence, given the lazy Christmas-break mood I am in right now, I am conceding myself the right to copy-paste and edit David&amp;rsquo;s review right away.
I know of nobody else who writes as thoughtfully and intelligently as DFW. That he manages to write so informatively, with humor and genuine wit, on almost any subject under the sun is mind-blowing – it&amp;rsquo;s also why I am willing to forgive his occasional stylistic excesses.</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
