<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>speaking on Nicola Iarocci</title>
    <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/tags/speaking/</link>
    <description>Recent content in speaking on Nicola Iarocci</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 23 Nov 2023 07:05:25 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://nicolaiarocci.com/tags/speaking/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>I am speaking at the .NET Conference Italia 2023</title>
      <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/i-am-speaking-at-the-dotnet-conference-italia-2023/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Nov 2023 07:05:25 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nicolaiarocci.com/i-am-speaking-at-the-dotnet-conference-italia-2023/</guid>
      <description>In a few days, on Monday, December 4, at 10 a.m., I will present at the .NET Conference Italia 2023, which will be held at the Microsoft House in Milan. My session is titled &amp;ldquo;C#12 What&amp;rsquo;s new and interesting&amp;rdquo; and is part of a rich agenda focused on the recent release of .NET 8.
I presented on the same subject at a DevRomagna meetup a few months ago when C# 12 was in preview and still had several moving parts.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>I am speaking at WebDay 2023</title>
      <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/i-am-speaking-at-webday-2023/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 13 Mar 2023 07:05:25 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nicolaiarocci.com/i-am-speaking-at-webday-2023/</guid>
      <description>On Thursday, I will be speaking in Milan at WebDay 2023. Mine is a hands-on session on building a reliable and continuous end-to-end testing environment for web apps using Microsoft Playwright. If you attended my introductory Playwright session at WPC last year, Thursday&amp;rsquo;s session would be the ideal follow-up to that one, as I only briefly touched on CI deployments there.
Drawing from my experience doing the whole thing in production, I&amp;rsquo;ll essentially be live testing a Blazor app, then take the entire thing to remote CI via GitHub Actions.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the state of developer conferences</title>
      <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/on-the-state-of-developer-conferences/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Feb 2023 07:05:25 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nicolaiarocci.com/on-the-state-of-developer-conferences/</guid>
      <description>Brian Rinaldi has an insightful post on his blog about the current state of developer conferences, where &amp;lsquo;current state&amp;rsquo; means post-COVID pandemic. Brian is well-positioned to reason about this space as a long-time conference organizer. I appreciate that he also takes the time to explain how the developer conference business works. The core of his blog is about post-pandemic conference attendance, which has plunged.
independent, in-person developer conferences are hurting. Based on my own observation as well as talks with organizers and sponsors that I have come to know over the years, the average independent in-person event is still down 30-40% from pre-pandemic attendance levels.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>My session at WPC 2022</title>
      <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/my-session-at-wpc-2022/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Oct 2022 07:05:25 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nicolaiarocci.com/my-session-at-wpc-2022/</guid>
      <description>Yesterday I was at WPC 2022, &amp;ldquo;the most important Italian conference on Microsoft technologies&amp;rdquo;, where I presented a one-hour session titled &amp;ldquo;Reliable end-to-end testing for modern web apps with Microsoft Playwright.&amp;rdquo;
Attendance was great and there was a lot of excitement up in the air; it was evident that people were happy to meet and interact in person again. After the forced two years hiatus, it was great to be back at a big on-site conference, let alone speak at it.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>My Playwright session at WebDay 2022</title>
      <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/my-playwright-session-at-webday-2022/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 01 Apr 2022 06:05:25 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nicolaiarocci.com/my-playwright-session-at-webday-2022/</guid>
      <description>If you understand Italian, the recording of my Playwright session at UGIdotNET&amp;rsquo;s WebDay 2022 is now available on YouTube1. Playwright is a phenomenal cross-browser, cross-platform, cross-language, single-API, mobile-friendly front-end testing tool.
I&amp;rsquo;m looking forward to giving the same session in English sooner or later, but I should first win my laziness and start looking for exciting events with open CFPs. If you happen to know one, please let me know.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Seven years ago at FOSDEM</title>
      <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/seven-years-ago-at-fosdem/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 15 Feb 2021 07:05:25 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nicolaiarocci.com/seven-years-ago-at-fosdem/</guid>
      <description>About seven years ago, I presented the Eve Framework in a very crowded Python room at FOSDEM 2014 in Brussels. If you don&amp;rsquo;t know about FOSDEM, well, you should check it out. Every year thousands of developers who recognize themselves with the free and open-source movement gather in Brussels from all over the world. And I mean thousands of them. According to Wikipedia, since 2011, the meeting hosts about 4,000 visitors every year.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Upcoming speaking engagements, with ramblings</title>
      <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/upcoming-speaking-engagements-with-ramblings/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 29 Jan 2021 07:05:25 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nicolaiarocci.com/upcoming-speaking-engagements-with-ramblings/</guid>
      <description>I am presenting at two different events in February next month. Given the current COVID situation, that is entirely unexpected. In 2020 I only gave four talks, three of which were virtual. I am not holding my breath for 2021. Conferences are going virtual all year-long. Next year too, most likely.
There are some clear advantages in going virtual, but the final result is a net negative. Any conference junkie will tell you that she/he attends for the people first, and only then for the sessions themselves.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Una mattinata con MongoDB</title>
      <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/una-mattinata-con-mongodb/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Oct 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nicolaiarocci.com/una-mattinata-con-mongodb/</guid>
      <description>Il prossimo 24 ottobre sarò a Milano per A Morning with MongoDB, evento ufficiale 10gen nel corso del quale racconterò la mia esperienza nell’integrazione di MongoDB in una Web REST API. Partecipazione e registrazione sono gratuite: cosa aspettate?</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Sviluppare una RESTful Web API con Python, Flask e MongoDB</title>
      <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/sviluppare-una-restful-web-api-con-python-flask-e-mongodb/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 09 Jul 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nicolaiarocci.com/sviluppare-una-restful-web-api-con-python-flask-e-mongodb/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;La scorsa settimana a &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;EuroPython 2012&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt; ho tenuto un talk intitolato &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;Sviluppare una RESTful Web API con Python, Flask e MongoDB&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;. Mi ha fatto piacere riscontrare forte interesse sia per gli aspetti teorici dell’architettura REST che per la loro implementazione pratica con strumenti quali Flask e MongoDB. In entrambe le sessioni inglese e italiana mi sono state rivolte molte domande, sia in occasione delle Q&amp;amp;A plenarie che nei successivi colloqui informali. Parecchi anche i commenti ed i suggerimenti, davvero utili ed apprezzati (a quanto pare non sono l’unico che, forte di un background .NET, ha compiuto o sta per compiere il salto verso Python e il mondo open source).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Soprattutto ho rilevato una forte curiosità su MongoDB, un database non-relazionale verso il quale sembra prevalere un atteggiamento  di generale timidezza: “vorrei ma non oso”, insomma. Per quanto riguarda Flask direi che ormai, nel vasto firmamento dei micro web framework, è una stella che brilla di luce propria.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Offline / Online: superare la crisi anche grazie alla rete</title>
      <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/offline-online-superare-la-crisi-anche-grazie-alla-rete/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Apr 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nicolaiarocci.com/offline-online-superare-la-crisi-anche-grazie-alla-rete/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;La scorsa settimana ho partecipato come relatore alla prima edizione del &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;Ravenna CNA Barcamp&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt; sulla cultura d’impresa 2.0. &lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt;Offline / Online&lt;!-- raw HTML omitted --&gt; è il racconto di una esperienza vissuta sul campo; un case study su come il mercato del software si è evoluto nel corso degli anni passando dalla classica filiera lunga sul territorio, tipica degli anni ’90 e della prima metà dei 2000, alla vendita online dei giorni nostri. La crisi economica degli ultimi anni si è innestata in un processo evolutivo già in atto e inarrestabile, perlomeno per quanto riguarda il nostro settore:&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Speaker a EuroPython 2012</title>
      <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/speaker-a-europython-2012/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 13 Apr 2012 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nicolaiarocci.com/speaker-a-europython-2012/</guid>
      <description>EuroPython è la conferenza europea di riferimento per il linguaggio Python. Si terrà anche quest’anno a Firenze, dal 2 al 8 luglio. Sono in programma molti interventi davvero interessanti, cosa che rende ancor più soprendente il fatto che i miei talk siano stati votati così tanto.
Date un’occhiata al sito ufficiale per saperne di più sulla conferenza (in questo momento è ancora possibile approfittare dell’offerta early bird per l’acquisto dei biglietti); maggiori informazioni sui miei interventi tra qualche tempo, quando sarà ufficializzato il calendario dei talk.</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
