<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>proust on Nicola Iarocci</title>
    <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/tags/proust/</link>
    <description>Recent content in proust on Nicola Iarocci</description>
    <image>
      <title>Nicola Iarocci</title>
      <url>https://nicolaiarocci.com/images/avatar.png</url>
      <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/images/avatar.png</link>
    </image>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <copyright>Produced / Written / Maintained by [Nicola Iarocci](/) since 2010</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 15 Jul 2021 07:05:25 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://nicolaiarocci.com/tags/proust/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Proust&#39;s Madeleine Was Originally a Slice of Toast</title>
      <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/prousts-madeleine-was-originally-a-slice-of-toast/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 15 Jul 2021 07:05:25 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nicolaiarocci.com/prousts-madeleine-was-originally-a-slice-of-toast/</guid>
      <description>A long-sought first draft of Marcel Proust&amp;rsquo;s &amp;lsquo;In Search of Lost Time&amp;rsquo; surfaced a few years ago. Its fascinating story and intriguing news are revealed in a Tablet article titled Proust&amp;rsquo;s Madeleine Was Originally a Slice Toast.
Being the Tablet &amp;ldquo;a daily online magazine of Jewish news, ideas, and culture&amp;rdquo;, it makes sense that a good part of the article focuses on Proust&amp;rsquo;s ambivalence about his Jewishness. Still, there are many other interesting tidbits to be learned.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>A long-sought first draft of Marcel Proust&rsquo;s &lsquo;In Search of Lost Time&rsquo; surfaced
a few years ago. Its fascinating story and intriguing news are revealed in
a Tablet article titled <a href="https://www.tabletmag.com/sections/arts-letters/articles/proust-madeleine-antisemitism-jewishness">Proust&rsquo;s Madeleine Was Originally a Slice Toast</a>.</p>
<p>Being the Tablet &ldquo;a daily online magazine of Jewish news, ideas, and culture&rdquo;,
it makes sense that a good part of the article focuses on Proust&rsquo;s ambivalence
about his Jewishness. Still, there are many other interesting tidbits to be
learned. On the novel itself and its development, on some relevant characters
and their real-world counterparts, and Proust himself.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Most of these matters, as is natural in early drafts, differ from the final
versions: the iconic madeleine in these pages is the far more prosaic toast.
Sound, not just taste or the narrator’s position standing on cobblestones, is
added to the battery of things that can revive the past. Proust writes here,
after trying in vain to resuscitate a lost day of his youth, that &ldquo;I let my
spoon fall onto my plate. There was then produced exactly the same sound as
that of the hammer of the brakemen who that day struck the wheels of the
train at its stop. At that same moment the burning and blinded hour when this
noise rang out was revived for me …&rdquo; Perhaps most surprisingly, the Narrator,
here given his actual name, has a younger brother, an annoying one to boot,
who &ldquo;though only five-and-a-half years-old, was of a rather violent nature.&rdquo;</p>
</blockquote>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
