<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>opinions on Nicola Iarocci</title>
    <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/tags/opinions/</link>
    <description>Recent content in opinions on Nicola Iarocci</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <copyright>Produced / Written / Maintained by [Nicola Iarocci](/) since 2010</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 03 Feb 2021 07:05:25 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://nicolaiarocci.com/tags/opinions/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Strong opinions on software development</title>
      <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/strong-opinions-on-software-development/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Feb 2021 07:05:25 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nicolaiarocci.com/strong-opinions-on-software-development/</guid>
      <description>After six years in the field, Chris has [shared][1] his strong opinions on software development practices, languages, and methodologies. I like his attitude. Willingness to continuously put one&amp;rsquo;s personal views under scrutiny, eventually adapting or even changing them as needed, is not a common trait. Not in our field. While I generally agree with most of his opinions, I feel the urge to comment on a few of them.
Typed languages are better when you&amp;rsquo;re working on a team of people with various experience levels</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>After six years in the field, Chris has [shared][1] his strong opinions on
software development practices, languages, and methodologies. I like his
attitude. Willingness to continuously put one&rsquo;s personal views under scrutiny,
eventually adapting or even changing them as needed, is not a common trait. Not
in our field. While I generally agree with most of his opinions, I feel the
urge to comment on a few of them.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Typed languages are better when you&rsquo;re working on a team of people with
various experience levels</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Typed languages are better, period.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Software architecture probably matters more than anything else. A shitty
implementation of a good abstraction causes no net harm to the code base.
A bad abstraction or missing layer causes everything to rot.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Perfect. I am stealing this line.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Clever code isn&rsquo;t usually good code. Clarity trumps all other concerns.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Good <em>and</em> clever code is very possible, though. Agree on the second part.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Bad code can be written in any paradigm</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Ça va sans dire</p>
<blockquote>
<p>So called &ldquo;best practices&rdquo; are contextual and not broadly applicable. Blindly
following them makes you an idiot</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Not following them also makes you an idiot.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Designing scalable systems when you don&rsquo;t need to makes you a bad engineer.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>But how do I know in advance whether I need to be scalable or not? Not always
an easy call. Also, scalability doesn&rsquo;t necessarily imply complexity.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>In general, RDBMS &gt; NoSql</p>
</blockquote>
<p>In general, use the right tool for the right job.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Functional programming is another tool, not a panacea.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>The jury is out on this one. In my admittedly limited experience, functional
programming tends to win over OOP. It&rsquo;s not a coincidence that most OOP
languages keep adding functional features (looking at you, C#.).</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Pencil and paper are the best programming tools and vastly under used</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Old fart me concurs.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Trading purity in exchange for practicality is usually a good call</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Don&rsquo;t get carried away with that.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Talking directly to the customer always reveals more about the problem, in
less time, and with higher accuracy</p>
</blockquote>
<p><em>:s/always/sometimes</em></p>
<blockquote>
<p>The word &ldquo;scalable&rdquo; has a mystical and stupefying power over the mind of the
software engineer. Its mere utterance can whip them into a depraved frenzy.
Grim actions have been justified using this word</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I plea guilty on this one.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Despite being called &ldquo;engineers,&rdquo; most decision are pure cargo-cult with no
backing analysis, data, or numbers</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I am a software craftsman.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>People who stress over code style, linting rules, or other minutia are insane
weirdos</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I am an insane weirdo.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Code coverage has absolutely nothing to do with code quality</p>
</blockquote>
<p>It also has nothing to do with <em>tests</em> quality.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Monoliths are pretty good in most circumstances</p>
</blockquote>
<p><em>:s/most/some</em></p>
<blockquote>
<p>TDD purists are just the worst. Their frail little minds can&rsquo;t process the
existence of different workflows.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Ouch. This hurts.</p>
<p>I am not sure I would have had so many well-formed opinions only six years in.
Read them all on [Chris&rsquo; website][1].</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
