<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>monks on Nicola Iarocci</title>
    <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/tags/monks/</link>
    <description>Recent content in monks on Nicola Iarocci</description>
    <image>
      <title>Nicola Iarocci</title>
      <url>https://nicolaiarocci.com/images/avatar.png</url>
      <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/images/avatar.png</link>
    </image>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <copyright>Produced / Written / Maintained by [Nicola Iarocci](/) since 2010</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 03 Aug 2023 07:05:25 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://nicolaiarocci.com/tags/monks/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>The Medieval Monks Who Lived on Top of Giant Pillars</title>
      <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/the-medieval-monks-who-lived-on-top-of-giant-pillars/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 03 Aug 2023 07:05:25 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nicolaiarocci.com/the-medieval-monks-who-lived-on-top-of-giant-pillars/</guid>
      <description>Imagine, for a moment, that you are walking along a dirt road in the seventh century Middle East. The sun is hot, the air is dry, your feet are tired. It’s been a long journey, by boat and foot, from your home in Constantinople to where you find yourself now: outside of the walls of the mountainous river city of Antioch. In the bright sunlight, you strain your eyes to catch a distant glimpse of the sight you’ve come all this way to see – and then suddenly, you do.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<blockquote>
<p>Imagine, for a moment, that you are walking along a dirt road in the seventh century Middle East. The sun is hot, the
air is dry, your feet are tired. It’s been a long journey, by boat and foot, from your home in Constantinople to where
you find yourself now: outside of the walls of the mountainous river city of Antioch. In the bright sunlight, you
strain your eyes to catch a distant glimpse of the sight you’ve come all this way to see – and then suddenly, you do.
A bright stone pillar, stretching as tall as a church dome with an unsteady-looking wooden platform; and atop it a
tiny, bedraggled, flinty old man.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>You’ve found him: the Pillar Saint.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>To our modern eyes, this is a profoundly weird image – but it would have been a recognisable, even iconic, one if we
were living in the early medieval Middle East. To explain how we got here – and how that guy got on that pillar - we
need to step back and tell the origin story of one of the most recognisable characters in medieval life: the monk.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>More <a href="https://weirdmedievalguys.substack.com/p/the-medieval-monks-who-lived-on-top">here</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
