<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>covid on Nicola Iarocci</title>
    <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/tags/covid/</link>
    <description>Recent content in covid on Nicola Iarocci</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <copyright>Produced / Written / Maintained by [Nicola Iarocci](/) since 2010</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 19 May 2022 07:05:25 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://nicolaiarocci.com/tags/covid/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>I got Covid</title>
      <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/i-got-covid/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 19 May 2022 07:05:25 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nicolaiarocci.com/i-got-covid/</guid>
      <description>After two years of avoiding it, I finally got Covid. First two days, I had a few symptoms but was testing negative (it was likely to be Covid because one of my daughters was positive.) On day three, I tested positive. It&amp;rsquo;s ten days now, but only during the first three or four I didn&amp;rsquo;t feel good: a light fever, pinching throat, some coughing and sleepiness, that&amp;rsquo;s all. I did not have to miss any working days (I&amp;rsquo;m self-employed) and only had to skip two of my daily training routines[^1].</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>After two years of avoiding it, I finally got Covid. First two days, I had
a few symptoms but was testing negative (it was likely to be Covid because one
of my daughters was positive.) On day three, I tested positive. It&rsquo;s ten days
now, but only during the first three or four I didn&rsquo;t feel good: a light fever,
pinching throat, some coughing and sleepiness, that&rsquo;s all.  I did not have to
miss any working days (I&rsquo;m self-employed) and only had to skip two of my daily
training routines[^1]. I&rsquo;m in my early fifties, healthy, fully vaccinated and
boosted.</p>
<p>These days, in our household, three out of four got the Covid. Our eldest son
is in Berlin at the university, but he got Covid one year ago when studying in
France. As I write, I learn that my brother and his wife have tested positive.
Hopefully, our elders will stay clear of it. I&rsquo;m so thankful for all the
science that makes this less terrible.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Get the Fucking Vaccine Already, You Fucking Fucks</title>
      <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/get-the-fucking-vaccine-already-you-fucking-fucks/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 04 Sep 2021 07:05:25 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nicolaiarocci.com/get-the-fucking-vaccine-already-you-fucking-fucks/</guid>
      <description>Wendy Molyneux, [writing unabashedly][1] for McSweeney&amp;rsquo;s, summarizes all I have to say on the COVID vaccine and never dared to say:
You think vaccines don’t fucking work? Oh, fuck off into the trash, you attention-seeking fuckworm-faced shitbutt. This isn’t even a point worth discussing, you fuck-o-rama fuck-stival of ignorance. Vaccines got rid of smallpox and polio and all the other disgusting diseases that used to kill off little fucks like you en masse.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Wendy Molyneux, [writing unabashedly][1] for McSweeney&rsquo;s, summarizes all I have
to say on the COVID vaccine and never dared to say:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>You think vaccines don’t fucking work? Oh, fuck off into the trash, you
attention-seeking fuckworm-faced shitbutt. This isn’t even a point worth
discussing, you fuck-o-rama fuck-stival of ignorance. Vaccines got rid of
smallpox and polio and all the other disgusting diseases that used to kill
off little fucks like you en masse. Your relatives got fucking vaccinated and
let you live, and now here you are signing up to be killed by a fucking
disease against which there is a ninety-nine-percent effective vaccine. You
fucking moron. Go in the fucking ocean and fuck a piranha. Fuck. Fuck that.
Fuck you. Get vaccinated.</p>
</blockquote>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
