<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>calvino on Nicola Iarocci</title>
    <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/tags/calvino/</link>
    <description>Recent content in calvino on Nicola Iarocci</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 17 Mar 2023 07:05:25 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://nicolaiarocci.com/tags/calvino/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Quoting Italo Calvino</title>
      <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/quoting-italo-calvino/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Mar 2023 07:05:25 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nicolaiarocci.com/quoting-italo-calvino/</guid>
      <description>Quoting the last paragraph from Italo Calvino&amp;rsquo;s Invisible Cities:
The inferno of the living is not something that will be; if there is one, it is what is already here, the inferno where we live every day, that we form by being together. There are two ways to escape suffering it. The first is easy for many: accept the inferno and become such a part of it that you can no longer see it.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Book Review: Invisible Cities</title>
      <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/book-review-invisible-cities/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 May 2022 07:05:25 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nicolaiarocci.com/book-review-invisible-cities/</guid>
      <description>&amp;ldquo;Kublai Khan does not necessarily believe everything Marco Polo says when he describes the cities visited on his expeditions, but the emperor of the Tartars does continue listening to the young Venetian with greater attention and curiosity than he shows any other messenger or explorer of his.&amp;rdquo; So begins Italo Calvino&amp;rsquo;s compilation of fragmentary urban images. As Marco tells the khan about Armilla, which &amp;ldquo;has nothing that makes it seem a city, except the water pipes that rise vertically where the houses should be and spread out horizontally where the floors should be,&amp;rdquo; the spider-web city of Octavia, and other marvelous burgs, it may be that he is creating them all out of his imagination, or perhaps he is recreating fine details of his native Venice over and over again, or perhaps he is simply recounting some of the myriad possible forms a city might take.</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
