<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>longreads on Nicola Iarocci</title>
    <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/tags/longreads/</link>
    <description>Recent content in longreads on Nicola Iarocci</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 08 Dec 2021 07:05:25 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://nicolaiarocci.com/tags/longreads/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>On the incredible opportunities offered by Starship</title>
      <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/on-the-incredible-opportunities-offered-by-starship/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Dec 2021 07:05:25 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nicolaiarocci.com/on-the-incredible-opportunities-offered-by-starship/</guid>
      <description>Space-junkie me is back, this time reading about the innumerable opportunities that SpaceX&amp;rsquo;s Starship will offer once it becomes operational, hopefully no later than this year or the next. In his Science Upside for Starship, the exceptionally knowledgeable Casey Handmer makes a case for Starship relevance in the future of space exploration by listing an astounding number of reasonable use-cases for the vessel.
I think it is relatively straightforward to think of cool things to do with SpaceX Starships, so recent posts have focused on trying to understand the more mixed consequences for incumbent industrial organizations that are not ideally positioned to exploit the coming advances.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The posthuman dog</title>
      <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/the-posthuman-dog/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 06 Nov 2021 08:05:25 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nicolaiarocci.com/the-posthuman-dog/</guid>
      <description>Flo, our dog, spent her whole fifteen-years long life with us. Many, many times after she passed away, I wondered if she lived a happy dog life or not. In The posthuman dog (Aeon), Jessica Pierce poses a fascinating question that somehow helps find answers to my troubling question:
If humans were to disappear from the face of the Earth, what might dogs become? And would they be better off without us?</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Internet is Rotting</title>
      <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/the-internet-is-rotting/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 17 Jul 2021 07:05:25 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nicolaiarocci.com/the-internet-is-rotting/</guid>
      <description>Terrific piece by Jonathan Zittrain, on The Atlantic, on link rot and digital preservation. I love how well documented and informative it is. Yet, it remains perfectly approachable for both the non-knowledgeable reader and the technically savvy.
Too much has been lost already. The glue that holds humanity’s knowledge together is coming undone.
We need more content like this.
Subscribe to the newsletter, the RSS feed, or follow @nicolaiarocci on Twitter</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>On the CEO and founder of Signal</title>
      <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/on-the-ceo-and-founder-of-signal/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Mar 2021 07:05:25 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nicolaiarocci.com/on-the-ceo-and-founder-of-signal/</guid>
      <description>Last weekend&amp;rsquo;s reading list also included Taking Back Our Privacy, yet another1 New Yorker piece but this time signed by Anna Wiener. This article is a long-read on Moxie Marlinspike, co-founder and CEO of Signal. Moxie is a childhood nickname. That alone signals (pun intended) an original personality. I mean, how many times have you heard of a CEO going by his childhood nickname?
Indeed the personal story of Marlinspike, along with that of the ascent of Signal, is fascinating.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Activists Who Embrace Nuclear Power</title>
      <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/the-activists-who-embrace-nuclear-power/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 28 Feb 2021 07:05:25 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nicolaiarocci.com/the-activists-who-embrace-nuclear-power/</guid>
      <description>Today, my Sunday long-reading list included New Yorker&amp;rsquo;s The Activists Who Embrace Nuclear Power by Rebecca Tuhus-Dubrow. Can nuclear power possibly be a viable solution for climate change? Twenty or even ten years ago, my answer would have been a big fat No. Today? Not so sure anymore.
Today, the looming disruptions of climate change have altered the risk calculus around nuclear energy. James Hansen, the NASA scientist credited with first bringing global warming to public attention, in 1988, has long advocated a vast expansion of nuclear power to replace fossil fuels.</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
