<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>wolwes on Nicola Iarocci</title>
    <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/tags/wolwes/</link>
    <description>Recent content in wolwes on Nicola Iarocci</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <copyright>Produced / Written / Maintained by [Nicola Iarocci](/) since 2010</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 20 Oct 2021 07:05:25 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://nicolaiarocci.com/tags/wolwes/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>I met with the wolves</title>
      <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/i-met-with-the-wolves/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Oct 2021 07:05:25 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nicolaiarocci.com/i-met-with-the-wolves/</guid>
      <description>I sit under a wild apple tree at the edge of the clearing. Like a plant, I absorb the mild October sun. At the same time, I attentively listen to the sounds of the forest. Suddenly I hear a stomping of dry leaves about twenty meters ahead of me, slightly to my right. A wolf emerges out of the thicket. He stops for a moment, glances around, then starts crossing the clearing.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I sit under a wild apple tree at the edge of the clearing. Like a plant,
I absorb the mild October sun. At the same time, I attentively listen to the
sounds of the forest. Suddenly I hear a stomping of dry leaves about twenty
meters ahead of me, slightly to my right. A wolf emerges out of the thicket. He
stops for a moment, glances around, then starts crossing the clearing. A few
moments and another wolf appears. After a brief pause, he follows his pal. They
parade right in front of me, sinuous, silent, and feral. They do not see or
hear me, and yet I am right there, by their side, in plain sight<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1</a></sup>. It is all
over in a few seconds. The couple leaves the clearing and disappears into the
forest. I stand sitting there, shocked and in complete awe.</p>
<p>Incredibly, the scene above is real. It happened to me last Sunday, in the wild
Apennines, in a place I&rsquo;ve been visiting for years. I&rsquo;ve seen a lot of animals
there: wild boar, deer, badgers, foxes. I knew wolves frequent the area but
meeting them, in the plain day? No way. I dreamed about it, of course, but
never expected it would really happen.  I had goosebumps, and I still have them
now as I write this. I keep telling myself it&rsquo;s impossible. And yet, I have
photos on my cellphone. In the heat of the moment, I somehow managed to snap
a couple. My family confirms the wolves. It was not a dream.</p>
<p><em>Subscribe to the [newsletter][nl], the [RSS feed][rss], or follow @[nicolaiarocci][tw] on Twitter</em></p>
<div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
<hr>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1">
<p>In hindsight, I think that having been sitting there motionless and not producing any sound for a long time did the trick. By pure luck, I also happened to be downwind to them.
[rss]: <a href="https://nicolaiarocci.com/index.xml">https://nicolaiarocci.com/index.xml</a>
[tw]: <a href="http://twitter.com/nicolaiarocci">http://twitter.com/nicolaiarocci</a>
[nl]: <a href="https://buttondown.email/nicolaiarocci">https://buttondown.email/nicolaiarocci</a>&#160;<a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
</ol>
</div>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
