<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>bluetooth on Nicola Iarocci</title>
    <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/tags/bluetooth/</link>
    <description>Recent content in bluetooth on Nicola Iarocci</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <copyright>Produced / Written / Maintained by [Nicola Iarocci](/) since 2010</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 09 Feb 2022 07:05:25 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://nicolaiarocci.com/tags/bluetooth/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>The curious origins of Bluetooth&#39;s name</title>
      <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/the-curious-origins-of-bluetooths-name/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 09 Feb 2022 07:05:25 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nicolaiarocci.com/the-curious-origins-of-bluetooths-name/</guid>
      <description>When Giulia came home from school today, she was anxious to tell me what she learned about a Viking King and his legacy. She told me the story of King Harald Gormsson, who ruled Denmark and Norway from c. 958 to c. 986. Harald is mainly known for introducing Christianity to Denmark and consolidating his rule over most Jutland and Zealand. However, what sparked my interest is that Harald was nicknamed &amp;ldquo;Bluetooth&amp;rdquo;, and, in 1997, the Bluetooth wireless specification design was named after him.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>When Giulia came home from school today, she was anxious to tell me what she
learned about a Viking King and his legacy. She told me the story of King
Harald Gormsson, who ruled Denmark and Norway from c. 958 to c. 986. Harald is
mainly known for introducing Christianity to Denmark and consolidating his rule
over most Jutland and Zealand. However, what sparked my interest is that Harald
was nicknamed &ldquo;Bluetooth&rdquo;, and, in 1997, the Bluetooth wireless specification
design was named after him. The choice was based on an analogy that the
technology would unite devices the way Harald united the tribes of Denmark into
a single kingdom. Furthermore, the Bluetooth logo consists of the two
Scandinavian runes for his initials, H (ᚼ) and B (ᛒ)[^2]</p>
<p>The traditional explanation for his byname is that Harald must have had
a conspicuous bad tooth that appeared &ldquo;blue&rdquo; (i.e. &ldquo;black&rdquo;, as blár &ldquo;blue&rdquo;
meant &ldquo;blue-black&rdquo;, or &ldquo;dark-coloured&rdquo;). Another explanation is that he was
called &ldquo;blue thane&rdquo; (or &ldquo;dark thane&rdquo;) in England (with Anglo-Saxon thegn
corrupted to tan when the name came back into Old Norse).[^3]</p>
<p>Another interesting tidbit is that, according to Bluetooth&rsquo;s official website,
Bluetooth was only intended as a placeholder until marketing could come up with
something cool. Later, when it came time to select a serious name, Bluetooth
was to be replaced with either RadioWire or PAN (Personal Area Networking). PAN
was the front runner, but an exhaustive search discovered it already had tens
of thousands of hits throughout the internet. A full trademark search on
RadioWire couldn&rsquo;t be completed in time for launch, making Bluetooth the only
choice. The name caught on fast, and before it could be changed, it spread
throughout the industry, becoming synonymous with short-range wireless
technology[^4].</p>
<p>I&rsquo;m a sucker for stories like this in which technology pays proper tribute to
our past, without which it wouldn&rsquo;t exist in the first place.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
