<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>magazines on Nicola Iarocci</title>
    <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/tags/magazines/</link>
    <description>Recent content in magazines on Nicola Iarocci</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <copyright>Produced / Written / Maintained by [Nicola Iarocci](/) since 2010</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 19 Apr 2023 07:05:25 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://nicolaiarocci.com/tags/magazines/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>The end of computer magazines in America (and elsewhere)</title>
      <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/the-end-of-computer-magazines-in-america-and-elsewhere/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Apr 2023 07:05:25 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nicolaiarocci.com/the-end-of-computer-magazines-in-america-and-elsewhere/</guid>
      <description>In the mid-to-late 80s, my excitement used to culminate by the end of the month when BYTE&amp;rsquo;s new issue would hit the newsstands1. In my small Italian hometown, only one, sometimes two, newsstands would sometime get a copy (BYTE was published in the US and copies sent abroad were scarce; only major, close-to-the-train-station stands had a chance to receive it). I wasn&amp;rsquo;t the only kid in town interested in that elusive one issue; I had an anonymous competitor.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>In the mid-to-late 80s, my excitement used to culminate by the end of the month when BYTE&rsquo;s new issue would hit the
newsstands<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1</a></sup>. In my small Italian hometown, only one, sometimes two, newsstands would sometime get a copy (BYTE was
published in the US and copies sent abroad were scarce; only major, close-to-the-train-station stands had a chance to
receive it). I wasn&rsquo;t the only kid in town interested in that elusive one issue; I had an anonymous competitor. The race
was on every third week of the month, give or take. You see, the thing is, back then, computer magazines were the only
source of reliable, precious information on everything hardware and software. I could barely read English at that age.
Yet, I spent whole afternoons stubbornly reading the magazine cover to cover, probably understanding only fifty percent
of its content. Rather than at school, I learned most of my English by reading computer magazines.</p>
<p>This morning, these memories were brought back to me while reading <a href="https://www.technologizer.com/2023/04/15/the-end-of-computer-magazines-in-america">The End of Computer Magazines in America</a> by Harry
McCracken. He was involved with the computer magazine industry in its golden age, so the article has exciting insights.
I also appreciated the several former colleagues and competitors who commented, helping frame the period. Computer
magazines are dead indeed, and it&rsquo;s a bittersweet sensation. Quoting McCracken&rsquo;s closing words:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>I do remain grateful that computer magazines existed. Their time has passed—but what a time it was.</p>
</blockquote>
<div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
<hr>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1">
<p>This is a story I probably already mentioned on this site, but hey, it&rsquo;s my site; I can afford to repeat myself.
[rss]: <a href="https://nicolaiarocci.com/index.xml">https://nicolaiarocci.com/index.xml</a>
[m]: <a href="https://fosstodon.org/@nicola">https://fosstodon.org/@nicola</a>
[nl]: <a href="https://buttondown.email/nicolaiarocci">https://buttondown.email/nicolaiarocci</a>&#160;<a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
</ol>
</div>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
