<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>essays on Nicola Iarocci</title>
    <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/tags/essays/</link>
    <description>Recent content in essays on Nicola Iarocci</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <copyright>Produced / Written / Maintained by [Nicola Iarocci](/) since 2010</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 25 Nov 2021 07:05:25 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://nicolaiarocci.com/tags/essays/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Book Review: Mathematics is politics</title>
      <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/book-review-mathematics-is-politics/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 25 Nov 2021 07:05:25 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nicolaiarocci.com/book-review-mathematics-is-politics/</guid>
      <description>Mathematics as the study of relationships: in this aspect lies the similarity and affinity with politics. And then the need in both cases to proceed with stubbornness and trust, without fearing error which, as in all difficult things, is not only lying in wait but inherent, and often, when it is discovered, it is the stimulus and engine of new successes and goals. Hence the need to respect rules and (not or, mind you) the compelling need for revolutions.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Mathematics as the study of relationships: in this aspect lies the similarity
and affinity with politics. And then the need in both cases to proceed with
stubbornness and trust, without fearing error which, as in all difficult
things, is not only lying in wait but inherent, and often, when it is
discovered, it is the stimulus and engine of new successes and goals. Hence the
need to respect rules and (not or, mind you) the compelling need for
revolutions. The parallel narration of the author&rsquo;s life and the change, over
the years, of her own beliefs and points of view, makes this short essay more
credible and streamlines the story.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Mathematics was my apprenticeship to revolution because it taught me to
distrust absolute truths and unquestionable authorities. Democracy and
mathematics, from a political point of view, are similar: like all creative
processes, they can&rsquo;t stand remaining unchanged.</p>
</blockquote>
<p><img loading="lazy" src="/images/matematica-politica.jpg#right" alt="La matematica è politica"  />

Not a book for everyone, perhaps, but suitable to those who like to think and
be challenged with ideas. Background theme to which I am susceptible: the
necessity for school to illuminate our existences. I wouldn&rsquo;t say I liked the
frequent references to contingent situations in Italian politics. I bought an
short essay on the interconnections between mathematics and politics; I expect
it to make me fly high, far away from the quarrels and events of daily
politics. Also, sometimes the similarities between the two fields seem a bit
too far fetched.</p>
<p>I don&rsquo;t think this book is currently available in English. I read it in the
original Italian edition.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Book Review: Nomadland</title>
      <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/book-review-nomadland/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 21 Aug 2021 07:05:25 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nicolaiarocci.com/book-review-nomadland/</guid>
      <description>Some call them homeless. The new nomads refer to themselves as &amp;lsquo;houseless&amp;rsquo;. Many took to the road after their savings were obliterated by the Great Recession. To keep their gas tanks and bellies full, they work long hours at hard, physical jobs. In a time of flat wages and rising housing costs, they have unshackled themselves from rent and mortgages as a way to get by. They are surviving America.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<blockquote>
<p>Some call them homeless. The new nomads refer to themselves as &lsquo;houseless&rsquo;.
Many took to the road after their savings were obliterated by the Great
Recession. To keep their gas tanks and bellies full, they work long hours at
hard, physical jobs. In a time of flat wages and rising housing costs, they
have unshackled themselves from rent and mortgages as a way to get by. They
are surviving America.</p>
</blockquote>
<p><img loading="lazy" src="/images/nomadland_book_cover.jpg#right" alt="Nomadland book cover"  />

Jessica Bruder is a journalist. For three years, she followed the lives of
a group of nomads who live in their RVs or even in their cars, moving from one
seasonal work to the next in their pursuit to survive the collapse of their own
personal American Dream. Her writing is dry, concise, with little room for
personal feelings or ramblings, to the point that, at times, she sounds
distant, almost detached from the events being told. That isn&rsquo;t the case, as
you can tell by the second half of the book when she finally decides to take
the plunge and get herself a van to live herself the &ldquo;workcamper&rdquo; life. That is
a tipping point in the book. The author becomes the main character, the story
is personal, and the reader is more involved.</p>
<p>Bruder interviews many folks and followed a few of them in detail. Linda May,
amongst others, is the centrepiece of the story. Linda was 62 when she took
social security and was forced into living in a van. Most people living the
&ldquo;workcamper&rdquo; life are in what would be their retirement age. They are in their
60s, 70s and sometimes even 80s. Yet, they work very hard at their seasonal
jobs, like at Amazon warehouses as inventory scanners or in Minnesota and North
Dakota, for the seasonal harvest of sugar beets. These work experiences are
depicted with great detail. Bruder herself walked the plank and experienced how
demanding these assignments are on the body and the spirit (Amazon provides
painkillers to their aged employees). Despite all the difficulties, these
people carry on with great dignity and, often, upbeat attitude, well
represented by Linda, a lovely elderly woman.</p>
<p>I had no idea that the &ldquo;workcampers&rdquo; subculture existed in the USA. As someone
who has always been mildly fascinated by the RV life (like many others, we
sometimes fantasize about travelling the world in a camper when we retire),
I admit I was pretty shocked by this work, an engaging and very unsettling
read. I am grateful to Bruder for her hard-earned report.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>At one time there was a social contract that if you played by the rules (went
to school, got a job, and worked hard) everything would be fine. That’s no
longer true today. You can do everything right, just the way society wants
you to do it, and still end up broke, alone, and homeless.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>PS. By pure coincidence, I came across the awarded Nomandland movie only a few days
after finishing the book. It was great. At first, I was startled by the acting
of some roles. Then, by the final credits, I realized that it wasn&rsquo;t
professional actors who played those roles. It was the actual persons from the
book, Linda May included, who played themselves.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Book Review. Eight Days in May: The Final Collapse of the Third Reich</title>
      <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/book-review.-eight-days-in-may-the-final-collapse-of-the-third-reich/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 18 Jul 2021 07:05:25 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nicolaiarocci.com/book-review.-eight-days-in-may-the-final-collapse-of-the-third-reich/</guid>
      <description>Volker Ullrich&amp;rsquo;s Eight Days in May describes the period from April 30, 1945, the day of Hitler&amp;rsquo;s suicide, to May 8, the day of signing the German capitulation, with significant jumps backwards in time and some hops in the future. We&amp;rsquo;re covering only eight days, and the dictator dies on day one. What essential events might ever have happened in such a short period? Well, many pivotal ones, as this well-researched work shows us.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Volker Ullrich&rsquo;s Eight Days in May describes the period from April 30, 1945,
the day of Hitler&rsquo;s suicide, to May 8, the day of signing the German
capitulation, with significant jumps backwards in time and some hops in the
future. We&rsquo;re covering only eight days, and the dictator dies on day one. What
essential events might ever have happened in such a short period? Well, many
pivotal ones, as this well-researched work shows us.</p>
<p>The book is merciless towards Hitler&rsquo;s heirs and not accommodating at all
towards Germans of that age in general. Reading the behaviors and things said
in those days is gruesome. Under track are the horrible consequences of war and
concentration camps. The resulting picture is that of the supreme horrors and
mistakes that humanity can reach.</p>
<p>The text focuses on the protagonists of those days, the Nazi hierarchs (not
just the most infamously well known) and their Allies and Red Army
counterparts. There are few notable exceptions, like the story of Marlene
Dietrich, already a Hollywood star, who served as an American army officer and
returned to Germany to look for her sister lost in the fog of war. To her
dismay, she found that her sister had prospered, cooperating and taking advance
of the Nazi regime. Marlene bought her sisters&rsquo; silence, and for the rest of
her life, fiercely negated the very own existence of a sister.</p>
<p>I found the part on the German population and its shocked, instinctive reaction
to the regime&rsquo;s fall particularly informative. The immediate turncoat of most,
along with the lying denial of knowing anything about the atrocities.The
disturbing (George Orwell&rsquo;s word), immediate sympathy for the Allies. Also, the
eulogy for the few who courageously conducted a desperate, clandestine and
seemingly hopeless resistance within the Reich. It is especially relevant that
the author is German.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" src="/images/eight-days-in-may.jpg#right" alt="Eight Days in May book cover"  />

This book leaves me stunned. It is always painful to read about that historical
period. The millions of deaths. The suffering. The atrocities. We need to keep
going back, walk the way over and over, never to forget, never to repeat. To
that end, Eight Days in May is a book everyone should read.</p>
<p>By May 8, 1945, Germany was a humiliated, devastated country. Most major cities
were annihilated, the economy had collapsed, and millions of people were
reduced to hunger. The contrast with today&rsquo;s Germany is mind-blowing. With the
help of the winning countries, sure, but predominantly and undoubtedly thanks
to grit and desire for rebirth, Germany resurged from the catastrophe as
a modern country and a sought-out model for democracy, economy, justice, and
reception of diverse cultures.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Book Review: Power to the Words</title>
      <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/book-review-power-to-the-words/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 09 Jul 2021 07:05:25 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nicolaiarocci.com/book-review-power-to-the-words/</guid>
      <description>Vera Gheno&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;Potere alle Parole&amp;rdquo; (Power to the Words) is an essay on the importance of appropriate use of the (Italian) language, not just in written works but also and predominately in everyday life.
What would we think of a person who, having a vast wardrobe of beautiful clothes, always wore the same suit out of laziness? These situations appear unlikely; yet, they are examples of the attitude that many have towards their language: they have access to an immense, incalculable patrimony, which out of indolence, or fear, or inexperience, they use partially.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Vera Gheno&rsquo;s &ldquo;Potere alle Parole&rdquo; (Power to the Words) is an essay on the
importance of appropriate use of the (Italian) language, not just in written
works but also and predominately in everyday life.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>What would we think of a person who, having a vast wardrobe of beautiful
clothes, always wore the same suit out of laziness? These situations appear
unlikely; yet, they are examples of the attitude that many have towards their
language: they have access to an immense, incalculable patrimony, which out
of indolence, or fear, or inexperience, they use partially. Even if the
Italian does not need to be saved or preserved, we should love it more
because it is a magnificent instrument. It is a shame to limit ourselves to
only a superficial frequentation.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Vera Gheno is a sociolinguist. She teaches at the Universities of Florence and
Siena. She collaborates with the &ldquo;Accademia della Crusca&rdquo;, the most important
research institution of the Italian language and the oldest linguistic academy
in the world. She is also a phenomenal popularizer. I am sure that some
concepts and notions expressed here are well known to the knowledgeable person,
but this book is not targeted to that kind of reader. I think this work is
purposedly aiming at the general public.Yet, I suspect it would remain
enjoyable to those in the field mainly thanks to its always fresh and
entertaining style.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" src="/images/potere-alle-parole.jpg#right" alt="Potere alle Parole book cover"  />

One of the many takeaways is that languages change, evolve, and constantly
adapt over time. Hence there is no standard, norm, or canon set in stone. New
words are minted continuously. At the same time, some others decay and slowly
disappear. Words initially borrowed from foreign languages (English, yes, but
also French, and many other unexpected ones, like Hungarian) enter the
dictionary to become part of the norm. We old farts should not be so quick to
condemn our kids&rsquo; slang: some of their jargon will soon be forgotten, some will
join the canon. The same happened, of course, in our time and forever before.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Book Review: Alpi Ribelli: Storie di montagna, resistenza e utopia</title>
      <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/book-review-alpi-ribelli-storie-di-montagna-resistenza-e-utopia/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 05 Jun 2021 07:05:25 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nicolaiarocci.com/book-review-alpi-ribelli-storie-di-montagna-resistenza-e-utopia/</guid>
      <description>The idea behind this book is fascinating. As the subtitle suggests, the book collects stories of rebel mountaineers of all kinds. Some chose to disobey orders; others built refuges of resistance, outposts of autonomy and laboratories of social innovation.
The collection is rich and varied. We go from the heretics who went with Fra Dolcino to the partisans who stopped the Nazi fascists in the mountains of Cuneo and Belluno, up to the contemporary movements against the high-speed train in the Susa Valley.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The idea behind this book is fascinating. As the subtitle suggests, the book
collects stories of rebel mountaineers of all kinds. Some chose to disobey
orders; others built refuges of resistance, outposts of autonomy and
laboratories of social innovation.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" src="/images/alpi-ribelli-book-cover.jpeg#right" alt="Alpi Ribelli book cover"  />

The collection is rich and varied. We go from the heretics who went with Fra
Dolcino to the partisans who stopped the Nazi fascists in the mountains of
Cuneo and Belluno, up to the contemporary movements against the high-speed
train in the Susa Valley. Some high-profile mountain climbers are present as
well. Tita Piaz, the Dolomiti Devil; the Nuovo Mattino climbers who, inspired
by the revolution going in Yosemite , let go of the classic &ldquo;fight with the
Alp&rdquo; approach to mountain climbing; the very notable (and totally unknown to
me) story of Guido Rossa, worker, trade unionist, and fantastic rock climber.
The Italian Alpine Club internal struggle from which the Mountain Wilderness
association originated.</p>
<p>Enrico Camanni, the author, is essentially a journalist, and it shows. I know
him since the mid-90s when he was the editorial director of the then best
mountain magazine, Alp. I might be wrong, but I suspect that this work is
mainly composed of articles previously written for magazines and other works,
here edited and enriched. That is not necessarily a negative, but I find the
prose sometimes short-lived, other times emphatic, erratic in some ways.</p>
<p>Overall a good book. I appreciated some reflections and considerations,
especially those around the now unbreakable, intertwined bonds between the
lowlands and the highlands.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Book Review: The Voice of the Sirens. The Greeks and the art of persuasion</title>
      <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/book-review-the-voice-of-the-sirens.-the-greeks-and-the-art-of-persuasion/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 15 May 2021 07:05:25 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nicolaiarocci.com/book-review-the-voice-of-the-sirens.-the-greeks-and-the-art-of-persuasion/</guid>
      <description>According to a famous and fortunate Homeric expression, words are winged, not so much like birds but rather like arrows, which cut the air quickly to go straight to the target and break through the listener&amp;rsquo;s heart. The Greeks have always known that the word is used to convince and show truth and correctness. But they also know that it has a magical force in it: it can turn into a spell, capable of dominating and dragging the listener&amp;rsquo;s soul; to bewitch like music and to heal like medicine; but, above all, to deceive and mislead.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<blockquote>
<p>According to a famous and fortunate Homeric expression, words are winged, not
so much like birds but rather like arrows, which cut the air quickly to go
straight to the target and break through the listener&rsquo;s heart. The Greeks
have always known that the word is used to convince and show truth and
correctness. But they also know that it has a magical force in it: it can
turn into a spell, capable of dominating and dragging the listener&rsquo;s soul; to
bewitch like music and to heal like medicine; but, above all, to deceive and
mislead.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Laura Pepe teaches ancient greek law at the University of Milan. In her career,
she published many academic works and also scientific divulgation books. The
Voice of the Sirens falls in the latter category.</p>
<p>For the ancients, the Sirens were horrifying monsters, half birds and half
women. Yet, they had something that made them irresistible: the voice,
persuasive and captivating. In this book, along with other similar mythological
figures such as Circe, Calypso and Elena, Sirens are protagonists of a journey
that starts from Homer and focuses on the Athens of the 5th century. Athens,
the city of democracy and, even before that, of the word. Retracing
little-known stories and famous passages of prose and poetry, Professor Pepe
investigates the incredible potential of <em>peithó</em>, persuasion, the word that
both seduces and convinces.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" src="/images/la-voce-delle-sirene.jpg#right" alt="La Voce delle Sirene"  />

The word, the most powerful sovereign, can carry out the most divine deeds: it
knows how to convince the true and the just, but it can also deceive and
mislead. Pepe shows its strengths by looking at the protagonists of politics
who address people gathered in assembly, and then at accusers and accused, who
work hard to convince the court&rsquo;s judges. Finally, she looks at the masters of
persuasion, the sophists, who were also active in 5th century Athens.</p>
<p>Professor Pepe does a great job at reminding us how and why Ancient Greece</p>
<ul>
<li>between history, myth, poems and philosophy - has shaped our way of thinking
and dealing with the world. In almost thousands of years, we have significantly
progressed in many incredible ways. Yet the mechanisms that drive modern
societies have evolved only marginally and, what&rsquo;s humbling, the fundamental
questions raised by the great minds of that age remain unanswered<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1</a></sup>.</li>
</ul>
<div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
<hr>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1">
<p>Unfortunately, I am not aware of any international edition currently available for this book. It deserves one.
[rss]: <a href="https://nicolaiarocci.com/index.xml">https://nicolaiarocci.com/index.xml</a>
[tw]: <a href="http://twitter.com/nicolaiarocci">http://twitter.com/nicolaiarocci</a>
[nl]: <a href="https://buttondown.email/nicolaiarocci">https://buttondown.email/nicolaiarocci</a>&#160;<a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
</ol>
</div>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
