<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>essays on Nicola Iarocci</title>
    <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/tags/essays/</link>
    <description>Recent content in essays on Nicola Iarocci</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 25 Nov 2021 07:05:25 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://nicolaiarocci.com/tags/essays/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Book Review: Mathematics is politics</title>
      <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/book-review-mathematics-is-politics/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 25 Nov 2021 07:05:25 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nicolaiarocci.com/book-review-mathematics-is-politics/</guid>
      <description>Mathematics as the study of relationships: in this aspect lies the similarity and affinity with politics. And then the need in both cases to proceed with stubbornness and trust, without fearing error which, as in all difficult things, is not only lying in wait but inherent, and often, when it is discovered, it is the stimulus and engine of new successes and goals. Hence the need to respect rules and (not or, mind you) the compelling need for revolutions.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Book Review: Nomadland</title>
      <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/book-review-nomadland/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 21 Aug 2021 07:05:25 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nicolaiarocci.com/book-review-nomadland/</guid>
      <description>Some call them homeless. The new nomads refer to themselves as &amp;lsquo;houseless&amp;rsquo;. Many took to the road after their savings were obliterated by the Great Recession. To keep their gas tanks and bellies full, they work long hours at hard, physical jobs. In a time of flat wages and rising housing costs, they have unshackled themselves from rent and mortgages as a way to get by. They are surviving America.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Book Review. Eight Days in May: The Final Collapse of the Third Reich</title>
      <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/book-review.-eight-days-in-may-the-final-collapse-of-the-third-reich/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 18 Jul 2021 07:05:25 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nicolaiarocci.com/book-review.-eight-days-in-may-the-final-collapse-of-the-third-reich/</guid>
      <description>Volker Ullrich&amp;rsquo;s Eight Days in May describes the period from April 30, 1945, the day of Hitler&amp;rsquo;s suicide, to May 8, the day of signing the German capitulation, with significant jumps backwards in time and some hops in the future. We&amp;rsquo;re covering only eight days, and the dictator dies on day one. What essential events might ever have happened in such a short period? Well, many pivotal ones, as this well-researched work shows us.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Book Review: Power to the Words</title>
      <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/book-review-power-to-the-words/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 09 Jul 2021 07:05:25 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nicolaiarocci.com/book-review-power-to-the-words/</guid>
      <description>Vera Gheno&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;Potere alle Parole&amp;rdquo; (Power to the Words) is an essay on the importance of appropriate use of the (Italian) language, not just in written works but also and predominately in everyday life.
What would we think of a person who, having a vast wardrobe of beautiful clothes, always wore the same suit out of laziness? These situations appear unlikely; yet, they are examples of the attitude that many have towards their language: they have access to an immense, incalculable patrimony, which out of indolence, or fear, or inexperience, they use partially.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Book Review: Alpi Ribelli: Storie di montagna, resistenza e utopia</title>
      <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/book-review-alpi-ribelli-storie-di-montagna-resistenza-e-utopia/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 05 Jun 2021 07:05:25 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nicolaiarocci.com/book-review-alpi-ribelli-storie-di-montagna-resistenza-e-utopia/</guid>
      <description>The idea behind this book is fascinating. As the subtitle suggests, the book collects stories of rebel mountaineers of all kinds. Some chose to disobey orders; others built refuges of resistance, outposts of autonomy and laboratories of social innovation.
The collection is rich and varied. We go from the heretics who went with Fra Dolcino to the partisans who stopped the Nazi fascists in the mountains of Cuneo and Belluno, up to the contemporary movements against the high-speed train in the Susa Valley.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Book Review: The Voice of the Sirens. The Greeks and the art of persuasion</title>
      <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/book-review-the-voice-of-the-sirens.-the-greeks-and-the-art-of-persuasion/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 15 May 2021 07:05:25 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nicolaiarocci.com/book-review-the-voice-of-the-sirens.-the-greeks-and-the-art-of-persuasion/</guid>
      <description>According to a famous and fortunate Homeric expression, words are winged, not so much like birds but rather like arrows, which cut the air quickly to go straight to the target and break through the listener&amp;rsquo;s heart. The Greeks have always known that the word is used to convince and show truth and correctness. But they also know that it has a magical force in it: it can turn into a spell, capable of dominating and dragging the listener&amp;rsquo;s soul; to bewitch like music and to heal like medicine; but, above all, to deceive and mislead.</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
