<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>tomcc on Nicola Iarocci</title>
    <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/tags/tomcc/</link>
    <description>Recent content in tomcc on Nicola Iarocci</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- 0.121.1</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <copyright>Produced / Written / Maintained by Nicola Iarocci since 2010</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 09 May 2023 07:05:25 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://nicolaiarocci.com/tags/tomcc/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Motorcycling the Tuscan Chianti</title>
      <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/motorcycling-the-tuscan-chianti/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 09 May 2023 07:05:25 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nicolaiarocci.com/motorcycling-the-tuscan-chianti/</guid>
      <description>Last weekend I attended Eroica 2023, a motorcycling event organized by the Italian branch of the Triumph Owners Motorcycle Club I currently preside. We rode the Eroica route, a legendary gravel bicycle race that runs through the most beautiful territories of the Tuscan Chianti region. It was glorious. The weather was perfect, the food was incredible, and the close-knit party of thirty T.O.M.C.C. bikers had great fun. We all ended up covered in an astonishing amount of powder.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Last weekend I attended <em>Eroica 2023</em>, a motorcycling event organized by the Italian branch of the <a href="https:/tomccitalia.org">Triumph Owners
Motorcycle Club</a> I currently preside. We rode the <a href="https://eroica.cc/en">Eroica</a> route, a legendary gravel bicycle race that runs
through the most beautiful territories of the Tuscan Chianti region. It was glorious. The weather was perfect, the food
was incredible, and the close-knit party of thirty T.O.M.C.C. bikers had great fun. We all ended up covered in an
astonishing amount of powder.</p>

<div style="position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;">
  <iframe src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/Hrb-t4M01FY" style="position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;" allowfullscreen title="YouTube Video"></iframe>
</div>

<p><em>Eroica 2023</em> was the first in a series of events we&rsquo;ll run throughout the summer and fall. I&rsquo;m looking forward to the
next ones.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Motorcycling the Foreste Casentinesi National Park</title>
      <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/motorcycling-the-foreste-casentinesi-national-park/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Oct 2022 07:05:25 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nicolaiarocci.com/motorcycling-the-foreste-casentinesi-national-park/</guid>
      <description>Last Saturday I went on a motorcycle trip with my club. We had about forty motorcycles, many coming from afar—a tremendous turnout considering how advanced the season is. This event was particularly involving for me, as my local group was in charge of the organization. We were going to visit the Foreste Casentinesi National Park, which isn&amp;rsquo;t far from our hometown.
We know those roads and their surroundings well; we call them home, yet I insisted on scouting the planned route not once but twice, and I think it was crucial to the event&amp;rsquo;s success.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Last Saturday I went on a motorcycle trip with <a href="https://tomccitalia.org">my club</a>. We had about forty
motorcycles, many coming from afar—a tremendous turnout considering how
advanced the season is. This event was particularly involving for me, as my
local group was in charge of the organization. We were going to visit the
<a href="https://it.wikipedia.org/wiki/Parco_nazionale_delle_Foreste_Casentinesi%2C_Monte_Falterona_e_Campigna">Foreste Casentinesi National Park</a>, which isn&rsquo;t far from our hometown.</p>
<p>We know those roads and their surroundings well; we call them home, yet
I insisted on scouting the planned route not once but twice, and I think it was
crucial to the event&rsquo;s success. On the narrow road that climbs to a mountain
pass, we spotted a mobile traffic light (for a road construction site) with
a long (six minutes!) red/green cycle. We arranged a plan in case the
motorcycle&rsquo;s column split at the light: almost one kilometer past the red
light, there was a safe place where the forward group could safely stop off the
road and wait for the rest to rejoin. All the participants were informed at the
departure briefing: if you get stopped at the red light, don&rsquo;t get
over-stressed: we&rsquo;ll be waiting for you one kilometer down the road. You won&rsquo;t
see us, but we&rsquo;ll be waiting for you safely. Don&rsquo;t rush it, and don&rsquo;t stop to
phone us. We won&rsquo;t be at the first apparently-good parking place but at the
second spot, which, despite not looking as good, is way safer (less gravel on
the ground). Situations like these can cause confusion and danger to a large
group of motorcycles roaming on narrow, steep mountain roads which are often in
poor conditiong. The reconnaissance ride allowed us to plan for several
potential pitfalls like this one.</p>
<p>Anyways, I&rsquo;m rambling. It was a great late autumn trip. The woods are
spectacular this time of the year, which is why we hit that area with this
trip.</p>
<p><em>Update. A video recorded during the event is available on <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=rDoGXW9K7IM">YouTube</a></em>.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" src="/images/foreste-casentinesi-tomcc-3.jpg" alt=""  />

<img loading="lazy" src="/images/foreste-casentinesi-tomcc-2.jpg" alt=""  />

<img loading="lazy" src="/images/foreste-casentinesi-tomcc-1.jpg" alt=""  />
</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Motorcycling the Dolomites with the club</title>
      <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/motorcycling-the-dolomites-with-the-club/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 Sep 2022 07:05:25 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nicolaiarocci.com/motorcycling-the-dolomites-with-the-club/</guid>
      <description>Last weekend I went on a motorcycle trip with my club. Our goal was to visit the beautiful Dolomites in the Italian Alps1. We had twenty motorcycles on the road, evenly split between modern classics (Bonnevillles in all their variations) and adventure bikes (Tigers new and old). A great turnout considering that the weather forecast for the weekend wasn&amp;rsquo;t exactly great. Of all the TOMCC members who registered, only two were missing because they tested positive for COVID.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><img loading="lazy" src="/images/dolomiti_tomcc_2022.JPG" alt=""  />
</p>
<p>Last weekend I went on a motorcycle trip with <a href="https://tomccitalia.org">my club</a>. Our goal was to
visit the beautiful Dolomites in the Italian Alps<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1</a></sup>. We had twenty
motorcycles on the road, evenly split between modern classics (Bonnevillles in
all their variations) and adventure bikes (Tigers new and old). A great turnout
considering that the weather forecast for the weekend wasn&rsquo;t exactly great. Of
all the TOMCC members who registered, only two were missing because they tested
positive for COVID.</p>
<p>Seeing old and new friends and spending time together roaming the mountain
roads felt great. We even visited places I didn&rsquo;t know about, namely the <a href="https://www.agordinodolomiti.it/index.php/cosa-vedere/natura/lago-del-mis/">Soffia
Falls at Mis Lake</a> and <a href="https://www.castellodiandraz.it">Castle Andraz</a>. After lunch at <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lake_Misurina">Malga
Misurina</a>, where the food was good and personnel not so much, we were
supposed to cover another long stretch of road up to the springs of the Piave
river. When we looked in that direction and saw the intimidating front of
blue/black clouds ready to open their floodgates on us, we changed our minds
and headed back to our base camp. We still got flooded, but certainly not as
much as if we&rsquo;d pressed on with the original plan. The next day, a handful of
us continued roaming the countryside for more fantastic views, corners, food,
and camaraderie.</p>
<p>I&rsquo;m grateful to Sandro (&ldquo;Momo&rdquo;) for organizing this event. I know very well how
demanding and stressful running a motorcycle event can be. So far, we&rsquo;ve always
been lucky to have people willing to take on the challenge and volunteer to
hold events all around the country. As long as this continues, we&rsquo;ll have
a bright future and lots of fun.</p>
<div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
<hr>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1">
<p>Last year, I went there with a fellow TOMCC member and recorded a YouTube video. Check it out <a href="/triumph-bonneville-dolomites-ride-2021/">here</a>.
[rss]: <a href="https://nicolaiarocci.com/index.xml">https://nicolaiarocci.com/index.xml</a>
[tw]: <a href="http://twitter.com/nicolaiarocci">http://twitter.com/nicolaiarocci</a>
[nl]: <a href="https://buttondown.email/nicolaiarocci">https://buttondown.email/nicolaiarocci</a>&#160;<a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
</ol>
</div>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Triumph Bonneville Dolomites Ride 2021</title>
      <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/triumph-bonneville-dolomites-ride-2021/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Jun 2021 07:05:25 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nicolaiarocci.com/triumph-bonneville-dolomites-ride-2021/</guid>
      <description>So the motorcycle-touring season has started, albeit a little late this year because of the COVID situation, and I&amp;rsquo;ve been avidly pursuing it. On Sunday, I embarked on a 700 km trip from my place to the Dolomites and back.
It&amp;rsquo;s been a glorious day. We (Antonio and I) visited many renowned Mountain Passes, enjoyed stunning views, ate great food and chatted like there&amp;rsquo;s no tomorrow.
I took my GoPro along with me.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>So the motorcycle-touring season has started, albeit a little late this year
because of the COVID situation, and I&rsquo;ve been avidly pursuing it. On Sunday,
I embarked on a 700 km trip from my place to the Dolomites and back.</p>
<p>It&rsquo;s been a glorious day.  We (<a href="/musings-on-an-unexpected-motorcycle-trip/">Antonio</a> and I) visited many renowned
Mountain Passes, enjoyed stunning views, ate great food and chatted like
there&rsquo;s no tomorrow.</p>
<p>I took my GoPro along with me. I wanted to record some scenes to inspire my
motorcycle club<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1</a></sup> comrades. However, I admit I was dubious that it would be
worth the hassle. Filming while driving would be difficult; editing and
assembling the cuts later would be tedious. Moreover, I have almost no
experience with this stuff.</p>
<p>The video is available on YouTube, and I already know it&rsquo;s probably too long.
Ideally, it should feature live voice recording, possibly a second camera
point-of-view, and, heck, even some drone footage<sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">2</a></sup>. But it&rsquo;s only the first
attempt; it will have to do.</p>
<p>Contrary to my expectations, filming on the go wasn&rsquo;t too stressful, and
editing was.. ok I guess. However, once it was done and I finally got to watch
it, I realized the obvious: it will primarily serve as a remarkable memory of
a glorious day. Eventually, it will also inspire some of my club comrades; but
that&rsquo;s now a secondary goal.</p>

<div style="position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;">
  <iframe src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/s7SUZZ1dvd0" style="position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;" allowfullscreen title="YouTube Video"></iframe>
</div>

<div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
<hr>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1">
<p>The Triumph Owners MotorCycle Club (<a href="https://tomccitalia.org/">italy</a>; <a href="https://tomcc.org">international</a>)&#160;<a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
<li id="fn:2">
<p>For some quality moto vlogging, see the <a href="https://www.youtube.com/c/ItchyBoots">Itchy Boots</a> on YouTube
[rss]: <a href="https://nicolaiarocci.com/index.xml">https://nicolaiarocci.com/index.xml</a>
[tw]: <a href="http://twitter.com/nicolaiarocci">http://twitter.com/nicolaiarocci</a>
[nl]: <a href="https://buttondown.email/nicolaiarocci">https://buttondown.email/nicolaiarocci</a>&#160;<a href="#fnref:2" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
</ol>
</div>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
