<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>religion on Nicola Iarocci</title>
    <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/tags/religion/</link>
    <description>Recent content in religion on Nicola Iarocci</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <copyright>Produced / Written / Maintained by [Nicola Iarocci](/) since 2010</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 01 May 2023 07:05:25 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://nicolaiarocci.com/tags/religion/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>The religious aspects of the corporate space race</title>
      <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/the-religious-aspects-of-the-corporate-space-race/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 May 2023 07:05:25 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nicolaiarocci.com/the-religious-aspects-of-the-corporate-space-race/</guid>
      <description>A fascinating article surfaced on Nautilus last week. Mary-Jane Rubenstein, a professor of religion and science in society at Wesleyan University, shares her concerns about the technical strides and aspirations of Elon Musk&amp;rsquo;s SpaceX, the company&amp;rsquo;s mission to enable thousands of people to live on Mars, and the ethics of terraforming the planet to be more like Earth. What&amp;rsquo;s intriguing, though, is Rubenstein&amp;rsquo;s thoughts about the religious underpinnings of the United States space program and how even modern science is still hostage to imperialistic Christian ideas.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>A fascinating article surfaced on Nautilus last week. Mary-Jane Rubenstein, a professor of religion and science in
society at Wesleyan University, shares her concerns about the technical strides and aspirations of Elon Musk&rsquo;s SpaceX,
the company&rsquo;s mission to enable thousands of people to live on Mars, and the ethics of terraforming the planet to be
more like Earth. What&rsquo;s intriguing, though, is Rubenstein&rsquo;s thoughts about the religious underpinnings of the United
States space program and how even modern science is still hostage to imperialistic Christian ideas.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>“I started realizing that religion shows up in the natural sciences and the contemporary world in a funny and alarming
way,” Rubenstein said. “Because sciences tend to think of themselves as something as far away as possible from
religion, as having freed themselves from God. To an extent that’s true. But in the process, they tend to generate
these big stories, big mythologies, about the origins and the ends of the world. And conjure characters who are
heroes, gods, and monsters. I started tracking the way that the natural sciences themselves generate new ways of
understanding the world that, a couple centuries ago, we would have called religion.”</p>
</blockquote>
<p>More <a href="https://nautil.us/the-race-to-colonize-mars-perpetuates-a-dangerous-religion-298323/">here</a>.</p>
<p><em>Subscribe to the <a href="https://buttondown.email/nicolaiarocci">newsletter</a>, the <a href="https://nicolaiarocci.com/index.xml">RSS feed</a>, or <a href="https://fosstodon.org/@nicola">follow me on Mastodon</a></em></p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
