<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>blogging on Nicola Iarocci</title>
    <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/tags/blogging/</link>
    <description>Recent content in blogging on Nicola Iarocci</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <copyright>Produced / Written / Maintained by [Nicola Iarocci](/) since 2010</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 08 Feb 2024 09:25:30 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://nicolaiarocci.com/tags/blogging/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>A new golden era of blogging?</title>
      <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/a-new-golden-era-of-blogging/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 08 Feb 2024 09:25:30 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nicolaiarocci.com/a-new-golden-era-of-blogging/</guid>
      <description>After yesterday&amp;rsquo;s, another article on the modern era of blogging surfaced on my RSS feed. In A Golden Era of Blogging, Jim Nielsen boldly proposes that we live in, you guessed it, a new golden era of blogging.
He argues that the advent of the ads market tainted the original blogging scene in the mid-2000s, and something similar is now happening in the YouTube scene. Today&amp;rsquo;s independent blogger is not in it for the money (there&amp;rsquo;s none to be had) but for passion and an (unconscious?</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>After <a href="/the-20-year-indie-web-cycle-maybe/">yesterday</a>&rsquo;s, another article on the
modern era of blogging surfaced on my RSS feed. In <a href="https://blog.jim-nielsen.com/2024/golden-era-blogging/">A Golden Era of
Blogging</a>, Jim Nielsen
boldly proposes that we live in, you guessed it, a new golden era of blogging.</p>
<p>He argues that the advent of the ads market tainted the original blogging scene
in the mid-2000s, and something similar is now happening in the YouTube scene.
Today&rsquo;s independent blogger is not in it for the money (there&rsquo;s none to be had)
but for passion and an (unconscious?) belief in indie web ideals, and these are
precisely the forces that drove the first wave of bloggers in the 2000s.</p>
<p>We modern bloggers still inhabit a tiny self-indulging bubble that is not
comparable with the original scene. But you know what, I feel comfortable in it.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
