<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>tradewars2002 on Nicola Iarocci</title>
    <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/tags/tradewars2002/</link>
    <description>Recent content in tradewars2002 on Nicola Iarocci</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 29 May 2021 07:05:25 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://nicolaiarocci.com/tags/tradewars2002/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Trade Wars 2002 and its connection to Eve Online</title>
      <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/trade-wars-2002-and-its-connection-to-eve-online/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 29 May 2021 07:05:25 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nicolaiarocci.com/trade-wars-2002-and-its-connection-to-eve-online/</guid>
      <description>Trade Wars 2002 was a great 1991 online game I hosted on one of my BBSes back in the day. Not sure if it was Lorien or Phoenix BBS; it might have been the latter given the game&amp;rsquo;s release date. I totally forgot TW2002 until yesterday when I spotted this 1991: Trade Wars 2002 article on the 50 Years of Text Games newsletter.
I humbly confess that, until yesterday, I never made the obvious connection between TW2002 and Eve Online.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Trade Wars 2002 was a  great 1991 online game I hosted on one of my BBSes <a href="https://nicolaiarocci.com/a-trip-down-memory-lane-fidonet-and-usenet/">back
in the day</a>. Not sure if it was Lorien or Phoenix BBS; it might have been
the latter given the game&rsquo;s release date. I totally forgot TW2002 until
yesterday when I spotted this <a href="https://if50.substack.com/p/1991-trade-wars-2002">1991: Trade Wars 2002</a> article on the <em>50
Years of Text Games</em> newsletter.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" src="/images/trade-wars-2002.png" alt="Trade Wards 2002"  />
</p>
<p>I humbly confess that, until yesterday, I never made the obvious connection
between TW2002 and Eve Online. That&rsquo;s quite startling considering that I&rsquo;ve
been a beta player first and then an avid Eve player for a few years (Eve was
also the last game I seriously played on a computer.)</p>
<p>In retrospect, what&rsquo;s surprising is that Station Interaction, possibly the best
trait of TW2002, never really made it to Eve Online (not in my playing
timeframe, at least).</p>
<blockquote>
<p>The StarDock was a key addition to Martin’s version of the game that went
a long way toward making its galaxy feel more like a dynamic, living place.
It’s filled with things to do: shop, gamble, visit a theatre to watch
ASCII-art sci-fi parody “movies” (short animations) with titles like Vulcan
Thunder. But more interesting are the chances for community interaction. The
StarDock’s tavern provides a range of different ways to interact with fellow
players: among other options, you can pay credits to post a public message
that everyone will see, add to the graffiti scrawled on the bathroom wall, or
pay a “grimy Trader” in the back room to learn information about other
players, such as what sector their ship was last seen in. The grimy trader
could share a huge selection of hints and useful info about the game state,
provided you could think of the right things to ask him about and had the
credits to pay.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>And of course:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>The StarDock also holds secrets: the large menu of available commands doesn’t
show all the options available. Pressing a key not listed on the menu would
describe your character exploring the seedier, lesser-known parts of the
station. A particular unlisted key would lead you to a locked door and a secret
password which, once learned—from the grimy Trader, perhaps, or another
player—admits you to the Underground, where nefarious players can buy illicit
goods and coordinate against law-abiding Federation forces.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Eve was (probably still is) a fantastic concept. I was Jexter the Caldari. With
my friend Fist, we founded a small roleplaying space-pirate group known as
Jokers. Back in our time, I think <a href="https://oldforums.eveonline.com/?a=topic&amp;threadID=356966">we made the news</a>.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" src="/images/eve-online-space-station.png" alt="Eve&amp;rsquo;s Online 2009 Space Station"  />
</p>
<p>But what we found always missing was space station interaction. Besides
a generic system-wide chat, nothing encouraged players to spend time (and
roleplay!) while their ships were docked at those stunning space stations.
That&rsquo;s something TW2002 nailed down to near perfection. I wish Eve had that. It
could have kept me in the game for far longer.</p>
<p><em>Subscribe to the <a href="https://nicolaiarocci.substack.com">newsletter</a>, the <a href="https://nicolaiarocci.com/index.xml">RSS feed</a>, or follow @<a href="http://twitter.com/nicolaiarocci">nicolaiarocci</a> on Twitter</em></p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
