<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>wikis on Nicola Iarocci</title>
    <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/tags/wikis/</link>
    <description>Recent content in wikis on Nicola Iarocci</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <copyright>Produced / Written / Maintained by [Nicola Iarocci](/) since 2010</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 09 Feb 2024 15:58:54 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://nicolaiarocci.com/tags/wikis/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>GitHub Wikis don&#39;t allow edits or pull requests</title>
      <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/github-wikis-dont-allow-edits-or-pull-requests/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 09 Feb 2024 15:58:54 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nicolaiarocci.com/github-wikis-dont-allow-edits-or-pull-requests/</guid>
      <description>Today I learned that GitHub wikis are not editable online and do not support pull requests. You can clone and edit a wiki locally but not return your change to the original repository.
I don&amp;rsquo;t use wikis in my projects; I prefer documentation to stay with the project, usually in a dedicated directory, and publish it on a dedicated site through GitHub Pages. But today was different as I opened a pull request for PaperMod, the Hugo theme I use on this website.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Today I learned that GitHub wikis are not editable online and <a href="https://github.com/orgs/community/discussions/50163">do not support
pull requests</a>. You can
clone and edit a wiki locally but not return your change to the original
repository.</p>
<p>I don&rsquo;t use wikis in <a href="/opensource/">my projects</a>; I prefer documentation to stay with the
project, usually in a dedicated directory, and publish it on a dedicated site
through GitHub Pages. But today was different as I <a href="https://github.com/adityatelange/hugo-PaperMod/pull/1419">opened a pull
request</a> for PaperMod,
the Hugo theme I use on this website. Someone asked if I could update the
documentation, too. Right, too bad it&rsquo;s impossible to do that.</p>
<p>The first ticket on this <a href="https://github.com/isaacs/github/issues/846">goes back to
2016</a>. This limitation makes GitHub
wikis impractical for any team project (maybe 90% of those on the platform),
confining them to personal projects or small experiments. No wonder so many
Wikis appear as outdated on GitHub.</p>
<p>It would be better to withdraw the feature given that GitHub offers a much more
compelling solution in Pages.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
