<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>Achievements on Nicola Iarocci</title>
    <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/tags/achievements/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Achievements on Nicola Iarocci</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- 0.143.1</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <copyright>Produced / Written / Maintained by Nicola Iarocci since 2010</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 20 Apr 2021 07:05:25 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://nicolaiarocci.com/tags/achievements/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>I am a Mars Helicopter Contributor</title>
      <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/i-am-a-mars-helicopter-contributor/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 20 Apr 2021 07:05:25 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nicolaiarocci.com/i-am-a-mars-helicopter-contributor/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt=&#34;The Mars Helicopter Contributor badge&#34; loading=&#34;lazy&#34; src=&#34;https://nicolaiarocci.com/images/mars-achievement.webp#right&#34;&gt;
As I was browsing my RSS feed this morning, I came across a [new blog][1] from
Nat Friedman over at GitHub. The piece was titled &amp;ldquo;Open source goes to Mars&amp;rdquo;,
and, of course, it caught my interest. In the article, Nat announced a Mars
2020 Helicopter Mission badge added to GitHub profiles contributing to
open-source projects and libraries used by Ingenuity. Some time ago, like many
others, I was granted the Arctic Code Vault badge, so I am familiar with the
concept. I quickly dismissed the information as &amp;ldquo;nice, not gonna get it&amp;rdquo; and
moved along.&lt;/p&gt;</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><img alt="The Mars Helicopter Contributor badge" loading="lazy" src="/images/mars-achievement.webp#right">
As I was browsing my RSS feed this morning, I came across a [new blog][1] from
Nat Friedman over at GitHub. The piece was titled &ldquo;Open source goes to Mars&rdquo;,
and, of course, it caught my interest. In the article, Nat announced a Mars
2020 Helicopter Mission badge added to GitHub profiles contributing to
open-source projects and libraries used by Ingenuity. Some time ago, like many
others, I was granted the Arctic Code Vault badge, so I am familiar with the
concept. I quickly dismissed the information as &ldquo;nice, not gonna get it&rdquo; and
moved along.</p>
<p>Later during the day, I got a mail from an Eve contributor. In between other
things, he briefly congratulated me on my new GitHub badge. I went to check my
profile, only to find that, indeed, I am a Mars Helicopter Contributor. I was
bewildered. To my knowledge, I never worked on something even remotely related
to the Ingenuity mission.</p>
<p>Years ago, I received a package from a software team at a private space agency
whose name I cannot tell. They sent me a lot of cool swag and a hand-written
letter signed by all team members. In it, I learned that they had been using
one of my open-source projects with success. They added that I should take
pride, as my work was used in one of their renowned space ships projects. The
package was their way to express gratitude. If you&rsquo;ve attended any of my talks
in the past, you probably know this story. You might have seen me wearing one
of their t-shirts too. I knew my work was used in many places; I certainly did
not expect it was contributing to a space ship program.</p>
<p>So when I reached for my profile page on GitHub today, I was confused, yes, but
not wholly unprepared. And indeed, there it is, the new, shiny Mars Helicopter
Contributor badge. A quick investigation revealed that I earned it as a Flask
contributor. To be honest, I don&rsquo;t even remember contributing to it<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1</a></sup>. I know
I&rsquo;ve used it extensively, of course, as [Eve][4] inherits from and builds on it.</p>
<p><img alt="The Mars Helicopter Contributor badge" loading="lazy" src="/images/mars-profile-badge.png"></p>
<p>So, what to make of all of this? I am happy, of course. I have a badge of
honor to show off to my kids later this evening. I appreciate the intent:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>“Many of the people who are getting a badge probably have no idea their
software is being used to fly a helicopter on another planet,” says GitHub
Senior Director of Developer Relations Martin Woodward. “We wanted to make
sure everyone was recognized for their contributions to this incredible human
achievement.” (<a href="https://github.com/readme/nasa-ingenuity-helicopter">source</a>)</p></blockquote>
<p>These badges surely help raise awareness of open-source relevance in the
modern-day world. I am grateful for it. I have to say, however, that I am not
a fan of the current gamification process going on at GitHub. I cringed when
I saw the &ldquo;How do you feel today&rdquo; box in my profile page a while ago<sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">2</a></sup>. This
Achievements feature looks good on the surface. Still, it leans itself to be
leveraged in many different, even subtle ways. Let&rsquo;s hope for the best.</p>
<div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
<hr>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1">
<p>A quick <code>git shortlog -sne</code> on the flask repo confirms the rumors.&#160;<a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
<li id="fn:2">
<p>It seems gone now?
[4]: <a href="https://github.com/pyeve/">https://github.com/pyeve/</a>
[1]: <a href="https://github.blog/2021-04-19-open-source-goes-to-mars/">https://github.blog/2021-04-19-open-source-goes-to-mars/</a>
[rss]: <a href="https://nicolaiarocci.com/index.xml">https://nicolaiarocci.com/index.xml</a>
[tw]: <a href="http://twitter.com/nicolaiarocci">http://twitter.com/nicolaiarocci</a>
[nl]: <a href="https://buttondown.email/nicolaiarocci">https://buttondown.email/nicolaiarocci</a>&#160;<a href="#fnref:2" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
</ol>
</div>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
