<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>reviews on Nicola Iarocci</title>
    <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/tags/reviews/</link>
    <description>Recent content in reviews on Nicola Iarocci</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 29 Dec 2023 15:51:02 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://nicolaiarocci.com/tags/reviews/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Books I read in 2023</title>
      <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/books-i-read-in-2023/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 29 Dec 2023 15:51:02 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nicolaiarocci.com/books-i-read-in-2023/</guid>
      <description>I read 24 books for a total of 7070 pages in 2023. That&amp;rsquo;s seven more books than last year, which is quite an outstanding result considering the seemingly unstoppable decline in book reading I have suffered in recent years. Most have been fiction books, and that&amp;rsquo;s something new and influential with the final result, as I tend to read non-fiction more slowly. The bad news is that I did not review most of the books I read this year, and that sucks.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A few late book reviews</title>
      <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/a-few-late-book-reviews/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 26 Aug 2023 07:05:25 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nicolaiarocci.com/a-few-late-book-reviews/</guid>
      <description>I&amp;rsquo;ve been reading a few books throughout the summer and needed to be more active in reviewing them here. Rather than writing five individual posts in a row (too lazy for that), I will catch up with this single post.
Born to Run 2 I&amp;rsquo;ve been back to running after a long hiatus, and this book helped me get back on track with the right, lightly-hearted approach. The fundamentals are solid (the barefoot-like technique is the way), the 90-day training plan is a good platform, the nutrition hints are remarkable, and I appreciated the injury-treatment segments.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Book Review: La Mossa del Matto (The Fool&#39;s Move)</title>
      <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/book-review-la-mossa-del-matto-the-fools-move/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 19 May 2023 07:05:25 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nicolaiarocci.com/book-review-la-mossa-del-matto-the-fools-move/</guid>
      <description>Alessandro Barbaglia&amp;rsquo;s La mossa del matto (The fool&amp;rsquo;s move) tries to be three things in one: the life story of chess champion Bobby Fischer, a reconciliation dialogue between author and father, who died too soon, as well the tracing of a daring parallel between Fischer&amp;rsquo;s relationship with Russian champion Boris Spasskij and that of Achilles and Ulysses of Homeric memory. In our neck of the woods, we say that too much is crippling, and this work runs the risk.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Book Review: Disastri (Disasters)</title>
      <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/book-review-disastri/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 14 May 2023 07:05:25 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nicolaiarocci.com/book-review-disastri/</guid>
      <description>Daniil Charms was considered a children&amp;rsquo;s author and could not stand children all his life. While his whimsical fairy tales populated illustrated books and magazines, giving him something to live on in the silence of his room, he also feverishly wrote tales for adults, equally imaginative but inhabited by an excruciating melancholy, as in fairy tales went wrong.
At the dawn of the USSR, this desperate fantasy of his was tolerable only if it was confined where it was least dangerous, in children&amp;rsquo;s literature.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Book Review: Land and Sea</title>
      <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/book-review-land-and-sea/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 May 2023 07:05:25 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nicolaiarocci.com/book-review-land-and-sea/</guid>
      <description>Land and Sea is an essay in short story form written in 1942 by Carl Schmitt. Subtitled &amp;ldquo;A consideration of world history told to my daughter Anna,&amp;rdquo; this essay recounts and summarizes the geo-historical-legal evolution of our planet since the discovery of the New World. The originality of the work lies in the author&amp;rsquo;s identification of the Earth-Sea dichotomy as the driving force of human history.
I went into this book knowing very little about the author, Carl Schmitt, and the contents.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Book Review: Medieval Callings</title>
      <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/book-review-medieval-callings/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 29 Apr 2023 06:05:25 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nicolaiarocci.com/book-review-medieval-callings/</guid>
      <description>Medieval Callings comprises eleven essays by internationally renowned medieval historians. Somewhat deceptively, only Jacques Le Goff&amp;rsquo;s prestigious name appears on the front page, as he authored the introductive essay and handpicked and curated the collection. Each piece presents a nuanced profile of a significant social or professional Middle Ages group. Warrior knights, monks, high churchmen, criminals, lepers, shepherds, artists, and prostitutes, all prominent figures of medieval society, are depicted here with great detail.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Book Review: Essere Lupo (Being Wolf)</title>
      <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/book-review-essere-lupo-being-wolf/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Apr 2023 07:05:25 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nicolaiarocci.com/book-review-essere-lupo-being-wolf/</guid>
      <description>I saw a wolf: that&amp;rsquo;s the phrase Ulf, a hunter and former forestry inspector now in his seventies, has been brooding, unable to confess to anyone since he spotted a majestic specimen at dawn on the first day of the year. Something clicks inside him, and Ulf, one of the most respected men in the village in deep Sweden where he lives, feels an increasingly solid and intimate connection with the creature.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Book Review: No Sleep Till Shengal</title>
      <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/book-review-no-sleep-till-shengal/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Mar 2023 07:05:25 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nicolaiarocci.com/book-review-no-sleep-till-shengal/</guid>
      <description>Zerocalcare is an Italian cartoonist whose strips, especially in the form of illustrated books, have surged to an iconic level in the last decade. His drawing is excellent, but it is with his writing that, I think, he conquered fame. His stories are fun to read and yet profound and vibrant, all at the same time. Also, he often touches on themes nobody else covers, at least not in the comics world.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Book Review: Red Mars</title>
      <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/book-review-red-mars/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 02 Mar 2023 07:05:25 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nicolaiarocci.com/book-review-red-mars/</guid>
      <description>Regarding space-related topics and scientific research, Casey Handmer&amp;rsquo;s blog is one of my references. So when Casey started his Mars Trilogy Technical Commentary and I learned about Kim Stanley Robinson&amp;rsquo;s masterpiece, I was instantly intrigued. In Casey&amp;rsquo;s opinion, KSR&amp;rsquo;s Mars Trilogy is &amp;ldquo;one of the finest works of literature ever composed.&amp;rdquo; It took a couple of weeks of futile resistance before I gave in and ordered the first book in the series, Red Mars, a 420 pages tome that attempts to depict a scientifically credible human colonization of Mars1.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Book Review: Sanguina Ancora (Still Bleeding)</title>
      <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/book-review-sanguina-ancora-still-bleeding/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Feb 2023 07:05:25 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nicolaiarocci.com/book-review-sanguina-ancora-still-bleeding/</guid>
      <description>Sanguina Ancora (Still Bleeding) is not a biography but a passionate and informative tribute to Dostoevsky. The nonlinear, not literary style works and the continuous back and forth between Dostoevsky&amp;rsquo;s epic and the author&amp;rsquo;s own experiences as a scholar and Russian literature enthusiast is probably a good idea as it helps stress the actualness of Dostoevsky&amp;rsquo;s opus.
However, the continuous jumping in and out of the Russian&amp;rsquo;s life, though sympathetic at first, gets tedious over time.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Book Review: Uomini, boschi e api</title>
      <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/book-review-uomini-boschi-e-api/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 21 Jan 2023 07:05:25 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nicolaiarocci.com/book-review-uomini-boschi-e-api/</guid>
      <description>I wish everyone could listen to the song of the partridges as the sun rises, see the deer on pastures in spring, the larch trees reddened by autumn on the edges of rocks, the darting of fish among the clear waters of streams, and the bees gathering nectar from the flowering cherry trees. In these stories, I write about village places. These natural environments are still livable, about the beautiful social insects that are bees, but also about ancient jobs that are slowly and inexorably disappearing.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Book Review: Stoner</title>
      <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/book-review-stoner/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 Dec 2022 07:05:25 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nicolaiarocci.com/book-review-stoner/</guid>
      <description>I tend to shy away from publishing cases, so Stoner has been resting on my yeah-maybe-one-day list for years. Over time I stumbled on notable mentions that kept the book on the fringe of my attention zone. Then one day, I read a brief and intriguing [review][2] in Giovanni Zagni&amp;rsquo;s excellent newsletter, Incertezze. Like me, Zagni suffers from the stay-away-from-editorial-cases idiosyncrasy, but he finally gave in, read the thing, reread it, and finally tagged it a modern classic.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Book Review: Candide</title>
      <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/book-review-candide/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 18 Dec 2022 07:05:25 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nicolaiarocci.com/book-review-candide/</guid>
      <description>This short novel was a genuine surprise. I certainly didn&amp;rsquo;t expect Voltaire to be this accessible, witty, sarcastic, and also outrageous for the era (1759). Below the surface of a seemingly entertaining and often absurd sequence of improbable events is a constant philosophical struggle. Quoting from the back cover:
Candide is the story of a gentle man who, though pummeled and slapped in every direction by fate, clings desperately to the belief that he lives in &amp;ldquo;the best of all possible worlds.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Book Review: When We Cease to Understand the World</title>
      <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/book-review-when-we-cease-to-understand-the-world/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 10 Dec 2022 07:05:25 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nicolaiarocci.com/book-review-when-we-cease-to-understand-the-world/</guid>
      <description>When We Cease to Understand the World, by Benjamin Labatut, is a strange narrative object. It mixes fact and fiction in imaginative ways, sometimes making it hard for the reader to distinguish between them, which is probably a testimonial to the experiment&amp;rsquo;s success. As I was reading, Wu Ming&amp;rsquo;s unidentified narrative objects (UNO) came to mind. If it doesn&amp;rsquo;t qualify as UNO, it comes close enough. It certainly fits the &amp;lsquo;faction&amp;rsquo; (fact+fiction) genre, if such a thing exists.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Book Review: Mašen&#39;ka</title>
      <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/book-review-ma%C5%A1enka/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Nov 2022 07:05:25 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nicolaiarocci.com/book-review-ma%C5%A1enka/</guid>
      <description>Masen&amp;rsquo;ka (or Mary) is Nabokov&amp;rsquo;s debut novel. It was written when he was in his twenties, living as an émigré in Berlin, just like the story&amp;rsquo;s protagonist. In the introduction of my Italian edition (Adelphi), the author admits that some life events poured into the narration. The depiction of Ganin&amp;rsquo;s life in a pension filled with fellow Russian ex-pats, and the relationships between them, is undoubtedly reminiscent of Nabokov&amp;rsquo;s own experience.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Book Review: The Crow Comes Last</title>
      <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/book-review-the-crow-comes-last/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 25 Nov 2022 07:05:25 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nicolaiarocci.com/book-review-the-crow-comes-last/</guid>
      <description>The Crow Comes Last is a collection of thirty short stories written between 1945 and 1948, primarily based on the author&amp;rsquo;s wartime experiences as a resistance fighter during WWII and then in postwar Italy. Some are brutal, others funny, and some are gritty. They all revolve around the themes he perfectly defined while talking about his book:
I prefer to divide the subject into three parts, to highlight three thematic lines of my work from those years.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Book Review: Ravenna</title>
      <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/book-review-ravenna/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 07 Nov 2022 07:05:25 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nicolaiarocci.com/book-review-ravenna/</guid>
      <description>Nerdy prelude. Local Bulletin Board Systems (BBS) were all the range when I was a teenager. With my group of local hackers, we hacked our way into ITAPAC, the then-leading Italian packet-switching network (we are talking pre-Internet era here.) Via ITAPAC, we&amp;rsquo;d connect to so-called &amp;ldquo;out-dial systems&amp;rdquo; in the USA. From one of those, we&amp;rsquo;d finally call our target BBSes with a local call at no cost. We felt so invincible!</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Book Review: The Count of Monte Cristo</title>
      <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/book-review-the-count-of-monte-cristo/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 16 Sep 2022 07:05:25 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nicolaiarocci.com/book-review-the-count-of-monte-cristo/</guid>
      <description>In my early morning stroll, I sometimes listen to audiobooks. This was the case with The Count of Monte Cristo. Rai Radio 3, the third channel of the national broadcasting service, has been airing Ad Alta Voce (Aloud) for many years. In the program, top-tier actors read old and new literary classics. The quality of these productions is astounding. Audio editions are often edited, which was the case with The Count, as the unabridged edition surpasses the 1200-page count (a little-known fact is that most printed editions are also edited for brevity).</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Book Review: Smiling Bears</title>
      <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/book-review-smiling-bears/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 12 Sep 2022 07:05:25 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nicolaiarocci.com/book-review-smiling-bears/</guid>
      <description>My perception of zoos has always been of prisons—places of suffering where animals are held captive for human entertainment. Smiling Bears offered a new perspective. Some (hopefully most) zoos provide a safe harbor to abused and rescued animals who could never return to their natural habitats. Zookeepers like Else Poulsen care for these creatures, accompanying them in their rehabilitation process. I imagine not all zoos and zookeepers meet these standards, but it is reassuring to know these things happen.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Book Review: A Captive West or the tragedy of Central Europe</title>
      <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/book-review-a-captive-west-or-the-tragedy-of-central-europe/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 18 Aug 2022 07:05:25 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nicolaiarocci.com/book-review-a-captive-west-or-the-tragedy-of-central-europe/</guid>
      <description>Adelphi1 prints in book form two unpublished speeches by Milan Kundera, one from 1967 and the other from 1983, in which the great Czech writer reflects on the fate of the small nations in central Europe and the cultural drift of (western) Europe as a whole. As we read along, thanks to Kundera&amp;rsquo;s acumen and depth of analysis, we find many surprising ante-litteram references to today&amp;rsquo;s critical situation (Russian-Ukrainian war).</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Book Review: Just an Ordinary Day</title>
      <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/book-review-just-an-ordinary-day/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 18 Aug 2022 07:05:25 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nicolaiarocci.com/book-review-just-an-ordinary-day/</guid>
      <description>As a Shirley Jackson fan, I couldn&amp;rsquo;t pass on this new collection of unpublished short stories. A good chunk of these was unheard of for thirty years until someone unearthed some cardboard boxes in a Vermont barn and then sent them to her heirs.
Unlike The Lottery, where all tales followed a distinct theme, Just an Ordinary Day has little to unite the stories. Several genres are represented: classic family stories, supernatural, horror, and unsettling accounts of day-to-day life in the fifties all make up the list.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Book Review: Italica</title>
      <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/book-review-italica/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 29 Jul 2022 07:05:25 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nicolaiarocci.com/book-review-italica/</guid>
      <description>Suppose you are looking for a juicy and thought-provoking read on Italy&amp;rsquo;s twentieth-century crucial moments. In that case, I heartily recommend Italica by Giacomo Papi, a significant collection of short stories by prominent Italian writers of the period including the likes of Italo Calvino, Elsa Morante, Beppe Fenoglio, Natalia Ginzburg, and Giorgio Scerbanenco. A short essay introduces each tale. I thoughtfully appreciated these introductions, sometimes even more so than the story itself, as they are quintessential to comprehending the tale&amp;rsquo;s historical background.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Book Review: The Rings of Saturn</title>
      <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/book-review-the-rings-of-saturn/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 Jun 2022 07:05:25 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nicolaiarocci.com/book-review-the-rings-of-saturn/</guid>
      <description>W.G. Sebald is widely considered among the best modern German authors, so I approached this book with curiosity and high expectations. The Rings of Saturn records the author&amp;rsquo;s walking tour along the East Coast of England. As W.G. Sebald resides in the intellectual world, his tour naturally brings up literary, cultural or historical reminiscences.
An astute Goodreads reviewer noted that Britain&amp;rsquo;s decline&amp;rsquo;s eccentric and grotesque aspects are this work&amp;rsquo;s central theme.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Book Review: Invisible Cities</title>
      <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/book-review-invisible-cities/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 May 2022 07:05:25 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nicolaiarocci.com/book-review-invisible-cities/</guid>
      <description>&amp;ldquo;Kublai Khan does not necessarily believe everything Marco Polo says when he describes the cities visited on his expeditions, but the emperor of the Tartars does continue listening to the young Venetian with greater attention and curiosity than he shows any other messenger or explorer of his.&amp;rdquo; So begins Italo Calvino&amp;rsquo;s compilation of fragmentary urban images. As Marco tells the khan about Armilla, which &amp;ldquo;has nothing that makes it seem a city, except the water pipes that rise vertically where the houses should be and spread out horizontally where the floors should be,&amp;rdquo; the spider-web city of Octavia, and other marvelous burgs, it may be that he is creating them all out of his imagination, or perhaps he is recreating fine details of his native Venice over and over again, or perhaps he is simply recounting some of the myriad possible forms a city might take.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Book Review: Memoirs of Hadrian</title>
      <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/book-review-memoirs-of-hadrian/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 16 May 2022 07:05:25 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nicolaiarocci.com/book-review-memoirs-of-hadrian/</guid>
      <description>Memoirs of Hadrian and its author Marguerite Yourcenar have always induced a cautious fear in me. I fretted the tome for high literary circles, one of those texts so infused with learned quotations and obscure literary references as to be utterly indigestible to the average reader. Despite their evident reputation, I relegated the Memoirs to the bottom of my reading list for a long time. When I stumbled on another reference to Yourcenar&amp;rsquo;s work a couple of weeks ago, I finally decided to plunge and pull the Memoirs off the shelf.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Book Review: Lone Rider</title>
      <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/book-review-lone-rider/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Apr 2022 07:05:25 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nicolaiarocci.com/book-review-lone-rider/</guid>
      <description>In 1982, at just twenty-three years old and halfway through her architectural studies, Elspeth Beard left her family and friends in London and set off on a 35,000-mile solo adventure around the world on her 1974 BMW R60/6.
Exhausted by a recent breakup and with only a few savings scraped together from her job in a pub, a tent, a few clothes and some tools, all packed on the back of her bike, she was determined to prove herself.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Book Review: Roumeli</title>
      <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/book-review-roumeli/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 02 Apr 2022 07:05:25 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nicolaiarocci.com/book-review-roumeli/</guid>
      <description>Roumeli describes Fermor&amp;rsquo;s travels around Northern Greece and Macedonia. He visits secluded and remote areas and describes the rugged countryside and how people of these remote regions live. As he meets Sarakatsan shepherds and spends some time with them, visits the impressive monasteries of Meteora, attempts to track a pair of Byron&amp;rsquo;s slippers in Missolonghi and investigates Kravara and its secret language, he makes acute observations about these communities and their history.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Book Review: Thinking Fast and Slow</title>
      <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/book-review-thinking-fast-and-slow/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Mar 2022 07:05:25 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nicolaiarocci.com/book-review-thinking-fast-and-slow/</guid>
      <description>This book stands up to its fame. It&amp;rsquo;s chock-full of precious insights on our decision-making and behavioral processes and how and why we humans are often capable of making informed yet awful decisions. The bad news is that we can hardly avoid most of these biases, no matter how hard we try and even if we know about them. So-called experts in the field are subject to these same biases: their short-term estimates and predictions can even be pretty good, but they will fail miserably in the long term, like any other man or woman.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Book Review: Eichmann in Jerusalem. A Report on the Banality of Evil</title>
      <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/book-review-eichmann-in-jerusalem.-a-report-on-the-banality-of-evil/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Feb 2022 07:05:25 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nicolaiarocci.com/book-review-eichmann-in-jerusalem.-a-report-on-the-banality-of-evil/</guid>
      <description>This book is not about the famous, daring, and in some ways fortunate capture of Eichmann in Buenos Aires in 1960, nor about the covert transfer of the Nazi officer to Israel. Instead, the volume recounts the 1961 trial in Jerusalem, which ended with the defendant being sentenced to death. Hannah Arendt followed the trial as a correspondent for The New Yorker. She took notes, studied the papers, and reconstructed the many witnesses&amp;rsquo; personal stories.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Book Review: Finnish Fairy Tales</title>
      <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/book-review-finnish-fairy-tales/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Jan 2022 07:05:25 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nicolaiarocci.com/book-review-finnish-fairy-tales/</guid>
      <description>Over the years, Iperborea, one of my favorite Italian publishers, has been publishing an unofficial Nordic Tales series. Their renowned nordic fiction series includes one fairy tale volume per year, usually published in December, just for Christmas. The first book was Lapland Tales in 2014, and then they continued with Danish, Icelandic, Swedish, Faroe, Norwegian, Greenlandic and then Finnish in 2021. I&amp;rsquo;ve been greedily reading each one of them, usually as my last book of the year.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Book Review: Consider the Lobster</title>
      <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/book-review-consider-the-lobster/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Dec 2021 07:05:25 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nicolaiarocci.com/book-review-consider-the-lobster/</guid>
      <description>I found a Consider the Lobster review on Goodreads that almost precisely matches my thoughts on DFW and the book. Hence, given the lazy Christmas-break mood I am in right now, I am conceding myself the right to copy-paste and edit David&amp;rsquo;s review right away.
I know of nobody else who writes as thoughtfully and intelligently as DFW. That he manages to write so informatively, with humor and genuine wit, on almost any subject under the sun is mind-blowing – it&amp;rsquo;s also why I am willing to forgive his occasional stylistic excesses.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Book Review: About the Meaning of Life</title>
      <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/book-review-about-the-meaning-of-life/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 26 Dec 2021 07:05:25 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nicolaiarocci.com/book-review-about-the-meaning-of-life/</guid>
      <description>I&amp;rsquo;m not a regular philosophy reader, much less of self-improvement guides. I&amp;rsquo;m wary of the latter and too ignorant for the former. Yet, theologian Vito Mancuso has intrigued me for some time. I followed his podcast on the &amp;ldquo;Four Masters of Life&amp;rdquo;1 and found it excellent. In it, Mancuso discusses his four tutelary deities: &amp;ldquo;Socrates, the educator. Buddha, the physician. Confucius, the politician. Jesus, the prophet.&amp;rdquo; I also listened to some TV interviews where I always found him fascinating.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Book Review: A useless man</title>
      <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/book-review-a-useless-man/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 04 Dec 2021 07:05:25 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nicolaiarocci.com/book-review-a-useless-man/</guid>
      <description>Sait Faik Abasıyanık is an acclaimed Turkish storyteller. A useless man is a collection of short stories that spans nearly two decades of the author&amp;rsquo;s output, offering a glimpse into his imaginative and troubled mind. His overflowing love for others (even sensual, with a preference for street kids) combined with a &amp;ldquo;mal de vivre&amp;rdquo; that pushes him towards self-destruction are apparent.
His passion for the most popular areas of Istanbul and, in contrast, the atavistic nostalgia for the simple life of the nearby fishermen islets exudes from these stories, which often run similar one after another.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Book Review: Endurance, Shackleton&#39;s Incredible Voyage</title>
      <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/book-review-endurance-shackletons-incredible-voyage/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 28 Nov 2021 07:05:25 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nicolaiarocci.com/book-review-endurance-shackletons-incredible-voyage/</guid>
      <description>Of all the stories of maritime adventures I&amp;rsquo;ve read, that of the Endurance, masterfully told by Alfred Lansing in this book, is the most incredible and shocking. Unbelievable to say, given the premise (a crew of 28 men stranded on the Antarctic pack, camped on floating slabs of ice hundreds of miles from any human settlement, at the gates of the Antarctic winter), but the story does not end in tragedy.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Book Review: Mathematics is politics</title>
      <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/book-review-mathematics-is-politics/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 25 Nov 2021 07:05:25 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nicolaiarocci.com/book-review-mathematics-is-politics/</guid>
      <description>Mathematics as the study of relationships: in this aspect lies the similarity and affinity with politics. And then the need in both cases to proceed with stubbornness and trust, without fearing error which, as in all difficult things, is not only lying in wait but inherent, and often, when it is discovered, it is the stimulus and engine of new successes and goals. Hence the need to respect rules and (not or, mind you) the compelling need for revolutions.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Book Review: King and Emperor, A New Life of Charlemagne</title>
      <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/book-review-king-and-emperor-a-new-life-of-charlemagne/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 31 Oct 2021 07:05:25 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nicolaiarocci.com/book-review-king-and-emperor-a-new-life-of-charlemagne/</guid>
      <description>In this scholarly biography by Janet L. Nelson, Charlemagne is stripped back from the years of mythologizing and idolizing that have occurred since his death. He is presented as distinctly human, and this book is the first time I have felt I could reasonably understand Charlemagne as the man he was, not the man he has since been painted to be. Moreover, Nelson is excellent in her discussions of Charlemagne&amp;rsquo;s wives and their roles.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Book Review: Language of the Spirit, An Introduction to Classical Music</title>
      <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/book-review-language-of-the-spirit-an-introduction-to-classical-music/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 Oct 2021 07:05:25 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nicolaiarocci.com/book-review-language-of-the-spirit-an-introduction-to-classical-music/</guid>
      <description>In this introduction to classical music, Jan Swafford explains the different musical periods and their differences. Each period has its introductory chapter, followed by chapters dedicated to the most influential composers of the era. The choice is comprehensive and well cared for, with the most relevant names well-investigated both in biography and works. For each composer, Swafford also offers some listening suggestions. Biographies thicken as we get into the contemporary era.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Book Review: Nausea</title>
      <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/book-review-nausea/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Sep 2021 07:05:25 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nicolaiarocci.com/book-review-nausea/</guid>
      <description>Antoine Roquentin, the protagonist of the novel, is a former adventurer who has been living for three years in Bouville, a fictional French seaport town, researching the life of an 18th-century diplomat. During his previous life around the world, Antoine has seen many places, met many interesting people, done exciting things. For the last three years, however, he&amp;rsquo;s been alone in Bouville. He has no friends and no desire to make some or meet anyone.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Book Review: Proud tobea Flyer</title>
      <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/book-review-proud-tobea-flyer/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 28 Aug 2021 07:05:25 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nicolaiarocci.com/book-review-proud-tobea-flyer/</guid>
      <description>I happened across this book by pure chance. After having ice cream in our favourite place in Milano Marittima, my wife and I visited a small street market with all kinds of booths. Of course, there was a used book stand toward which I immediately gravitated. A quick scan revealed nothing of interest, so I moved along. But Serena, who arrived at the booth moments after I left, knew more. A simple, no-frills, cardboard-covered book which carried a giant PROUD 2BEA FLYER title on the spine caught her attention.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Book Review: Nomadland</title>
      <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/book-review-nomadland/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 21 Aug 2021 07:05:25 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nicolaiarocci.com/book-review-nomadland/</guid>
      <description>Some call them homeless. The new nomads refer to themselves as &amp;lsquo;houseless&amp;rsquo;. Many took to the road after their savings were obliterated by the Great Recession. To keep their gas tanks and bellies full, they work long hours at hard, physical jobs. In a time of flat wages and rising housing costs, they have unshackled themselves from rent and mortgages as a way to get by. They are surviving America.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Book Review. Eight Days in May: The Final Collapse of the Third Reich</title>
      <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/book-review.-eight-days-in-may-the-final-collapse-of-the-third-reich/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 18 Jul 2021 07:05:25 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nicolaiarocci.com/book-review.-eight-days-in-may-the-final-collapse-of-the-third-reich/</guid>
      <description>Volker Ullrich&amp;rsquo;s Eight Days in May describes the period from April 30, 1945, the day of Hitler&amp;rsquo;s suicide, to May 8, the day of signing the German capitulation, with significant jumps backwards in time and some hops in the future. We&amp;rsquo;re covering only eight days, and the dictator dies on day one. What essential events might ever have happened in such a short period? Well, many pivotal ones, as this well-researched work shows us.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Book Review: Power to the Words</title>
      <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/book-review-power-to-the-words/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 09 Jul 2021 07:05:25 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nicolaiarocci.com/book-review-power-to-the-words/</guid>
      <description>Vera Gheno&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;Potere alle Parole&amp;rdquo; (Power to the Words) is an essay on the importance of appropriate use of the (Italian) language, not just in written works but also and predominately in everyday life.
What would we think of a person who, having a vast wardrobe of beautiful clothes, always wore the same suit out of laziness? These situations appear unlikely; yet, they are examples of the attitude that many have towards their language: they have access to an immense, incalculable patrimony, which out of indolence, or fear, or inexperience, they use partially.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Book Review: Alpi Ribelli: Storie di montagna, resistenza e utopia</title>
      <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/book-review-alpi-ribelli-storie-di-montagna-resistenza-e-utopia/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 05 Jun 2021 07:05:25 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nicolaiarocci.com/book-review-alpi-ribelli-storie-di-montagna-resistenza-e-utopia/</guid>
      <description>The idea behind this book is fascinating. As the subtitle suggests, the book collects stories of rebel mountaineers of all kinds. Some chose to disobey orders; others built refuges of resistance, outposts of autonomy and laboratories of social innovation.
The collection is rich and varied. We go from the heretics who went with Fra Dolcino to the partisans who stopped the Nazi fascists in the mountains of Cuneo and Belluno, up to the contemporary movements against the high-speed train in the Susa Valley.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Book Review: The Voice of the Sirens. The Greeks and the art of persuasion</title>
      <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/book-review-the-voice-of-the-sirens.-the-greeks-and-the-art-of-persuasion/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 15 May 2021 07:05:25 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nicolaiarocci.com/book-review-the-voice-of-the-sirens.-the-greeks-and-the-art-of-persuasion/</guid>
      <description>According to a famous and fortunate Homeric expression, words are winged, not so much like birds but rather like arrows, which cut the air quickly to go straight to the target and break through the listener&amp;rsquo;s heart. The Greeks have always known that the word is used to convince and show truth and correctness. But they also know that it has a magical force in it: it can turn into a spell, capable of dominating and dragging the listener&amp;rsquo;s soul; to bewitch like music and to heal like medicine; but, above all, to deceive and mislead.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Book Review: One Man Caravan</title>
      <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/book-review-one-man-caravan/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 02 May 2021 07:05:25 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nicolaiarocci.com/book-review-one-man-caravan/</guid>
      <description>Robert Edison Fulton was the first solo round-the-world motorcycle tourer. He made his worldwide trip on a two-cylinder Douglas motorcycle between July 1932 and December 1933, more or less 90 years ago. On his way from London to the colonial Middle East, Fulton crossed Nazi Germany. Some of the countries and places he passed do not exist anymore. Most have changed dramatically; others, not so much. I suspect, for example, that his adventures in Syria, Afghanistan, or at the Indian-Pakistani borders might have been written today.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Book Review: The Silence, A Novel</title>
      <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/book-review-the-silence-a-novel/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 11 Apr 2021 07:05:25 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nicolaiarocci.com/book-review-the-silence-a-novel/</guid>
      <description>It is Super Bowl Sunday in the year 2022. Five people, dinner, an apartment on the east side of Manhattan. The retired physics professor and her husband and her former student waiting for the couple who will join them from what becomes a dramatic flight from Paris. The conversation ranges from a survey telescope in North-central Chile to a favorite brand of bourbon to Einstein’s 1912 Manuscript on the Special Theory of Relativity.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Book Review: In the Heart of the Sea, The Tragedy of the Waleship Essex</title>
      <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/book-review-in-the-heart-of-the-sea-the-tragedy-of-the-waleship-essex/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 02 Apr 2021 07:05:25 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nicolaiarocci.com/book-review-in-the-heart-of-the-sea-the-tragedy-of-the-waleship-essex/</guid>
      <description>While reading Erebus, The Story of a Ship, my attention was caught by a brief mention of the Whaleship Essex. Being the sucker that I am for exploration and dramatic adventure stories from the early days, I researched it, only to surface with Nathaniel Philbricks&amp;rsquo; In The Heart of the Sea in my hands.
In the Heart of the Sea brings to new life the incredible story of the wreck of the whaleship Essex - an event as mythic in its own century as the Titanic disaster in ours, and the inspiration for the climax of Moby-Dick.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Book Review: Materada</title>
      <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/book-review-materada/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 19 Mar 2021 07:05:25 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nicolaiarocci.com/book-review-materada/</guid>
      <description>I am very ignorant about the Istrian Peninsula&amp;rsquo;s history, a gap I always wanted to fill. After some research, Fulvio Tomizza&amp;rsquo;s book, Materada, surfaced as a good fit to fill this gap. It&amp;rsquo;s a semi-biographic historical novel set in the Istria of the author&amp;rsquo;s youth. Fulvio Tomizza was born in Giurizzani di Materada, Istria, in 1935. He had to go through all the torments caused in that disputed area by Fascism first (forced Italianization, cultural suppression), and then by the Second World War and the terrible events that followed: the Foibe massacres and the Istrian-Dalmatian exodus.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Book Review: The Library at Night</title>
      <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/book-review-the-library-at-night/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 06 Mar 2021 07:05:25 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nicolaiarocci.com/book-review-the-library-at-night/</guid>
      <description>As any other bookworm worth its salt, I digested a generous amount of books on books and the history of libraries. Alberto Manguel&amp;rsquo;s The Library at Night was last, and that is a pity. It probably arrived just a little too late on my shelves. I wish I found it at the beginning of my reading journey when my enthusiasm for libraries and their contents was pristine.
Manguel&amp;rsquo;s writing is mesmerizing and capable.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Book Review: We Have Always Lived in the Castle</title>
      <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/book-review-we-have-always-lived-in-the-castle/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 18 Feb 2021 07:05:25 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nicolaiarocci.com/book-review-we-have-always-lived-in-the-castle/</guid>
      <description>I came back to reading Shirley Jackson almost by coincidence. I had just finished watching The Haunting of Hill House, and, as I always do with stuff that tickles my curiosity, I was doing a little research on it. That&amp;rsquo;s how I learned that the TV Series is loosely based on a novel by the same name written by&amp;hellip; Shirley Jackson.
Still imbued by the TV Series&amp;rsquo;s atmospheres, now knowing about its connection with Jackson, I was ready for another dive into her literature of psychological suspense and terror.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Book Review: The Water Dancer</title>
      <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/book-review-the-water-dancer/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 06 Feb 2021 07:05:25 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nicolaiarocci.com/book-review-the-water-dancer/</guid>
      <description>The Water Dancer is the debut novel for Ta-Nehisi Coates, an author and journalist best known for his nonfiction works. Set in a slave plantation located in pre-civil war Virginia, this is a bold and ambitious story about slavery. From the editor website:
Young Hiram Walker was born into bondage. When his mother was sold away, Hiram was robbed of all memory of her—but was gifted with a mysterious power. Years later, when Hiram almost drowns in a river, that same power saves his life.</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Book Review: Erebus, The Story of a Ship</title>
      <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/book-review-erebus-the-story-of-a-ship/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 Jan 2021 07:05:25 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nicolaiarocci.com/book-review-erebus-the-story-of-a-ship/</guid>
      <description>I finished reading Erebus: The Story of a Ship by Michael Palin, an excellent book on the dramatic adventures of the HMS Erebus with her sister ship, the HMS Terror, first in James Clark Ross&amp;rsquo;s Antarctic expedition of 1839-43, and then during Franklin’s ill-fated Arctic expedition in search of the Northwest Passage. I knew Michael Palin as a member of the Monty Python comedy group. As it turns out, since 1980, he has also made many travel documentaries and books.</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
