<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>reviews on Nicola Iarocci</title>
    <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/tags/reviews/</link>
    <description>Recent content in reviews on Nicola Iarocci</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <copyright>Produced / Written / Maintained by [Nicola Iarocci](/) since 2010</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 30 Dec 2023 10:08:07 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://nicolaiarocci.com/tags/reviews/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Movie review: The Vast of the Night</title>
      <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/movie-review-the-vast-of-the-night/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 30 Dec 2023 10:08:07 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nicolaiarocci.com/movie-review-the-vast-of-the-night/</guid>
      <description>Yesterday evening, we watched &amp;ldquo;The Vast of the Night&amp;rdquo;, and what a pleasant surprise it was.
One night, in a small New Mexico town, a girl who works at a local radio station and an older reporter boy listen to a recording of some strange noises. Through the radio and its listeners, throughout a single night, they uncover a series of sighting stories that, from clue to clue and radio testimony to radio testimony, bring them close to uncovering something big.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Yesterday evening, we watched &ldquo;<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Vast_of_Night">The Vast of the
Night</a>&rdquo;, and what a pleasant
surprise it was.</p>
<p>One night, in a small New Mexico town, a girl who works at a local radio station
and an older reporter boy listen to a recording of some strange noises. Through
the radio and its listeners, throughout a single night, they uncover a series of
sighting stories that, from clue to clue and radio testimony to radio testimony,
bring them close to uncovering something big.</p>
<p>It has a distinctive retro soundtrack, and its beauty is the pleasure of the
stories told. At the center of everything always remains the mystery the two
protagonists try to investigate in one night, approaching the truth from
testimony to testimony. A good part of the film lies in the classic elements of
science fiction, namely the discovery (perhaps) of something from another
planet; another part, however, is the creation of the overwhelming sense of
excitement of two people from a small provincial town who increasingly feel they
are part of something important.</p>
<p>The photography, lighting, and camerawork are stellar:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>At the midpoint, Patterson wows with a tracking shot that seems to race a
half-mile down a quiet street, take a left-hook through a parking lot, sprint
through an ongoing basketball game, and zip up the crowded bleachers before
plunging out of a window. It&rsquo;s effective razzle-dazzle that will probably get
the young Oklahoman hired to make something 20 times The Vast of Night&rsquo;s budget.
Yet, the ambition behind it is just as impressive – as is the crew&rsquo;s creativity
at spinning financial limitations into magic.&quot; <br>
&ndash;Amy Nicholson, <a href="https://variety.com/2019/film/reviews/the-vast-of-night-review-1203335505/">Variety</a>.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>&ldquo;The Vast of the Night&rdquo; is a small, independent, character-driven debut film that
perfectly captures America&rsquo;s province life in the 50s and cleverly leverages
those atmospheres. Inventive and charming, it is also a homage to The Twilight
Zone, The War Of The Worlds (the radio station name is WOTW), and others.</p>
<p>Serena found it slow, especially at the beginning. I can understand that: the
first twenty minutes are a long walk-and-talk between the two protagonists, but
oh boy, look the world-building (and camera work) happening right there!</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Books I read in 2023</title>
      <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/books-i-read-in-2023/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 29 Dec 2023 15:51:02 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nicolaiarocci.com/books-i-read-in-2023/</guid>
      <description>I read 24 books for a total of 7070 pages in 2023. That&amp;rsquo;s seven more books than last year, which is quite an outstanding result considering the seemingly unstoppable decline in book reading I have suffered in recent years. Most have been fiction books, and that&amp;rsquo;s something new and influential with the final result, as I tend to read non-fiction more slowly. The bad news is that I did not review most of the books I read this year, and that sucks.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I read 24 books for a total of 7070 pages in 2023. That&rsquo;s seven more books than
last year, which is quite an outstanding result considering the seemingly
unstoppable decline in book reading <a href="/my-favorite-books-of-2022/">I have suffered in recent
years</a>. Most have been fiction books, and that&rsquo;s
something new and influential with the final result, as I tend to read
non-fiction more slowly. The bad news is that I did not review most of the books
I read this year, and that sucks. The last review was in August, a <a href="/a-few-late-book-reviews/">catch-up
review of several books</a> clearly showing I was in
trouble.</p>
<p>Inspired by <a href="https://adactio.com/journal/20740">Adactio</a>, I am considering a
different, less demanding approach.  Instead of one review for every book, I may
post one general review at the end of the year. I plan to start the article with
the first book of the year, keep it as a draft, update it with every new book I
read, and publish it by the end of the year. Individual notes should be short,
one or two paragraphs at most, maybe with a rating. This solution would reduce
the number of book-related posts, also benefitting, I suspect, most of my
readers. Also, this allows me to leverage a couple of new features on my
website: the table of contents and active title links (which I can then use in
my <a href="/books-i-have-read/">library</a> page).</p>
<p>I might as well adopt Adactio&rsquo;s scoring system:</p>
<ul>
<li>One star means a book is meh.</li>
<li>Two stars mean a book is perfectly fine.</li>
<li>Three stars mean a book is good—consider it recommended.</li>
<li>Four stars mean a book is exceptional.</li>
<li>Five stars is pretty much unheard of.</li>
</ul>
<p>Most ratings would fall in the two- to three-star range.</p>
<p>I&rsquo;m starting this year. When a previously posted, more detailed review is
available, I&rsquo;ll link it, and only repost the first paragrafe in this page.</p>
<h3 id="the-sorrows-of-young-werther-by-jw-von-goethe">The sorrows of young Werther, by J.W. von Goethe</h3>
<p><em>(I dolori del giovane Werther, Einaudi, traduzione di E. Ganni)</em></p>
<p>★★★☆☆</p>
<p><em>&ldquo;The first Dandy in European literature, Werther ignited the sensibilities of an
entire generation, that of the Sturm und Drang, which made him a timeless hero
of the rebellious culture that prefers the intensity of feeling to the aridity
of reason&rdquo;.</em> To modern eyes, the reading is sometimes disturbing, preconfiguring
Werther as the prototype of today&rsquo;s stalker (he goes so far as to consider the
suppression of the now unattainable love). Still, one has to refrain from
judging a text out of the context and period in which it was written. The
writing is superb, fluent, and accessible for a text published in 1774—Enrico
Ganni&rsquo;s Italian translation is excellent.</p>
<h3 id="happiness-as-such-by-natalia-ginzburg">Happiness, as such by Natalia Ginzburg</h3>
<p><em>(Caro Michele, Einaudi)</em></p>
<p>★★★☆☆</p>
<p>A mother already advanced in years but still young, and a son physically distant
and even more distant in ideas, needs, affections, and sorrows. A son for whom
the mother resents but from whom she cannot detach herself, and the last,
unbreakable umbilical cord is made of letters alone. It is a novel of many
scattered characters, divided by incommunicability and destined for loneliness.
I was struck by the precise description of society and culture in the early
1970s (the novel was published in 1973) and the non-trivial (for the time) theme
of homosexuality, treated effectively.</p>
<h3 id="the-ancient-hours-by-michael-bible">The ancient hours, by Michael Bible</h3>
<p><em>(L&rsquo;ultima cosa bella sulla faccia delle terra, Adelphi)</em></p>
<p>★★★★☆</p>
<p>A few troubled characters move through the area south of the Appalachians, one
of America&rsquo;s poorest and most religious (evangelical) areas. Though tormented,
the characters refuse to admit their defeats. They seek redemption in love in
memory and drugs, trying to bridge frailties and family conflicts, coming to
terms with God&rsquo;s cumbersome presence, and accompanied by the feeling that they
are moving forward but can only look backward. There is much poetry and
poignancy in this beautiful and passionate tale. Micheal Bible is a talented
writer who knows the places, culture and society he narrates, and it shows.</p>
<h3 id="milano-calibro-9-by-giorgio-scerbanenco">Milano calibro 9, by Giorgio Scerbanenco</h3>
<p><em>(La nave di Teseo)</em></p>
<p>★★☆☆☆</p>
<p>A collection of twenty-two noir tales about the ruthless Milan of the 1960s: the
sacred triad of crime, sex, money, and power is present on every page. The
characters in these tales are driven by aching and losing loves, vices and
addictions, or fatal sexual attractions. The stories were originally published
in weekly magazines that were then in vogue, first and foremost Novella 2000, of
which Scerbanenco was a longtime editor. At the time, Novella 2000 was not the
tabloid magazine we know today but a popular literature magazine (hence the
name). Only some of the stories are captivating; some are not well written, and
noir is not a genre that interests me, but I got this book to understand the
literary Milan of those times better, and I got what I wanted.</p>
<h3 id="ferrovie-del-messico-by-gian-marco-griffi">Ferrovie del messico, by Gian Marco Griffi</h3>
<p><em>(Laurana)</em></p>
<p>★★★★☆</p>
<p>If you are looking for adventure, you will find plenty and taste great
literature with this novel. There are so many characters to follow between Asti,
Italian Social Republic, February 1944 and then up and down the railroads of
Mexico between the 1920s and 1930s, all rich and exciting, never flat or
predictable, masterfully orchestrated by an author who manages to keep the
events narrated in perfect balance between comedy and tragedy, never dull
despite the length (824 pages). Gian Marco Griffi is the best modern Italian author I
discovered this year.</p>
<h3 id="adhd-workbook-for-adults-by-tara-wilson">ADHD workbook for adults, by Tara Wilson</h3>
<p><em>(ADHD negli adulti, independently published)</em></p>
<p>★★☆☆☆</p>
<p>A relative of mine was recently diagnosed with ADHD and this short introductory
book allowed me to learn more about it. I didn&rsquo;t find it particularly
enlightening (much of what it contains can be found online), nor is the author
particularly titled to talk about it (she is a professional coach), but perhaps
because of this the content remains simple, and serve its purpose.</p>
<h3 id="high-by-erica-fatland">High, by Erica Fatland</h3>
<p><em>(La vita in alto. Una stagione sull&rsquo;Himalaya, Marisilio)</em></p>
<p>★★★☆☆</p>
<p>Himalayan fiction has accustomed us to stories of climbers tackling Everest and
travelers seeking spiritual experiences in Buddhist monasteries. But what do we
know about the people living in that region? Erica Flatland tells of the
peoples, cultures, and societies that have inhabited the high areas in the
Himalayas since time immemorial, and to do so, she takes a long, slow journey
through these remote areas, encountering characters and places full of stories
to discover. High is an excellent reportage that I thoroughly enjoyed.</p>
<h3 id="codice-jury-by-jury-chechi">Codice Jury, by Jury Chechi</h3>
<p><em>(Longanesi)</em></p>
<p>★★☆☆☆</p>
<p>Jury Chechi won the Olympic title in the rings at Atlanta in 1996 and was third
at Athens in 2004. Chechi&rsquo;s bronze resulted from his attempted comeback into the
sport at 35, well above the average age of a male gymnast. Even at 54 (his
current age), he&rsquo;s astoundingly in shape. He&rsquo;s one of my idols. The news that he
authored a book on calisthenics primarily dedicated to older adults couldn&rsquo;t be
ignored by me. I recommend this work if you&rsquo;re starting and looking for
guidance, motivation, and solid routines, not so much for the expert.</p>
<h3 id="the-passenger-by-cormac-mccarthy">The Passenger, by Cormac McCarthy</h3>
<p><em>(Einaudi)</em></p>
<p>★★★★☆</p>
<p>In the middle of a cold night in 1980, Bobby Western dons his wetsuit and dives
into the black depths of Mississippi Bay. There, he catches sight of the outline
of a plane with nine bodies in the cabin, their eyes empty and their arms
outstretched in an icy embrace. What happened to the phantom&rsquo;s tenth passenger?
It sounds like a thriller and is also that, but also much, much more. The
author&rsquo;s classic themes are all present, only disguised in a story that is only
seemingly and partially different. The Passenger requires commitment and
concentration: there are many closed discussions, varied and more or less
recurring characters, numerous flashbacks and juxtapositions, but it is amply
worth it.</p>
<p>McCarthy&rsquo;s final diarchy consists of this work and its natural continuation,
Stella Maris, centered on Bobby&rsquo;s schizophrenic sister, Alice. Together, the two
volumes make a modern masterpiece.</p>
<h3 id="stella-maris-by-cormac-mccarthy">Stella Maris, by Cormac McCarthy</h3>
<p><em>(Einaudi)</em></p>
<p>★★★★☆</p>
<p>In The Passenger, we hear the story of Bobby Western, salvage diver, physics
expert, former race car driver, and grieving brother who is still in love with
his beautiful sister who killed herself. This very sister is the protagonist of
Stella Maris, the book&rsquo;s title being the name of the psychiatric facility she
admitted herself to. The text is set in 1972, and here (spoiler alert), we
discover that ten years before The Passenger events, Bobby was in a coma after a
car accident and brain dead. The doctors wanted Alice to agree to stop
life-support. Mind-blowing. The whole text comprises seven sessions with her
therapist, Dr. Cohen, rendered in pure dialogue and, therefore, more linear than
The Passenger. Stella Maris can be read without its companion, but I would
not advice doing that.</p>
<h3 id="born-to-run-2-by-chris-mcdougall-and-eric-orton">Born to run 2, by Chris McDougall and Eric Orton</h3>
<p>★★☆☆☆</p>
<p>I&rsquo;ve been back to running after a long hiatus, and this book helped me get back
on track with the right, lightly-hearted approach. The fundamentals are solid
(the barefoot-like technique is the way), the 90-day training plan is a good
platform, the nutrition hints are remarkable, and I appreciated the
injury-treatment segments. There&rsquo;s too much chitchat for my liking, though, with
many stories, anecdotes, and non-technical, gospel-like content. Some chapters
are unattractive to the experienced runner (running with dogs, the music while
running debate, and training with scooters?).  This book targets the newcomer
and the veteran runner switching to the barefoot technique. The first book in
the series, Born to Run, was the commercial hit introducing barefoot running to
the masses. This one is trying to be both a sequel and something different that
can live independently. Meeting all these goals was a complicated bet.</p>
<h3 id="blinds-man-bluff-by-susan-sontag">Blind’s man bluff, by Susan Sontag</h3>
<p><em>(Immersione rapida, Net)</em></p>
<p>★★★☆☆</p>
<p>This book made a lot of noise when it came out in 1998. Back then, most of the
events narrated were unknown to the general public. The cold-war stories
contained within are as enthralling as spy, maritime and Cold War stories can
get.  This book is still relevant today, as it does an excellent job of
recounting the Cold War craziness and revealing how close humanity got to
shooting his own feet, and we never knew.</p>
<h3 id="wuthering-heights-by-emily-bronte">Wuthering Heights, by Emily Bronte</h3>
<p><em>(Cime Tempestose, BUR)</em></p>
<p>★★★★☆</p>
<p>What a weird work of fiction. I was expecting the usual romantic story between
noble landowners in late 19th-century England, full of heartbreak and probably
opposed by their respective families, the difficulties of rural life, or both.
I found myself immersed in a much darker, twisted and sick version of the story,
in which every single character is flawed, and there is not a single light of
hope. A few weeks passed since I read it, and I&rsquo;m still trying to come to terms
with it. This book was well ahead of its time (1847) and still challenges the
readers today. As I read, I could not help but think, &ldquo;What kind of sick author
would write a thing like this?&rdquo; Emily Brontë&rsquo;s life was not easy, and many
experiences of her and her family percolated in the novel in one way or another.
I found an [excellent review][1] on Goodreads, and I&rsquo;m using it as a guideline
for pondering this novel. For as an oddball as it is, this book is a must-read.</p>
<h3 id="lumanità-è-un-tirocinio-by-domenico-starnone">L&rsquo;umanità è un tirocinio, by Domenico Starnone</h3>
<p><em>(Einaudi)</em></p>
<p>★★☆☆☆</p>
<p>Getting to know my beloved Starnone better through the literary fascinations
that turned him on, the sharp reflections on authors and texts, and his very
personal &ldquo;shattering&rdquo; of articles representing a lifetime&rsquo;s thoughts on writing
and writing was terrific. <em>&ldquo;The texts collected here owe what little good they
possibly hold to the forty-five years of passionate, enjoyable daily
conversation with Anita; time has passed too quickly.&rdquo;</em> It was not an easy read,
mainly because most of the mentioned texts I had never read before, but worth
it. My to-read list has surely grown much longer now.</p>
<h3 id="the-overstory-by-richard-powers">The overstory, by Richard Powers</h3>
<p><em>(Il sussurro del mondo, La nave di Teseo)</em></p>
<p>★☆☆☆☆</p>
<p>I found it overly dull and did not finish it. Strange, because it sounds like a book I&rsquo;d love. Maybe I&rsquo;ll try again in a
few years.</p>
<h3 id="la-mossa-del-matto-by-alessandro-barbaglia">La mossa del matto, by Alessandro Barbaglia</h3>
<p><em>(Mondadori)</em></p>
<p>★★★☆☆</p>
<p>Alessandro Barbaglia’s La mossa del matto (The fool’s move) tries to be three
things in one: the life story of chess champion Bobby Fischer, a reconciliation
dialogue between author and father, who died too soon, as well the tracing of a
daring parallel between Fischer’s relationship with Russian champion Boris
Spasskij and that of Achilles and Ulysses of Homeric memory. In our neck of the
woods, we say that too much is crippling, and this work runs the risk. More
<a href="/book-review-la-mossa-del-matto-the-fools-move/">here</a>.</p>
<h3 id="disasters-by-daniil-charms">Disasters, by Daniil Charms</h3>
<p><em>(Disastri, UTET)</em></p>
<p>★★★☆☆</p>
<p>Daniil Charms was considered a children’s author and could not stand children
all his life. While his whimsical fairy tales populated illustrated books and
magazines, giving him something to live on in the silence of his room, he also
feverishly wrote tales for adults, equally imaginative but inhabited by an
excruciating melancholy, as in fairy tales went wrong. More <a href="/book-review-disastri/">here</a>.</p>
<h3 id="land-and-sea-by-carl-schmitt">Land and sea, by Carl Schmitt</h3>
<p><em>(Terra e mare, Adelphi)</em></p>
<p>★★☆☆☆</p>
<p>Land and Sea is an essay in short story form written in 1942 by Carl Schmitt.
Subtitled “A consideration of world history told to my daughter Anna,” this
essay recounts and summarizes the geo-historical-legal evolution of our planet
since the discovery of the New World. The originality of the work lies in the
author’s identification of the Earth-Sea dichotomy as the driving force of human
history. More <a href="/book-review-land-and-sea/">here</a>.</p>
<h3 id="medieval-callings-by-jacques-le-goff">Medieval callings, by Jacques Le Goff</h3>
<p><em>(L&rsquo;uomo medievale, Laterza)</em></p>
<p>★★★☆☆</p>
<p>Medieval Callings comprises eleven essays by internationally renowned medieval
historians. Somewhat deceptively, only Jacques Le Goff’s prestigious name
appears on the front page, as he authored the introductive essay and handpicked
and curated the collection. Each piece presents a nuanced profile of a
significant social or professional Middle Ages group. Warrior knights, monks,
high churchmen, criminals, lepers, shepherds, artists, and prostitutes, all
prominent figures of medieval society, are depicted here with great detail. More
<a href="/book-review-medieval-callings/">here</a>.</p>
<h3 id="being-wolf-by-kerstin-ekman">Being wolf, by Kerstin Ekman</h3>
<p><em>(Essere lupo, Iperborea)</em></p>
<p>★★★☆☆</p>
<p>I saw a wolf: that’s the phrase Ulf, a hunter and former forestry inspector now in his seventies, has been brooding, unable to confess to anyone since he spotted a majestic specimen at dawn on the first day of the year. Something clicks inside him, and Ulf, one of the most respected men in the village in deep Sweden where he lives, feels an increasingly solid and intimate connection with the creature. They both are hunters and loners, but why does he feel like an intruder? More <a href="/book-review-essere-lupo-being-wolf/">here</a>.</p>
<h3 id="no-sleep-till-shengal-by-zerocalcare">No sleep till Shengal, by Zerocalcare</h3>
<p><em>(Bao)</em></p>
<p>★★☆☆☆</p>
<p>Zerocalcare is an Italian cartoonist whose strips, especially in the form of
illustrated books, have surged to an iconic level in the last decade. His
drawing is excellent, but it is with his writing that, I think, he conquered
fame. His stories are fun to read and yet profound and vibrant, all at the same
time. Also, he often touches on themes nobody else covers, at least not in the
comics world. It was the case with Kobane Calling: Greetings from Northern
Syria, his graphic reportage from Syrian Kurdistan and the Syria-Turkey border.
The author visited the area with other volunteers to support the Kurdish
resistance. I think Kobane Calling did a lot in raising awareness of the Kurdish
situation, at least here in Italy (an English edition was published too.) More
<a href="/book-review-no-sleep-till-shengal/">here</a>.</p>
<h3 id="red-mars-by-kim-stanley-robinson">Red Mars, by Kim Stanley Robinson</h3>
<p><em>(Il rosso di marte, Fanucci)</em></p>
<p>★★☆☆☆</p>
<p>Regarding space-related topics and scientific research, Casey Handmer’s blog is
one of my references. So when Casey started his Mars Trilogy Technical
Commentary and I learned about Kim Stanley Robinson’s masterpiece, I was
instantly intrigued. In Casey’s opinion, KSR’s Mars Trilogy is “one of the
finest works of literature ever composed.” It took a couple of weeks of futile
resistance before I gave in and ordered the first book in the series, Red Mars,
a 420 pages tome that attempts to depict a scientifically credible human
colonization of Mars. More <a href="/book-review-red-mars/">here</a>.</p>
<h3 id="sanguina-ancora-by-paolo-nori">Sanguina ancora, by Paolo Nori</h3>
<p><em>(Mondadori)</em></p>
<p>★★★☆☆</p>
<p>Sanguina Ancora (Still Bleeding) is not a biography but a passionate and
informative tribute to Dostoevsky. The nonlinear, not literary style works and
the continuous back and forth between Dostoevsky’s epic and the author’s own
experiences as a scholar and Russian literature enthusiast is probably a good
idea as it helps stress the actualness of Dostoevsky’s opus. More
<a href="/book-review-sanguina-ancora-still-bleeding/">here</a>.</p>
<h3 id="uomini-boschi-e-api-by-mario-rigoni-stern">Uomini, boschi e api, by Mario Rigoni Stern</h3>
<p><em>(Einaudi)</em></p>
<p>★★☆☆☆</p>
<p>&ldquo;I wish everyone could listen to the song of the partridges as the sun rises,
see the deer on pastures in spring, the larch trees reddened by autumn on the
edges of rocks, the darting of fish among the clear waters of streams, and the
bees gathering nectar from the flowering cherry trees. In these stories, I write
about village places. These natural environments are still livable, about the
beautiful social insects that are bees, but also about ancient jobs that are
slowly and inexorably disappearing.&rdquo; More
<a href="/book-review-uomini-boschi-e-api/">here</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>A few late book reviews</title>
      <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/a-few-late-book-reviews/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 26 Aug 2023 07:05:25 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nicolaiarocci.com/a-few-late-book-reviews/</guid>
      <description>I&amp;rsquo;ve been reading a few books throughout the summer and needed to be more active in reviewing them here. Rather than writing five individual posts in a row (too lazy for that), I will catch up with this single post.
Born to Run 2 I&amp;rsquo;ve been back to running after a long hiatus, and this book helped me get back on track with the right, lightly-hearted approach. The fundamentals are solid (the barefoot-like technique is the way), the 90-day training plan is a good platform, the nutrition hints are remarkable, and I appreciated the injury-treatment segments.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I&rsquo;ve been reading a few books throughout the summer and needed to be more active in reviewing them here. Rather than
writing five individual posts in a row (too lazy for that), I will catch up with this single post.</p>
<h2 id="born-to-run-2">Born to Run 2</h2>
<p>I&rsquo;ve been back to running after a long hiatus, and this book helped me get back on track with the right, lightly-hearted
approach. The fundamentals are solid (the barefoot-like technique is the way), the 90-day training plan is a good
platform, the nutrition hints are remarkable, and I appreciated the injury-treatment segments. There&rsquo;s too much chitchat
for my liking, though, with many stories, anecdotes, and non-technical, gospel-like content. Some chapters are
unattractive to the experienced runner (running with dogs, the music while running debate, and training with scooters?).
This book targets the newcomer and the veteran runner switching to the barefoot technique. The first book in the series,
Born to Run, was the commercial hit introducing barefoot running to the masses. This one is trying to be both a sequel
and something different that can live independently. Meeting all these goals was a complicated bet. <em>Authors: Chris
McDougall, Eric Orton.</em></p>
<h2 id="immersione-rapida-blinds-man-bluff">Immersione rapida (Blind&rsquo;s Man Bluff)</h2>
<blockquote>
<p>For decades, American submarines have roamed the depths in a dangerous battle for information and advantage in
missions known only to a select few. Now, after six years of research, those missions are told in Blind Man&rsquo;s Bluff, a
magnificent achievement in investigative reporting.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>This book made a lot of noise when it came out in 1998. Back then, most of the events narrated were unknown to the
general public. The cold-war stories contained within are as enthralling as spy, maritime and Cold War stories can get.
This book is still relevant today, as it does an excellent job of recounting the Cold War craziness and revealing how
close humanity got to shooting his own feet, and we never knew. <em>Authors: Sherry Sontag, Christopher Drew, Annette L.
Drew</em>.</p>
<h2 id="cime-tempestose-wuthering-heights">Cime tempestose (Wuthering Heights)</h2>
<p>What a weird work of fiction. I was expecting the usual romantic story between noble landowners in late 19th-century
England, full of heartbreak and probably opposed by their respective families, the difficulties of rural life, or both.
I found myself immersed in a much darker, twisted and sick version of the story, in which every single character is
flawed, and there is not a single light of hope. A few weeks passed since I read it, and I&rsquo;m still trying to come to
terms with it. This book was well ahead of its time (1847) and still challenges the readers today. As I read, I could
not help but think, &ldquo;What kind of sick author would write a thing like this?&rdquo; Emily Brontë&rsquo;s life was not easy, and many
experiences of her and her family percolated in the novel in one way or another. I found an <a href="https://www.goodreads.com/review/show/4840111965">excellent review</a> on
Goodreads, and I&rsquo;m using it as a guideline for pondering this novel. For as an oddball as it is, this book is a
must-read. <em>Author: Emily Brontë.</em></p>
<h2 id="lumanità-è-un-tirocinio-life-is-an-apprenticeship">L&rsquo;umanità è un tirocinio (Life is an apprenticeship)</h2>
<p>Getting to know my beloved Starnone better through the literary fascinations that turned him on, the sharp reflections
on authors and texts, and his very personal &ldquo;shattering&rdquo; of articles representing a lifetime&rsquo;s thoughts on writing and
writing was terrific. <em>&ldquo;The texts collected here owe what little good they possibly hold to the forty-five years of
passionate, enjoyable daily conversation with Anita; time has passed too quickly.&rdquo;</em> It was not an easy read, mainly
because most of the mentioned texts I had never read before, but worth it. My to-read list has surely grown much longer
now. <em>Author: Domenico Starnone</em>.</p>
<h2 id="il-sussurro-del-mondo-the-overstory">Il sussurro del mondo (The Overstory)</h2>
<blockquote>
<p>The Overstory is a sweeping, impassioned work of activism and resistance that is also a stunning evocation of - and
paean to - the natural world. From the roots to the crown and back to the seeds, Richard Powers&rsquo;s twelfth novel
unfolds in concentric rings of interlocking fables that range from antebellum New York to the late twentieth-century
Timber Wars of the Pacific Northwest and beyond. There is a world alongside ours—vast, slow, interconnected,
resourceful, magnificently inventive, and almost invisible to us. This is the story of a handful of people who learn
how to see that world and who are drawn up into its unfolding catastrophe.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I found it overly dull and did not finish it. Strange, because it sounds like a book I&rsquo;d love. Maybe I&rsquo;ll try again in a
few years. <em>Author: Richard Powers.</em></p>
<p><em>Subscribe to the <a href="https://nicolaiarocci.substack.com">newsletter</a>, the <a href="https://nicolaiarocci.com/index.xml">RSS feed</a>, or <a href="https://fosstodon.org/@nicola">follow me on Mastodon</a></em></p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Book Review: La Mossa del Matto (The Fool&#39;s Move)</title>
      <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/book-review-la-mossa-del-matto-the-fools-move/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 19 May 2023 07:05:25 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nicolaiarocci.com/book-review-la-mossa-del-matto-the-fools-move/</guid>
      <description>Alessandro Barbaglia&amp;rsquo;s La mossa del matto (The fool&amp;rsquo;s move) tries to be three things in one: the life story of chess champion Bobby Fischer, a reconciliation dialogue between author and father, who died too soon, as well the tracing of a daring parallel between Fischer&amp;rsquo;s relationship with Russian champion Boris Spasskij and that of Achilles and Ulysses of Homeric memory. In our neck of the woods, we say that too much is crippling, and this work runs the risk.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Alessandro Barbaglia&rsquo;s <em>La mossa del matto (The fool&rsquo;s move)</em> tries to be three things in one: the life story of chess
champion Bobby Fischer, a reconciliation dialogue between author and father, who died too soon, as well the tracing of a
daring parallel between Fischer&rsquo;s relationship with Russian champion Boris Spasskij and that of Achilles and Ulysses of
Homeric memory. In our neck of the woods, we say that too much is crippling, and this work runs the risk.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" src="/images/book-cover-la-mossa-del-matto.jpg#right" alt="Book cover: La mossa del matto"  />

I appreciated the accurate and skillfully woven account of Bobby Fischer&rsquo;s incredibly successful yet troubled
life. The intersection between Fischer&rsquo;s biography and actual episodes of the author&rsquo;s and his dad&rsquo;s lives works well,
too. The attempt to bind the Fischer/Spasskij relationship to that of Achilles and Ulysses, albeit intriguing and often
fitting, seems unnecessary, always risking breaking the fragile balance between the three narratives. Somehow Barbaglia
manages to keep it all together.</p>
<p>Before getting into this book, I knew very little about Bobby Fischer. He&rsquo;s known as the American genius who beat the
unbeatable Russians at chess, but there&rsquo;s much more to him than that, and this book does a great job at telling.</p>
<p><em>Subscribe to the <a href="https://nicolaiarocci.substack.com">newsletter</a>, the <a href="https://nicolaiarocci.com/index.xml">RSS feed</a>, or <a href="https://fosstodon.org/@nicola">follow me on Mastodon</a></em></p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Book Review: Disastri (Disasters)</title>
      <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/book-review-disastri/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 14 May 2023 07:05:25 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nicolaiarocci.com/book-review-disastri/</guid>
      <description>Daniil Charms was considered a children&amp;rsquo;s author and could not stand children all his life. While his whimsical fairy tales populated illustrated books and magazines, giving him something to live on in the silence of his room, he also feverishly wrote tales for adults, equally imaginative but inhabited by an excruciating melancholy, as in fairy tales went wrong.
At the dawn of the USSR, this desperate fantasy of his was tolerable only if it was confined where it was least dangerous, in children&amp;rsquo;s literature.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Daniil Charms was considered a children&rsquo;s author and could not stand children all his life. While his whimsical fairy
tales populated illustrated books and magazines, giving him something to live on in the silence of his room, he also
feverishly wrote tales for adults, equally imaginative but inhabited by an excruciating melancholy, as in fairy tales went
wrong.</p>
<p>At the dawn of the USSR, this desperate fantasy of his was tolerable only if it was confined where it was least
dangerous, in children&rsquo;s literature. Back then, adults were the children to be motivated and consoled with uplifting
novels aimed at glorifying the rise of the proletariat, a literature Charms refused to adhere to.</p>
<p>Thus, while socialist realism raged outside, Daniil Charms uncovered impossible worlds in the folds of reality. Gossipy
older women tipping over the window, curious people breaking their watches trying to seize the moment, men buried alive
rejoicing at the beautiful funeral, birds equipped with teeth (or maybe not), deadly challenges at cucumber blows,
caterpillars with their snouts covered in dust.</p>
<p>This book is an arsenal of incredible stories circling for a long time, only clandestinely in <em>samizdats</em>, illegal books
recopied by hand or typed in secret. Credit goes to Paolo Nori, who revealed to the Italian readers the greatness of
this pioneer of the literature of the absurd. Nori selects and assembles hundreds of narrative fragments, alternating
with excerpts from the diaries, in which Charms lays bare his tragic everyday life. The fresco of tightrope walking
characters and unbelievable animals is thus interwoven with the minute account of a sour life lived on the fringes of
literary society until the gloomy eye of the Party rests on this wacky dissident.</p>
<p>The Soviet Union tried multiple times to erase Charms by letting him die in an asylum. They finally succeeded on
February 2, 1942, when famine killed him in the psychiatric clinic in which he was confined.</p>
<p>Most of these things were written when socialist realism triumphed around, and their author knew very well that he could
never publish them in his lifetime. Yet, by reading his diaries, all this &ldquo;nonsense,&rdquo; as Charmes defined his crazy
writing assembly, clearly emerges as the most crucial thing in his life.</p>
<p>I found the book cover excellent and perfectly fit, with this dandy figure seemingly strolling amongst imposing orthodox
buildings. According to Wikipedia, Charms loved to appear dressed like an English dandy and with a calabash pipe.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" src="/images/disastri-book-cover.jpg" alt="Disastri book cover"  />
</p>
<p><em>Subscribe to the <a href="https://nicolaiarocci.substack.com">newsletter</a>, the <a href="https://nicolaiarocci.com/index.xml">RSS feed</a>, or <a href="https://fosstodon.org/@nicola">follow me on Mastodon</a></em></p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Book Review: Land and Sea</title>
      <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/book-review-land-and-sea/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 May 2023 07:05:25 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nicolaiarocci.com/book-review-land-and-sea/</guid>
      <description>Land and Sea is an essay in short story form written in 1942 by Carl Schmitt. Subtitled &amp;ldquo;A consideration of world history told to my daughter Anna,&amp;rdquo; this essay recounts and summarizes the geo-historical-legal evolution of our planet since the discovery of the New World. The originality of the work lies in the author&amp;rsquo;s identification of the Earth-Sea dichotomy as the driving force of human history.
I went into this book knowing very little about the author, Carl Schmitt, and the contents.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Land and Sea is an essay in short story form written in 1942 by Carl Schmitt. Subtitled &ldquo;A consideration of world
history told to my daughter Anna,&rdquo; this essay recounts and summarizes the geo-historical-legal evolution of our planet
since the discovery of the New World. The originality of the work lies in the author&rsquo;s identification of the Earth-Sea
dichotomy as the driving force of human history.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" src="/images/terra-e-mare-book-cover.jpeg#center" alt="Land and Sea book cover"  />

I went into this book knowing very little about the author, Carl Schmitt, and the contents. From the first pages, I
considered it a bizarre work, wondering whether a solid basis existed behind some of the assumptions and events
narrated. Quoting the back cover of my Italian edition (Adelphi):</p>
<blockquote>
<p>In a dazzling interweaving of historical interpretation and political theory, mythography and theology, philosophy and
esotericism, the great jurist thus enters a fascinating territory on the borderline between speculation and
imagination, where the search for the &ldquo;elemental&rdquo; goes &ldquo;to the threshold of eschatology.&rdquo; With a few strokes, Schmitt
traces millennia of history, unraveling its invisible plot, until he arrives at the decisive event: that &ldquo;planetary
spatial revolution&rdquo; from which the nomos of modern Europe was born. To then look beyond - and foreshadow, with
prophecy, the scenarios of the future world where we will be able to recognize our present.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Land and Sea is an essay written in 1942 by a then-eminent and internationally acclaimed jurist, who convincingly joined
the german nazi party in 1933. Historical events in the text are inevitably narrated from an opinionated (and sometimes
distorted) point of view. This bizarre work left me unconvinced. I don&rsquo;t regret reading it, though.</p>
<p><em>Subscribe to the <a href="https://nicolaiarocci.substack.com">newsletter</a>, the <a href="https://nicolaiarocci.com/index.xml">RSS feed</a>, or <a href="https://fosstodon.org/@nicola">follow me on Mastodon</a></em></p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Book Review: Medieval Callings</title>
      <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/book-review-medieval-callings/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 29 Apr 2023 06:05:25 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nicolaiarocci.com/book-review-medieval-callings/</guid>
      <description>Medieval Callings comprises eleven essays by internationally renowned medieval historians. Somewhat deceptively, only Jacques Le Goff&amp;rsquo;s prestigious name appears on the front page, as he authored the introductive essay and handpicked and curated the collection. Each piece presents a nuanced profile of a significant social or professional Middle Ages group. Warrior knights, monks, high churchmen, criminals, lepers, shepherds, artists, and prostitutes, all prominent figures of medieval society, are depicted here with great detail.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><em>Medieval Callings</em> comprises eleven essays by internationally renowned medieval historians. Somewhat deceptively, only
Jacques Le Goff&rsquo;s prestigious name appears on the front page, as he authored the introductive essay and handpicked and
curated the collection. Each piece presents a nuanced profile of a significant social or professional Middle Ages group.
Warrior knights, monks, high churchmen, criminals, lepers, shepherds, artists, and prostitutes, all prominent figures of
medieval society, are depicted here with great detail.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" src="/images/uomo-medievale-book-cover.jpg#right" alt="Medieval Callings, Italin edition&amp;rsquo;s book cover"  />

The style varies according to the piece (and its author); some will inevitably be more fluent than others. Fundamental
is the introductory essay by Le Goff himself, which provides a useful general overview of the work and also clarifies
its stylistic choices. The Monk essay was crucial to me, as it surfaced abbeys and monasteries&rsquo; relevance and incredible
influence on medieval society.</p>
<p><em>Medieval Callings&rsquo;</em> innovative approach offers a valuable and intriguing perspective on the complex social dynamics of
feudal Europe. The work shows signs of age, having passed more than 30 years since its publication. There are probably
newer, modern studies that improve on these texts, but it still serves as a fundamental resource for uneducated readers
such as myself.</p>
<p><em>Subscribe to the <a href="https://nicolaiarocci.substack.com">newsletter</a>, the <a href="https://nicolaiarocci.com/index.xml">RSS feed</a>, or <a href="https://fosstodon.org/@nicola">follow me on Mastodon</a></em></p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Book Review: Essere Lupo (Being Wolf)</title>
      <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/book-review-essere-lupo-being-wolf/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Apr 2023 07:05:25 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nicolaiarocci.com/book-review-essere-lupo-being-wolf/</guid>
      <description>I saw a wolf: that&amp;rsquo;s the phrase Ulf, a hunter and former forestry inspector now in his seventies, has been brooding, unable to confess to anyone since he spotted a majestic specimen at dawn on the first day of the year. Something clicks inside him, and Ulf, one of the most respected men in the village in deep Sweden where he lives, feels an increasingly solid and intimate connection with the creature.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I saw a wolf: that&rsquo;s the phrase Ulf, a hunter and former forestry inspector now in his seventies, has been brooding,
unable to confess to anyone since he spotted a majestic specimen at dawn on the first day of the year. Something clicks
inside him, and Ulf, one of the most respected men in the village in deep Sweden where he lives, feels an increasingly
solid and intimate connection with the creature. They both are hunters and loners, but why does he feel like an
intruder? Even the memory of his early experiences in the woods with his father, once a source of joy, changes in
flavor, just as pride in his hunting diaries fades, as they now only appear as a cold kill list. And his wife&rsquo;s dry and
practical empathy, their comfortable daily routine of love and habits, the faithful companionship of his dog Zenta and
the many chases made with her in the snow are not enough: Ulf feels as lost among his stuffed trophies as among the
traditions and customs of a community whose violence he now perceives. A society that, he will discover to his cost, is
quick at oppressing when one is not aligned with its most deeply rooted values.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" src="/images/being-wolf.jpeg#right" alt="Being Wolf"  />

The tension of the stakeouts, the contemplation of the woods in the long waits, the excitement of a trail to follow, the
scents and sounds of a wilderness where everyone is alone in front of himself: <em>Being Wolf</em> tells of a predator in
harmony with his world and of the human who, inspired by it,  questions and rethinks his place in nature. I found two
other themes well addressed: the hate and malice that often lurk beneath the surface of small, seemingly idyllic
communities and the comfort and serenity that a relationship of mutual trust, respect and love offers to aged partners
who stubbornly insist on loving and respect each other despite adversity, misunderstanding and betrayal.</p>
<p>This novel has yet to see an English edition, so as for the English title, I made it up from Essere Lupo of the Italian
edition. These quick notes offer me a chance to express my gratitude to Iperborea for their incredible work in
publishing so many exceptionally translated Northen-Europe works over the years.</p>
<p><em>Subscribe to the <a href="https://nicolaiarocci.substack.com">newsletter</a>, the <a href="https://nicolaiarocci.com/index.xml">RSS feed</a>, or <a href="https://fosstodon.org/@nicola">follow me on Mastodon</a></em></p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Book Review: No Sleep Till Shengal</title>
      <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/book-review-no-sleep-till-shengal/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Mar 2023 07:05:25 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nicolaiarocci.com/book-review-no-sleep-till-shengal/</guid>
      <description>Zerocalcare is an Italian cartoonist whose strips, especially in the form of illustrated books, have surged to an iconic level in the last decade. His drawing is excellent, but it is with his writing that, I think, he conquered fame. His stories are fun to read and yet profound and vibrant, all at the same time. Also, he often touches on themes nobody else covers, at least not in the comics world.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Zerocalcare is an Italian cartoonist whose strips, especially in the form of illustrated books, have surged to an iconic
level in the last decade. His drawing is excellent, but it is with his writing that, I think, he conquered fame. His
stories are fun to read and yet profound and vibrant, all at the same time. Also, he often touches on themes nobody else
covers, at least not in the comics world. It was the case with <em>Kobane Calling: Greetings from Northern Syria</em>, his
graphic reportage from Syrian Kurdistan and the Syria-Turkey border. The author visited the area with other volunteers
to support the Kurdish resistance. I think <em>Kobane Calling</em> did a lot in raising awareness of the Kurdish situation, at
least here in Italy (an English edition was published too.)</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" src="/images/no-sleep-till-shengal.jpg#right" alt="No Sleep Till Shengal"  />

<em>No Sleep Till Shengal</em> recounts the author&rsquo;s return to Iraq, this time to visit the Yazidi community of Shengal and
document their living conditions and struggle as they are threatened by international tensions and protected by Kurdish
militias. <em>No Sleep Till Shengal</em> is a good book. Like his predecessor, it is humorous yet tense and touching. I felt like
something was amiss in this work, though, and I am not exactly sure what. There are a couple of repetitive passages,
perhaps a sign that the author needed to fill in the blanks, having less fresh content at hand. Maybe there&rsquo;s a slight
Deja Vu sensation induced by the previous work; I don&rsquo;t know. <em>No Sleep</em> is a solid second work on an already visited
theme. My affection for Zerocalcare is intact, but I&rsquo;d pick <em>Kobane Calling</em> over <em>No Sleep</em>, especially for a first
reading of this author.</p>
<p><em>Subscribe to the <a href="https://nicolaiarocci.substack.com">newsletter</a>, the <a href="https://nicolaiarocci.com/index.xml">RSS feed</a>, or <a href="https://fosstodon.org/@nicola">follow me on Mastodon</a></em></p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Book Review: Red Mars</title>
      <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/book-review-red-mars/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 02 Mar 2023 07:05:25 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nicolaiarocci.com/book-review-red-mars/</guid>
      <description>Regarding space-related topics and scientific research, Casey Handmer&amp;rsquo;s blog is one of my references. So when Casey started his Mars Trilogy Technical Commentary and I learned about Kim Stanley Robinson&amp;rsquo;s masterpiece, I was instantly intrigued. In Casey&amp;rsquo;s opinion, KSR&amp;rsquo;s Mars Trilogy is &amp;ldquo;one of the finest works of literature ever composed.&amp;rdquo; It took a couple of weeks of futile resistance before I gave in and ordered the first book in the series, Red Mars, a 420 pages tome that attempts to depict a scientifically credible human colonization of Mars1.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Regarding space-related topics and scientific research, <a href="https://caseyhandmer.wordpress.com/">Casey Handmer&rsquo;s blog</a> is one of my references. So when Casey
started his <a href="https://caseyhandmer.wordpress.com/2022/12/13/mars-trilogy-technical-commentary/">Mars Trilogy Technical Commentary</a> and I learned about Kim Stanley Robinson&rsquo;s masterpiece, I was
instantly intrigued. In Casey&rsquo;s opinion, KSR&rsquo;s <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mars_trilogy">Mars Trilogy</a> is &ldquo;one of the finest works of literature ever
composed.&rdquo; It took a couple of weeks of futile resistance before I gave in and ordered the first book in the series, <em>Red
Mars</em>, a 420 pages tome that attempts to depict a scientifically credible human colonization of Mars<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1</a></sup>.</p>
<p>An incredible amount of research went into this book, and it shows. Still, there&rsquo;s never an overabundance of scientific
or nerdy details; quite the contrary, to be honest, and, at least to me, this is one of the book&rsquo;s weaknesses. It&rsquo;s
astonishing how pivotal moments in establishing the first human colony on the Red Planet are glossed over. One hundred
of Earth&rsquo;s best scientists travel to Mars to create the first human settlement. During their richly narrated, almost
two-year-long voyage, we get to know the main characters and learn the ins and outs of the first colonial spaceship.
Yet, when they finally reach the orbit, the reader is left with no clues on the undoubtedly dramatic first landing. The
settlement is already established in the next chapter, with a second one already in place on Phobos&rsquo; surface.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" src="/images/red-mars.jpg#right" alt="Red Mars"  />

Omitting details such as the first landing is undoubtedly an editorial choice. Given the time scope of the narrated
adventure (by the end of the trilogy, it will span a few centuries), it probably makes sense, but I couldn&rsquo;t help but
feel betrayed in some way. The story is more about how humans could establish a society and cultural identity in a
remote colony, how such a community develops over time, and, more importantly, how and why conflicts emerge with the
distant home first and within the settlement itself later on. While reading, I often thought, &lsquo;Hey, this all reminds me
of the  American colonization!&rsquo; and then, &lsquo;I wonder how much percolated into S.A. Corey&rsquo;s <em>The Expanse</em>,&rsquo; terraforming
and Earth-Mars trouble playing prominent roles in both series. In many ways, and I know I am making enemies now, <em>Red
Mars</em> could have served well as a prequel to <em>The Expanse</em><sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">2</a></sup>.</p>
<p>One thing I found confusing at first but later came to appreciate is that the story isn&rsquo;t told from a single person&rsquo;s
perspective. Instead, it sprawls across an extensive cast of characters as it expands over time. Viewpoints shift from
one character to another, and people we thought we understood suddenly seem strange and different when seen through
someone else&rsquo;s eyes. The Mars society is messy, very human, and often petty, with few clear answers and no simple
solutions. In <em>Red Mars</em>, we don&rsquo;t get an optimistic portrayal of the future of human society. Here, <em>Star Trek</em>&rsquo;s
pacified civilization and the idealistic United Federation of Planets are far away to come, if ever.</p>
<p>Overall, I liked this book, probably a lot, but I don&rsquo;t think I will read the next installments in the series, at least
not right away. Maybe in a while, when Mars dust has settled.</p>
<p><em>Subscribe to the [newsletter][nl], the [RSS feed][rss], or [follow me on Mastodon][m]</em></p>
<div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
<hr>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1">
<p><em>Red Mars</em> was first published in 1992. That&rsquo;s something to be considered when evaluating it. Also, some details tenderly show its age, like when characters look at &lsquo;videotapes&rsquo; recorded by remote satellites and surface cameras.&#160;<a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
<li id="fn:2">
<p><em>Disclaimer</em>: I never read <em>The Expanse</em>; I only watched and loved the TV show. So yeah, I don&rsquo;t qualify for an informed opinion on that franchise, let alone compare it with another one.
[rss]: <a href="https://nicolaiarocci.com/index.xml">https://nicolaiarocci.com/index.xml</a>
[m]: <a href="https://fosstodon.org/@nicola">https://fosstodon.org/@nicola</a>
[nl]: <a href="https://nicolaiarocci.substack.com">https://nicolaiarocci.substack.com</a>&#160;<a href="#fnref:2" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
</ol>
</div>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Book Review: Sanguina Ancora (Still Bleeding)</title>
      <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/book-review-sanguina-ancora-still-bleeding/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Feb 2023 07:05:25 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nicolaiarocci.com/book-review-sanguina-ancora-still-bleeding/</guid>
      <description>Sanguina Ancora (Still Bleeding) is not a biography but a passionate and informative tribute to Dostoevsky. The nonlinear, not literary style works and the continuous back and forth between Dostoevsky&amp;rsquo;s epic and the author&amp;rsquo;s own experiences as a scholar and Russian literature enthusiast is probably a good idea as it helps stress the actualness of Dostoevsky&amp;rsquo;s opus.
However, the continuous jumping in and out of the Russian&amp;rsquo;s life, though sympathetic at first, gets tedious over time.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><img loading="lazy" src="/images/book-cover-sanguina-ancora.jpg#right" alt="Book Cover: Sanguina Ancora, by Paolo Nori"  />
</p>
<p><em>Sanguina Ancora</em> (Still Bleeding) is not a biography but a passionate and
informative tribute to Dostoevsky. The nonlinear, not literary style works and
the continuous back and forth between Dostoevsky&rsquo;s epic and the author&rsquo;s own
experiences as a scholar and Russian literature enthusiast is probably a good
idea as it helps stress the actualness of Dostoevsky&rsquo;s opus.</p>
<p>However, the continuous jumping in and out of the Russian&rsquo;s life, though
sympathetic at first, gets tedious over time. While immersed in Dostoevsky&rsquo;s
events, it is not always pleasant to be torn away only to end up in the Parma
lowlands for a few entertaining anecdotes (that these anecdotes tend to
gravitate around the author&rsquo;s other works adds to the discomfort.)</p>
<p>That aside, the book contains precious information on Dostoevsky&rsquo;s life, opus,
Russian literature and society of the nineteenth century. Some random facts
from my reading notes:</p>
<ul>
<li>Dostoevsky&rsquo;s incredible tenacity in the face of early setbacks. The first
translation he worked on was aborted near the end, having discovered that the
novel had already been translated into Russian from French. The second was
published in a Russian magazine but heavily cut and, worse, without
attribution. Yet during all this time, he continued unceasingly, tirelessly,
fervently, day and night work what would become his first novel, <em>Poor Folk</em>
(an immediate hit.)</li>
<li>Writers in late 19th century Russia were astonishingly important. Tolstoy had
founded a kind of religious cult. Young people would gather in the evenings
to read Gogol. In those times, in Russia, writers were real stars.</li>
<li>Russian literature began with Pushkin. Before him, in the eighteenth century,
Russians who wrote did so by imitating the French and knew French better than
Russian, as did all the Russian nobles and educated people of the time.</li>
<li>Bulgakov, in <em>The Master and the Margarita</em><sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1</a></sup>, has one of his characters
say that Dostoevsky is immortal.</li>
<li>As great as the country is, there are no dialects in Russia. Also, Russian is
a spoken language first, and only then a written language (the Russian
alphabet has existed only since the 9th century, with Cyril and Methodius.)</li>
<li>Russians elected a monument to Arina, Pushkin&rsquo;s nanny who told him fairy
tales and made him love the language. She was illiterate.</li>
<li>Dostoevsky is arrested and sentenced to death for reading a letter aloud and
in public. With his comrades in his revolutionary circle, he undergoes a
false execution, an experience he will later give to the protagonist of <em>The
Idiot</em>. The five minutes the protagonist waits for the shooting is a
transcendental experience.</li>
<li>Lieutenant Frank Columbo, the protagonist of the famous TV show from
seventies, is inspired by Porfirij Petrovic, the detective from <em>Crime and
Punishment</em>.</li>
</ul>
<p>I&rsquo;ve got a lot of notes from this book, which is a good sign. Vasily Rizanov&rsquo;s
memorable quote on Dostoesky&rsquo;s writing, also reported in the book, is worth
mentioning:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>The miracle of Dostoevsky&rsquo;s writing lies in eliminating the distance between
the subject (the reader) and the object (the author), by virtue of which he
turns out to be the most familiar of all contemporary writers and, perhaps,
even of future writers, of all possible writers.</p>
</blockquote>
<p><em>Subscribe to the [newsletter][nl], the [RSS feed][rss], or [follow me on Mastodon][m]</em></p>
<div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
<hr>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1">
<p>One of my all-time favorites.
[rss]: <a href="https://nicolaiarocci.com/index.xml">https://nicolaiarocci.com/index.xml</a>
[m]: <a href="https://fosstodon.org/@nicola">https://fosstodon.org/@nicola</a>
[nl]: <a href="https://nicolaiarocci.substack.com">https://nicolaiarocci.substack.com</a>&#160;<a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
</ol>
</div>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Book Review: Uomini, boschi e api</title>
      <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/book-review-uomini-boschi-e-api/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 21 Jan 2023 07:05:25 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nicolaiarocci.com/book-review-uomini-boschi-e-api/</guid>
      <description>I wish everyone could listen to the song of the partridges as the sun rises, see the deer on pastures in spring, the larch trees reddened by autumn on the edges of rocks, the darting of fish among the clear waters of streams, and the bees gathering nectar from the flowering cherry trees. In these stories, I write about village places. These natural environments are still livable, about the beautiful social insects that are bees, but also about ancient jobs that are slowly and inexorably disappearing.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<blockquote>
<p>I wish everyone could listen to the song of the partridges as the sun rises,
see the deer on pastures in spring, the larch trees reddened by autumn on the
edges of rocks, the darting of fish among the clear waters of streams, and
the bees gathering nectar from the flowering cherry trees. In these stories,
I write about village places. These natural environments are still livable,
about the beautiful social insects that are bees, but also about ancient jobs
that are slowly and inexorably disappearing.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>The book<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1</a></sup> delivers on the author&rsquo;s promise in the introduction. Mario Rigoni
Stern is an author I have always admired and loved. His biography is touching,
his themes are awe-inspiring, and his writing is simple, clean, and enjoyable.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" src="/images/uomini-boschi-api.jpg#right" alt="Uomini, boschi e api book cover"  />

This work is a collection of short stories he wrote over the years, primarily
published in magazines and newspapers. The first part of the book, about
one-third, is about Rigoni Stern&rsquo;s struggles and experiences as a wartime
prisoner during WWII. The rest is mostly about his wilderness adventures,
either as a hunter or a nature-dweller (he spent most of his life living on the
Asiago plateau in the Italian alps.) As is often the case with Rigoni Stern,
his hunting adventures are proxies to show his deep connection, respect, and
empathy for the creatures he preys on, which is counter-intuitive for the
modern, educated reader.</p>
<p>Mario Rigoni Stern was one of the very last of his age when nature still played
a primary role in everyday life. Despite his early success as a writer, he was
lucky, or smart enough, to keep living in his relatively secluded place in the
mountains, from which he could observe the unstoppable transformation of our
society from afar.</p>
<p><em>Subscribe to the [newsletter][nl], the [RSS feed][rss], or [follow me on Mastodon][m]</em></p>
<div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
<hr>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1">
<p>I am afraid there&rsquo;s no English edition available. You could always read his WWII memoir and masterpiece, <em>The Sergeant in the Snow</em>.
[rss]: <a href="https://nicolaiarocci.com/index.xml">https://nicolaiarocci.com/index.xml</a>
[m]: <a href="https://fosstodon.org/@nicola">https://fosstodon.org/@nicola</a>
[nl]: <a href="https://nicolaiarocci.substack.com">https://nicolaiarocci.substack.com</a>&#160;<a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
</ol>
</div>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Book Review: Stoner</title>
      <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/book-review-stoner/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 Dec 2022 07:05:25 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nicolaiarocci.com/book-review-stoner/</guid>
      <description>I tend to shy away from publishing cases, so Stoner has been resting on my yeah-maybe-one-day list for years. Over time I stumbled on notable mentions that kept the book on the fringe of my attention zone. Then one day, I read a brief and intriguing [review][2] in Giovanni Zagni&amp;rsquo;s excellent newsletter, Incertezze. Like me, Zagni suffers from the stay-away-from-editorial-cases idiosyncrasy, but he finally gave in, read the thing, reread it, and finally tagged it a modern classic.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I tend to shy away from publishing cases, so <em>Stoner</em> has been resting on my
yeah-maybe-one-day list for years. Over time I stumbled on notable mentions
that kept the book on the fringe of my attention zone. Then one day, I read a
brief and intriguing [review][2] in Giovanni Zagni&rsquo;s excellent newsletter,
<em>Incertezze</em>. Like me, Zagni suffers from the stay-away-from-editorial-cases
idiosyncrasy, but he finally gave in, read the thing, reread it, and finally
tagged it a modern classic. Zagni was convincing, yet it took another year
before I surrendered my weapons and took the book off the shelf. I immediately
realized I was in front of a beautiful book.</p>
<p>The <em>New York Review of Books</em> has this to say about the novel:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>John Williams&rsquo;s luminous and deeply moving novel is a work of quiet
perfection. William Stoner emerges from it not only as an archetypal American
but as an unlikely existential hero, standing, like a figure in a painting by
Edward Hopper, in stark relief against an unforgiving world.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>I find this description perfectly fit. Like Hopper&rsquo;s paintings, John William&rsquo;s
prose is indeed sparse, detached and powerful.</p>
<p>The protagonist is a professor of English at the University of Missouri in the
first half of the twentieth century. From the outside, his life and attitude
appear ordinary and dull, and that&rsquo;s how most former students and colleagues
may remember him. And yet, as his life unfolds in the pages, from boyhood at
the dirt-poor family farm to college and then adulthood,  the reader soon
recognizes the William Stoner as a modern hero, incredibly resilient in the
face of continued and unremitting harassment from the people and events around
him.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" src="/images/stoner-book-cover.jpg#right" alt="Stoner by John Williams, book cover"  />

The author John Williams grew up on a small farm in Texas and had a similar
escape to the University as Stoner&rsquo;s. Not coincidentally, I think, the author
and protagonist share resembling names. While not an autobiography, the novel
is probably imbued with the author&rsquo;s experiences.</p>
<p>Going back to Zagni&rsquo;s review, his opinion is the this novel was ahead of its
time, which would explain why it wasn&rsquo;t an immediate hit. Indeed,I was struck
by the precise and painful description of some characters&rsquo; struggles with
mental issues and past abuses and how these can unintentionally affect family
dynamics and persist over generations.</p>
<p>Stoner is a deceptively simple novel written in 1965 that tells facts of the
early twentieth century, yet it has much to say to the people of the modern
age.<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1</a></sup></p>
<p><em>Subscribe to the [newsletter][nl], the [RSS feed][rss], or [follow me on Mastodon][m]</em></p>
<div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
<hr>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1">
<p>My paperback edition (Oscar Mondadori, Italian) includes a remarkable author interview. Also, while researching the book, I dug up an enlightening 2019 The Paris Review <a href="https://www.theparisreview.org/blog/2019/02/20/mrs-stoner-speaks-an-interview-with-nancy-gardner-williams/">interview</a> with Nancy Gardner Williams, his widow.
[1]: <a href="https://giovannizagni.substack.com/">https://giovannizagni.substack.com/</a>
[2]: <a href="https://giovannizagni.substack.com/p/stoner">https://giovannizagni.substack.com/p/stoner</a>
[rss]: <a href="https://nicolaiarocci.com/index.xml">https://nicolaiarocci.com/index.xml</a>
[m]: <a href="https://fosstodon.org/@nicola">https://fosstodon.org/@nicola</a>
[nl]: <a href="https://nicolaiarocci.substack.com">https://nicolaiarocci.substack.com</a>&#160;<a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
</ol>
</div>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Book Review: Candide</title>
      <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/book-review-candide/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 18 Dec 2022 07:05:25 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nicolaiarocci.com/book-review-candide/</guid>
      <description>This short novel was a genuine surprise. I certainly didn&amp;rsquo;t expect Voltaire to be this accessible, witty, sarcastic, and also outrageous for the era (1759). Below the surface of a seemingly entertaining and often absurd sequence of improbable events is a constant philosophical struggle. Quoting from the back cover:
Candide is the story of a gentle man who, though pummeled and slapped in every direction by fate, clings desperately to the belief that he lives in &amp;ldquo;the best of all possible worlds.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>This short novel was a genuine surprise. I certainly didn&rsquo;t expect Voltaire to
be this accessible, witty, sarcastic, and also outrageous for the era (1759).
Below the surface of a seemingly entertaining and often absurd sequence of
improbable events is a constant philosophical struggle. Quoting from the back
cover:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Candide is the story of a gentle man who, though pummeled and slapped in
every direction by fate, clings desperately to the belief that he lives in
&ldquo;the best of all possible worlds.&rdquo; On the surface a witty, bantering tale,
this eighteenth-century classic is actually a savage, satiric thrust at the
philosophical optimism that proclaims that all disaster and human suffering
is part of a benevolent cosmic plan.</p>
</blockquote>
<p><img loading="lazy" src="/images/book-cover-candide.jpg#right" alt=""  />

His wondrous adventures around the world teach Candide that, contrary to the
teachings of his distinguished tutor Dr. Pangloss, all is not always for the
best.</p>
<p>With Candide, Voltaire ridicules religion, theologians, governments, armies,
philosophies, and philosophers (Leibniz being his first target). An erratic,
fantastical, picaresque novel with a fast-moving plot that enjoyed both great
success and scandal at the time of its release.</p>
<p><em>Subscribe to the <a href="https://nicolaiarocci.substack.com">newsletter</a>, the <a href="https://nicolaiarocci.com/index.xml">RSS feed</a>, or <a href="https://fosstodon.org/@nicola">follow me on Mastodon</a></em></p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Book Review: When We Cease to Understand the World</title>
      <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/book-review-when-we-cease-to-understand-the-world/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 10 Dec 2022 07:05:25 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nicolaiarocci.com/book-review-when-we-cease-to-understand-the-world/</guid>
      <description>When We Cease to Understand the World, by Benjamin Labatut, is a strange narrative object. It mixes fact and fiction in imaginative ways, sometimes making it hard for the reader to distinguish between them, which is probably a testimonial to the experiment&amp;rsquo;s success. As I was reading, Wu Ming&amp;rsquo;s unidentified narrative objects (UNO) came to mind. If it doesn&amp;rsquo;t qualify as UNO, it comes close enough. It certainly fits the &amp;lsquo;faction&amp;rsquo; (fact+fiction) genre, if such a thing exists.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>When We Cease to Understand the World, by Benjamin Labatut, is a strange
narrative object. It mixes fact and fiction in imaginative ways, sometimes
making it hard for the reader to distinguish between them, which is probably a
testimonial to the experiment&rsquo;s success. As I was reading, Wu Ming&rsquo;s
<a href="https://www.jstor.org/stable/10.5749/j.ctt1j7x9vm.10#metadata_info_tab_contents">unidentified narrative objects (UNO) </a> came to mind. If it doesn&rsquo;t qualify
as UNO, it comes close enough. It certainly fits the &lsquo;faction&rsquo; (fact+fiction)
genre, if such a thing exists.</p>
<p>The lives of brilliant scientists of the 19th century, whose discoveries
changed how we understand and perceive the world, are told by drawing on their
biographies and filling in, where necessary, with well-told, captivating
inventions. Some protagonists are well-known (Heisenberg, Schrödinger), and
others, while first-grade stars in their field, are relatively unknown to the
layman, or at least, they were to me.</p>
<p>Astronomer and physicist Karl Schwarzschild is one of them. In 1915 he provided
the first exact solution to the Einstein field equations of general relativity.
Karl accomplished this tremendous feat while serving on the Russian front
during World War I. On December 22, 1915, a letter contaikning the solution to
Einstein&rsquo;s dilemma was sent from the trenches. One month later, Einstein
acknowledged it with enthusiasm and then, only five months later, on May 11,
1916, Schwarzschild died from a disease he developed at the Russian front.</p>
<p>Mathematician Alexander Grothendieck is another one I didn&rsquo;t know about, whose
life was fascinating. A stateless mathematician who became the leading figure
in the creation of modern algebraic geometry, he received the Fields Medal in
1966. While still producing relevant work, Alexander withdrew from the
mathematical community and devoted himself to political and religious pursuits.
In 1991, he moved to the French village of Lasserre in the Pyrenees, where he
lived in seclusion, still working tirelessly on mathematics and his
philosophical and religious thoughts until he died in 2014.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" src="/images/quando-abbiamo-smesso-di-capire-il-mondo.jpg#right" alt=""  />

And there&rsquo;s the extraordinary and controversial figure of Fritz Haber, the
german Nobel Prize chemist. His inventions allowed for the industrialization
and large-scale production of fertilizers and explosives. He became renowned as
the &ldquo;father of chemical warfare&rdquo; during World War I. His pioneering work
developing and weaponizing chlorine and other poisonous gases led to the cruel
death of tens of thousands of soldiers in WWI. His work led to the infamous
Zyklon B, responsible for killing millions of Jewish people in World War II
(Haber was of Jewish origins.)</p>
<p>Again, the problem with &lsquo;faction&rsquo; is that you never know whether you&rsquo;re reading
facts, making it hard to distinguish between actual stories and invention. Much
of fiction went into the main story, the gripping battle over quantum mechanics
between Heisenberg and Schrödinger, and in their biographies especially<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1</a></sup>.</p>
<p>A book worth reading.</p>
<p><em>Subscribe to the [newsletter][nl], the [RSS feed][rss], or follow @[nicolaiarocci][tw] on Twitter</em></p>
<div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
<hr>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1">
<p>In 2020, I read a non-fictionalized account of Heisenberg&rsquo;s and Schrödinger&rsquo;s struggles with quantum in Carlo Rovelli&rsquo;s excellent <em>Helgoland</em>.
[rss]: <a href="https://nicolaiarocci.com/index.xml">https://nicolaiarocci.com/index.xml</a>
[tw]: <a href="http://twitter.com/nicolaiarocci">http://twitter.com/nicolaiarocci</a>
[nl]: <a href="https://nicolaiarocci.substack.com">https://nicolaiarocci.substack.com</a>&#160;<a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
</ol>
</div>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Book Review: Mašen&#39;ka</title>
      <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/book-review-ma%C5%A1enka/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Nov 2022 07:05:25 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nicolaiarocci.com/book-review-ma%C5%A1enka/</guid>
      <description>Masen&amp;rsquo;ka (or Mary) is Nabokov&amp;rsquo;s debut novel. It was written when he was in his twenties, living as an émigré in Berlin, just like the story&amp;rsquo;s protagonist. In the introduction of my Italian edition (Adelphi), the author admits that some life events poured into the narration. The depiction of Ganin&amp;rsquo;s life in a pension filled with fellow Russian ex-pats, and the relationships between them, is undoubtedly reminiscent of Nabokov&amp;rsquo;s own experience.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Masen&rsquo;ka (or Mary) is Nabokov&rsquo;s debut novel. It was written when he was in his
twenties, living as an émigré in Berlin, just like the story&rsquo;s protagonist. In
the introduction of my Italian edition (Adelphi), the author admits that some
life events poured into the narration. The depiction of Ganin&rsquo;s life in a
pension filled with fellow Russian ex-pats, and the relationships between them,
is undoubtedly reminiscent of Nabokov&rsquo;s own experience.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" src="/images/book-cover-masenka.jpg#right" alt="Book cover: Masen&amp;rsquo;ka"  />

Several of the themes of this story will be recurrent in his later works:
memory, Russian ex-pat, nostalgia and a yearning for the past, which is, in
fact, the central theme here. Young Nabokov&rsquo;s prose is good but not as great as
in his later works. Here, we appreciate the beginnings of what will eventually
pupate and make Nabokov one of the greatest.</p>
<p>With this work, Nabokov tells us that no matter the pomp and nostalgia, one
must leave the past behind and let the present life flow.</p>
<p><em>Subscribe to the <a href="https://nicolaiarocci.substack.com">newsletter</a>, the <a href="https://nicolaiarocci.com/index.xml">RSS feed</a>, or follow @<a href="http://twitter.com/nicolaiarocci">nicolaiarocci</a> on Twitter</em></p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Book Review: The Crow Comes Last</title>
      <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/book-review-the-crow-comes-last/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 25 Nov 2022 07:05:25 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nicolaiarocci.com/book-review-the-crow-comes-last/</guid>
      <description>The Crow Comes Last is a collection of thirty short stories written between 1945 and 1948, primarily based on the author&amp;rsquo;s wartime experiences as a resistance fighter during WWII and then in postwar Italy. Some are brutal, others funny, and some are gritty. They all revolve around the themes he perfectly defined while talking about his book:
I prefer to divide the subject into three parts, to highlight three thematic lines of my work from those years.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The Crow Comes Last is a collection of thirty short stories written between
1945 and 1948, primarily based on the author&rsquo;s wartime experiences as a
resistance fighter during WWII and then in postwar Italy. Some are brutal,
others funny, and some are gritty. They all revolve around the themes he
perfectly defined while talking about his book:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>I prefer to divide the subject into three parts, to highlight three thematic
lines of my work from those years. The first is the &lsquo;Resistance&rsquo; story (or at
any rate of war or violence), seen as an adventure of suspense or terror, a
type of fiction that quite a few of us did at that time. The second line is
also common to much fiction of those years and is the postwar picaresque
tale, stories coloured by elemental characters and appetites. In the third,
the landscape of the Riviera dominates, with boys or teenagers and animals.
This last line is a personal development of a &rsquo;literature of memory. Needless
to say, the three lines often.</p>
</blockquote>
<p><img loading="lazy" src="/images/the-crow-comes-last.jpg#right" alt="The Crow Comes Last"  />

Although mainly written in the neorealist style, many scenes are infused with
visionary, fable-like elements characteristic of Calvino&rsquo;s later fantasy
period. My favourites are <em>Adam, One Afternoon</em>, <em>Theft in the Cake Shop</em>, <em>The
Cat and the Policeman</em>, <em>Fear on the Foothpath</em>, and <em>The Crow Comes Last</em>.</p>
<p>Short story collections are not fancy these days and probably never have been.
Yet this is a book I would probably suggest to someone coming to Calvino for
the first time, as some of his full-length novels can sometimes feel too
&ldquo;esotheric&rdquo; to the newcomer.</p>
<p><em>Subscribe to the <a href="https://nicolaiarocci.substack.com">newsletter</a>, the <a href="https://nicolaiarocci.com/index.xml">RSS feed</a>, or follow @<a href="http://twitter.com/nicolaiarocci">nicolaiarocci</a> on Twitter</em></p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Book Review: Ravenna</title>
      <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/book-review-ravenna/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 07 Nov 2022 07:05:25 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nicolaiarocci.com/book-review-ravenna/</guid>
      <description>Nerdy prelude. Local Bulletin Board Systems (BBS) were all the range when I was a teenager. With my group of local hackers, we hacked our way into ITAPAC, the then-leading Italian packet-switching network (we are talking pre-Internet era here.) Via ITAPAC, we&amp;rsquo;d connect to so-called &amp;ldquo;out-dial systems&amp;rdquo; in the USA. From one of those, we&amp;rsquo;d finally call our target BBSes with a local call at no cost. We felt so invincible!</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><em>Nerdy prelude.</em> Local Bulletin Board Systems (BBS) were all the
range when I was a teenager. With my group of local hackers, we hacked our way
into ITAPAC, the then-leading Italian packet-switching network (we are talking
pre-Internet era here.) Via ITAPAC, we&rsquo;d connect to so-called &ldquo;out-dial
systems&rdquo; in the USA. From one of those, we&rsquo;d finally call our target BBSes with
a local call at no cost. We felt so invincible! I signed up on Channel One BBS;
I think that was the name. This particular BBS was located in Cambridge, MA,
and was chock-full of public domain and shareware I could download. Anyways,
the SysOp sent me a postcard confirming my signup (an old-school paper postcard
delivered via international postal service). Receiving a postcard from the US
was exciting in itself, but what was startling was a handwritten note on the
postcard. It said, &ldquo;Ravenna, city of beautiful mosaics.&rdquo; I was shocked that
someone from Cambridge, MA, would know about my tiny, little hometown&rsquo;s mosaics
and let me know.</p>
<p>While Ravenna is relegated to a marginal role in the modern age, it played
a very significant one in ancient times. Quoting from the from the
backcover of the book:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>In 402 AD, after invading tribes broke through the Alpine frontiers of Italy
and threatened the imperial government in Milan, the young Emperor Honorius
made the momentous decision to move his capital to a small, easy defendable
city in the Po estuary - Ravenna. From then until 751 AD, Ravenna was first
the capital of the Western Roman Empire, then that of the immense kingdom of
Theoderic the Goth and finally the centre of Byzantine power in Italy.</p>
</blockquote>
<p><img loading="lazy" src="/images/book-cover-ravenna.jpg#right" alt=""  />

In her tome, Judith Herrin tells Ravenna&rsquo;s story from its time as the capital
of the Western Roman Empire to the late 8th century, when it inspired
Charlemagne&rsquo;s imperial and religious building projects in Aachen. This book&rsquo;s
576 pages are packed with dense information. Many political, military, and
spiritual characters&rsquo; in-life achievements and troubles build a complicated
narrative spanning four centuries. It helps that small, titled sections within
each chapter offer a palatable framework.</p>
<p>Herrin&rsquo;s monumental work is one to be admired and respected. I was especially
delighted when Pippin and his son Charlemagne came into play in the book&rsquo;s
final part. As I&rsquo;ve read <a href="/book-review-king-and-emperor-a-new-life-of-charlemagne/">King and Emperor, A New Life of Charlemagne</a>
recently, I could merge knowledge from the two works. The flow of events that
originated with the demise of the Western Roman Empire and, centuries later,
led to the first glimpse of &ldquo;Europe,&rdquo; as we intend it today, is much clearer
now.</p>
<p>Of Ravenna&rsquo;s glorious byzantine age, only the beautiful mosaics and the
baptisteries and churches containing them have survived for today&rsquo;s visitors to
enjoy.</p>
<p><em>&lsquo;O lone Ravenna! many a tale is told <!-- raw HTML omitted -->
Of thy great glories in the days of old&rsquo; <!-- raw HTML omitted -->
&ndash;Oscar Wilde</em></p>
<p><em>Subscribe to the <a href="https://nicolaiarocci.substack.com">newsletter</a>, the <a href="https://nicolaiarocci.com/index.xml">RSS feed</a>, or follow @<a href="http://twitter.com/nicolaiarocci">nicolaiarocci</a> on Twitter</em></p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Book Review: The Count of Monte Cristo</title>
      <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/book-review-the-count-of-monte-cristo/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 16 Sep 2022 07:05:25 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nicolaiarocci.com/book-review-the-count-of-monte-cristo/</guid>
      <description>In my early morning stroll, I sometimes listen to audiobooks. This was the case with The Count of Monte Cristo. Rai Radio 3, the third channel of the national broadcasting service, has been airing Ad Alta Voce (Aloud) for many years. In the program, top-tier actors read old and new literary classics. The quality of these productions is astounding. Audio editions are often edited, which was the case with The Count, as the unabridged edition surpasses the 1200-page count (a little-known fact is that most printed editions are also edited for brevity).</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>In my early morning stroll, I sometimes listen to audiobooks. This was the case
with The Count of Monte Cristo. Rai Radio 3, the third channel of the national
broadcasting service, has been airing <a href="https://www.raiplaysound.it/programmi/adaltavoce">Ad Alta Voce</a> (Aloud) for many years.
In the program, top-tier actors read old and new literary classics. The quality
of these productions is astounding. Audio editions are often edited, which was
the case with The Count, as the unabridged edition surpasses the 1200-page
count (a little-known fact is that most printed editions are also edited for
brevity). Despite the edits, <a href="https://www.raiplaysound.it/audiolibri/ilcontedimontecristo">the audiobook</a>, splendidly performed by <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Andrea_Giordana">Andrea
Giordana</a>, comprises thirty-five installments, each about thirty minutes
long. That makes for a lot of strolling.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" src="/images/the-count-of-monte-cristo.jpg#right" alt=""  />

The Count was initially published in a literary magazine, in eighteen parts,
from August 1844 to January 1846. Entirely attributed to Alexandre Dumas, it
was also authored by Auguste Maquet; ghostwriters are not just an XX-ish century
thing. According to the legend, when the publication started, Dumas didn&rsquo;t know
how the story would end or how it would develop. Nonetheless, it was an
immediate hit that quickly became a literary classic with many film and TV
adaptions and an infinite number of copycats. The story, partially based on
<a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pierre_Picaud">real facts</a>, is well known and as intriguing, captivating and entertaining
as it could get for a mid-XIX century adventure novel. It helps that it is
rooted in notable historical events like the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bourbon_Restoration_in_France">Bourbon Restoration</a> and
Napoleon&rsquo;s <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hundred_Days">Hundred Days</a>.</p>
<p>The audiobook does an excellent job at skipping the tedious parts while
focusing on the main narrative but still includes many characters and events.
It is sometimes hard to track them all, especially if your listening, or
reading, is discontinuous, like in my case.</p>
<p>Critics didn&rsquo;t go easy on this novel. Famously, Umberto Eco had this to say:
&ldquo;The Count of Monte Cristo is undoubtedly one of the most exciting novels ever
written, and on the other hand, it is one of the most poorly written novels of
all time and all literature.&rdquo; R.L Stevenson concurs: &ldquo;The first part of Monte
Cristo, up to the discovery of the treasure, is a perfect piece of knockout
storytelling; there has never been a man who has participated in these moving
adventures without a quiver, yet Faria is a papier-mâché character and Dantès
little more than a name. The sequel is but the prolongation of a mistake, dark,
bloody, unnatural and stupid.&rdquo;</p>
<p>I think I agree with both: The Count of Montecristo is rich of exciting
moments, intriguing events and unexpected plot twists. Yet, the composition is
often confusing (mainly in the second part) and, more importantly, too
many implausible coincidences occur throughout the story. Yet, it&rsquo;s a lot of
entertainment. What I found more compelling, however, are its social and
historical competence. I learned a lot by reading (listening to) this novel.</p>
<p>Being the book junkie I am, I went out and bought the unabridged tome. I can&rsquo;t
help it; I must possess the physical thing. The book is now happily resting in
my library, and I can move on.</p>
<p><em>Subscribe to the <a href="https://nicolaiarocci.substack.com">newsletter</a>, the <a href="https://nicolaiarocci.com/index.xml">RSS feed</a>, or follow @<a href="http://twitter.com/nicolaiarocci">nicolaiarocci</a> on Twitter</em></p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Book Review: Smiling Bears</title>
      <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/book-review-smiling-bears/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 12 Sep 2022 07:05:25 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nicolaiarocci.com/book-review-smiling-bears/</guid>
      <description>My perception of zoos has always been of prisons—places of suffering where animals are held captive for human entertainment. Smiling Bears offered a new perspective. Some (hopefully most) zoos provide a safe harbor to abused and rescued animals who could never return to their natural habitats. Zookeepers like Else Poulsen care for these creatures, accompanying them in their rehabilitation process. I imagine not all zoos and zookeepers meet these standards, but it is reassuring to know these things happen.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>My perception of zoos has always been of prisons—places of suffering where
animals are held captive for human entertainment. <em>Smiling Bears</em> offered a new
perspective. Some (hopefully most) zoos provide a safe harbor to abused and
rescued animals who could never return to their natural habitats. Zookeepers
like Else Poulsen care for these creatures, accompanying them in their
rehabilitation process. I imagine not all zoos and zookeepers meet these
standards, but it is reassuring to know these things happen.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" src="/images/smiling-bears.jpg#right" alt=""  />

Few people know bears as intimately as Else Poulsen. She has raised bears,
comforted bears, taught bears, learned from bears, had bears communicate their
needs to her, and nursed bears back to health. This book offers remarkable
insights into the complexity and richness of bears behavior and emotional life.
Individual bear stories are often touching, as is the relationship they develop
with their care keeper.</p>
<p><em>Subscribe to the <a href="https://nicolaiarocci.substack.com">newsletter</a>, the <a href="https://nicolaiarocci.com/index.xml">RSS feed</a>, or follow @<a href="http://twitter.com/nicolaiarocci">nicolaiarocci</a> on Twitter</em></p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Book Review: A Captive West or the tragedy of Central Europe</title>
      <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/book-review-a-captive-west-or-the-tragedy-of-central-europe/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 18 Aug 2022 07:05:25 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nicolaiarocci.com/book-review-a-captive-west-or-the-tragedy-of-central-europe/</guid>
      <description>Adelphi1 prints in book form two unpublished speeches by Milan Kundera, one from 1967 and the other from 1983, in which the great Czech writer reflects on the fate of the small nations in central Europe and the cultural drift of (western) Europe as a whole. As we read along, thanks to Kundera&amp;rsquo;s acumen and depth of analysis, we find many surprising ante-litteram references to today&amp;rsquo;s critical situation (Russian-Ukrainian war).</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Adelphi<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1</a></sup> prints in book form two unpublished speeches by Milan Kundera, one from
1967 and the other from 1983, in which the great Czech writer reflects on the
fate of the small nations in central Europe and the cultural drift of (western)
Europe as a whole. As we read along, thanks to Kundera&rsquo;s acumen and depth of
analysis, we find many surprising ante-litteram references to today&rsquo;s critical
situation (Russian-Ukrainian war).</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" src="/images/a-captive-west.jpg#right" alt=""  />

Reflecting on the fragmentary history of the Czech nation and on its shaky
equilibrium (as it will be evident shortly after that), in 1967, the writer
asks, &ldquo;Is the cultural value of our people such as to justify its [nation]
existence?&rdquo; And to this question, he then adds a second one: &ldquo;will this value
suffice in the future to protect it from losing its sovereignty?&rdquo; West Europe&rsquo;s
failure to understand the dilemma and its substantial indifference to the fate
of the small eastern nations, which Russia&rsquo;s totalitarian giant will eventually
swallow up, are co-responsible for this loss of living identity and culture.</p>
<p>In the second text (1983), Kundera questions the &ldquo;disappearance&rdquo; of Europe as
an ideal horizon (but also as a concrete force): united in the Middle Ages by
the Christian religion, in the 18th century by Enlightenment philosophy, and in
the modern age by the culture at large, what shared values constitute its
foundation today? Perhaps technology and the entertainment industry?</p>
<blockquote>
<p>It is not, therefore, political boundaries (inauthentic, always imposed by
invasions, conquests and occupations) that determine the Central European
aggregation. It is great common situations that bring peoples together, and
group them in ever-changing ways, within imaginary and ever-changing
boundaries, where the same memory, the same experience, and the same
traditions remain.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>If this unifying fabric is not there (and we need to understand by what threads
it is held fast), each small nation is bound to see its autonomous and free
existence called into question.</p>
<p>Thanks to Kundera&rsquo;s brilliant reflections, I could look into recent Central
Europe history from a different, non-western-centric perspective and get
precious insights into current events. Look at what is happening
today before our incredulous and appalled eyes.</p>
<p><em>Subscribe to the [newsletter][nl], the [RSS feed][rss], or follow @[nicolaiarocci][tw] on Twitter</em></p>
<div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
<hr>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1">
<p>I&rsquo;m not aware of any available English editions at this time, but it&rsquo;s likely that the transcriptions of the speeches can be found online.
[rss]: <a href="https://nicolaiarocci.com/index.xml">https://nicolaiarocci.com/index.xml</a>
[tw]: <a href="http://twitter.com/nicolaiarocci">http://twitter.com/nicolaiarocci</a>
[nl]: <a href="https://nicolaiarocci.substack.com">https://nicolaiarocci.substack.com</a>&#160;<a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
</ol>
</div>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Book Review: Just an Ordinary Day</title>
      <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/book-review-just-an-ordinary-day/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 18 Aug 2022 07:05:25 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nicolaiarocci.com/book-review-just-an-ordinary-day/</guid>
      <description>As a Shirley Jackson fan, I couldn&amp;rsquo;t pass on this new collection of unpublished short stories. A good chunk of these was unheard of for thirty years until someone unearthed some cardboard boxes in a Vermont barn and then sent them to her heirs.
Unlike The Lottery, where all tales followed a distinct theme, Just an Ordinary Day has little to unite the stories. Several genres are represented: classic family stories, supernatural, horror, and unsettling accounts of day-to-day life in the fifties all make up the list.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>As a Shirley Jackson fan, I couldn&rsquo;t pass on this new collection of unpublished
short stories. A good chunk of these was unheard of for thirty years until
someone unearthed some cardboard boxes in a Vermont barn and then sent them to
her heirs.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" src="/images/luna-di-miele-mrs-smith.jpg#right" alt=""  />

Unlike The Lottery, where all tales followed a distinct theme, Just an Ordinary
Day has little to unite the stories. Several genres are represented: classic
family stories, supernatural, horror, and unsettling accounts of day-to-day
life in the fifties all make up the list. Not all stories are of the same
level. While most are mature for prime time, a few could have used some more
tinkering, yet they were worth publishing as a precious testimony of an
(infinitely talented) writer&rsquo;s creative process. At one point, two versions of
the same tale are put side by side, thus allowing a look into how Shirley
Jackson revised her stories and perfected them over time. I think my Italian
(Adelphi) edition includes a selection of the original collection of more than
fifty, which is probably a good thing (I read somewhere that a second book with
the missing pieces is planned).</p>
<p>I would probably not recommend this book as a first-time Jackson reading. Her
renowned fiction would be a better entry point<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1</a></sup>, with The Lottery serving as her
must-read short-stories collection. Just an Ordinary Day is an excellent
addition to any Jackson collection, with some of its tales deserving
recognition at the top of her writing.</p>
<p><em>Subscribe to the [newsletter][nl], the [RSS feed][rss], or follow @[nicolaiarocci][tw] on Twitter</em></p>
<div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
<hr>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1">
<p>Somewhat recently, I reviewed <a href="/book-review-we-have-always-lived-in-the-castle/">We Have Always Lived in the Castle</a>.
[rss]: <a href="https://nicolaiarocci.com/index.xml">https://nicolaiarocci.com/index.xml</a>
[tw]: <a href="http://twitter.com/nicolaiarocci">http://twitter.com/nicolaiarocci</a>
[nl]: <a href="https://nicolaiarocci.substack.com">https://nicolaiarocci.substack.com</a>&#160;<a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
</ol>
</div>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Book Review: Italica</title>
      <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/book-review-italica/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 29 Jul 2022 07:05:25 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nicolaiarocci.com/book-review-italica/</guid>
      <description>Suppose you are looking for a juicy and thought-provoking read on Italy&amp;rsquo;s twentieth-century crucial moments. In that case, I heartily recommend Italica by Giacomo Papi, a significant collection of short stories by prominent Italian writers of the period including the likes of Italo Calvino, Elsa Morante, Beppe Fenoglio, Natalia Ginzburg, and Giorgio Scerbanenco. A short essay introduces each tale. I thoughtfully appreciated these introductions, sometimes even more so than the story itself, as they are quintessential to comprehending the tale&amp;rsquo;s historical background.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Suppose you are looking for a juicy and thought-provoking read on Italy&rsquo;s
twentieth-century crucial moments. In that case, I heartily recommend Italica
by Giacomo Papi, a significant collection of short stories by prominent Italian
writers of the period including the likes of Italo Calvino,  Elsa Morante,
Beppe Fenoglio, Natalia Ginzburg, and Giorgio Scerbanenco. A short essay
introduces each tale. I thoughtfully appreciated these introductions, sometimes
even more so than the story itself, as they are quintessential to comprehending
the tale&rsquo;s historical background. Papi&rsquo;s remarks are insightful, brilliant,
well-written, well-documented, and often heavily data-driven.</p>
<p>The last three tales conceal prophecies about the near future, corresponding to
today&rsquo;s present. I was impressed by Primo Levi&rsquo;s 1971 Forehead Writing, where
a world in which everyone can become a testimonial for a product is described
vividly and bitingly. It&rsquo;s impossible not to think of what we see and display
on social media these days. Papi&rsquo;s comment in this regard is illuminating:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>With the selfie, photography ceased to be an instant captured by the observer
to become a representation of the one being shown. The double lens blurred
the boundary between observer and observed, turned the subject into the
object, the viewer into the spectacle.</p>
</blockquote>
<p><img loading="lazy" src="/images/italica.jpg#right" alt="Italica, by Giacomo Papi"  />

Italica brilliantly recapitulates a hundred years of Italian history through
the words of some of the best writers who lived through them. It talks about
the Great War, fascism, racial laws, the Merlin law, terrorism, &ldquo;Mani Pulite,&rdquo;
and other events and situations that have conditioned Italy&rsquo;s twentieth century
and still have after-effects in our lives today.</p>
<p><em>Subscribe to the <a href="https://nicolaiarocci.substack.com">newsletter</a>, the <a href="https://nicolaiarocci.com/index.xml">RSS feed</a>, or follow @<a href="http://twitter.com/nicolaiarocci">nicolaiarocci</a> on Twitter</em></p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Book Review: The Rings of Saturn</title>
      <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/book-review-the-rings-of-saturn/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 Jun 2022 07:05:25 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nicolaiarocci.com/book-review-the-rings-of-saturn/</guid>
      <description>W.G. Sebald is widely considered among the best modern German authors, so I approached this book with curiosity and high expectations. The Rings of Saturn records the author&amp;rsquo;s walking tour along the East Coast of England. As W.G. Sebald resides in the intellectual world, his tour naturally brings up literary, cultural or historical reminiscences.
An astute Goodreads reviewer noted that Britain&amp;rsquo;s decline&amp;rsquo;s eccentric and grotesque aspects are this work&amp;rsquo;s central theme.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>W.G. Sebald is widely considered among the best modern German authors, so
I approached this book with curiosity and high expectations. The  Rings of
Saturn records the author&rsquo;s walking tour along the East Coast of England. As
W.G. Sebald resides in the intellectual world, his tour naturally brings up
literary, cultural or historical reminiscences.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" src="/images/the-rings-of-saturn.jpg#right" alt="The Rings of Saturn"  />

An astute Goodreads reviewer noted that Britain&rsquo;s decline&rsquo;s eccentric and
grotesque aspects are this work&rsquo;s central theme. The peregrinations of Thomas
Browne&rsquo;s skull, dubious capitalism, carpet bombing of Nazi Germany,
20th-century Imperialism, the case of Roger Casement, Belgian Congo genocide,
quasi-repatriation of Michael Hamburger, Tai-ping rebellion, Joseph Conrad&rsquo;s
Congo excursion, Edward Fitzgerald&rsquo;s life and times, etc.—and how these end,
or, indeed, constitute decay, dissolution and death. That&rsquo;s a lot of output for
a few days-long walk-about.</p>
<p>I learned about many people and events I was unaware of, and I&rsquo;m grateful for
that. The writing is excellent, as it is the Italian translation. But this work
lacks a solid central character; the narrator&rsquo;s travels don&rsquo;t tie its disparate
strands together adequately, making the whole not as gripping as desired.</p>
<p><em>Subscribe to the <a href="https://nicolaiarocci.substack.com">newsletter</a>, the <a href="https://nicolaiarocci.com/index.xml">RSS feed</a>, or follow @<a href="http://twitter.com/nicolaiarocci">nicolaiarocci</a> on Twitter</em></p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Book Review: Invisible Cities</title>
      <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/book-review-invisible-cities/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 May 2022 07:05:25 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nicolaiarocci.com/book-review-invisible-cities/</guid>
      <description>&amp;ldquo;Kublai Khan does not necessarily believe everything Marco Polo says when he describes the cities visited on his expeditions, but the emperor of the Tartars does continue listening to the young Venetian with greater attention and curiosity than he shows any other messenger or explorer of his.&amp;rdquo; So begins Italo Calvino&amp;rsquo;s compilation of fragmentary urban images. As Marco tells the khan about Armilla, which &amp;ldquo;has nothing that makes it seem a city, except the water pipes that rise vertically where the houses should be and spread out horizontally where the floors should be,&amp;rdquo; the spider-web city of Octavia, and other marvelous burgs, it may be that he is creating them all out of his imagination, or perhaps he is recreating fine details of his native Venice over and over again, or perhaps he is simply recounting some of the myriad possible forms a city might take.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<blockquote>
<p>&ldquo;Kublai Khan does not necessarily believe everything Marco Polo says when he
describes the cities visited on his expeditions, but the emperor of the
Tartars does continue listening to the young Venetian with greater attention
and curiosity than he shows any other messenger or explorer of his.&rdquo; So
begins Italo Calvino&rsquo;s compilation of fragmentary urban images. As Marco
tells the khan about Armilla, which &ldquo;has nothing that makes it seem a city,
except the water pipes that rise vertically where the houses should be and
spread out horizontally where the floors should be,&rdquo; the spider-web city of
Octavia, and other marvelous burgs, it may be that he is creating them all
out of his imagination, or perhaps he is recreating fine details of his
native Venice over and over again, or perhaps he is simply recounting some of
the myriad possible forms a city might take.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Invisible Cities is a collection of thoughts taking the form of cities or
cities taking the form of thoughts. It is an aesthetic and allegorical
description of some fictional, mostly surreal cities. Some of the portrayals
are fabulous: these cities suddenly come to life in the reader&rsquo;s mind thanks to
Calvino&rsquo;s mastery, who manages to materialize absurd cities, which have nothing
of the cities we are used to observing day after day; yet they appear to us
almost natural, absolutely possible, and charged with a suggestiveness that no
earthly city could have. In addition to the vivid images, however, we will be
confronted with the thought that the shapes of those cities give rise to the
figure of their inhabitants, who may represent various sides of human nature.</p>
<p>I can&rsquo;t help but think of suggestive architectures mentioned in other works,
like Mervyn Peake&rsquo;s Gormenghast series or Hayao Miyazaki&rsquo;s animes. In Peake and
Miyazaki, architecture plays a fundamental and often active role (think of
Howl&rsquo;s Moving Castle). Likewise, Calvino&rsquo;s Cities are absolute protagonists,
while Marco Polo and the khan are mere means to the narration.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" src="/images/citta-invisibili.jpg#right" alt="Le Città Invisibili"  />

Invisible Cities is one of Calvino&rsquo;s best works. Like others of his, it might
even appear light to the superficial reader while it&rsquo;s chock full of precious
insights and profound thoughts delivered by a master at the art.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>The inferno of the living is not something that will be; if there is one, it
is what is already here, the inferno where we live every day, that we form by
being together. There are two ways to escape suffering it. The first is easy
for many: accept the inferno and become such a part of it that you can no
longer see it. The second is risky and demands constant vigilance and
apprehension: seek and learn to recognize who and what, in the midst of
inferno, are not inferno, then make them endure, give them space. ― Italo
Calvino, Invisible Cities</p>
</blockquote>
<p><em>Subscribe to the <a href="https://nicolaiarocci.substack.com">newsletter</a>, the <a href="https://nicolaiarocci.com/index.xml">RSS feed</a>, or follow @<a href="http://twitter.com/nicolaiarocci">nicolaiarocci</a> on Twitter</em></p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Book Review: Memoirs of Hadrian</title>
      <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/book-review-memoirs-of-hadrian/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 16 May 2022 07:05:25 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nicolaiarocci.com/book-review-memoirs-of-hadrian/</guid>
      <description>Memoirs of Hadrian and its author Marguerite Yourcenar have always induced a cautious fear in me. I fretted the tome for high literary circles, one of those texts so infused with learned quotations and obscure literary references as to be utterly indigestible to the average reader. Despite their evident reputation, I relegated the Memoirs to the bottom of my reading list for a long time. When I stumbled on another reference to Yourcenar&amp;rsquo;s work a couple of weeks ago, I finally decided to plunge and pull the Memoirs off the shelf.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Memoirs of Hadrian and its author Marguerite Yourcenar have always induced
a cautious fear in me. I fretted the tome for high literary circles, one of
those texts so infused with learned quotations and obscure literary references
as to be utterly indigestible to the average reader. Despite their evident
reputation, I relegated the Memoirs to the bottom of my reading list for a long
time. When I stumbled on another reference to Yourcenar&rsquo;s work a couple of
weeks ago, I finally decided to plunge and pull the Memoirs off the shelf.</p>
<p>It was immediately apparent that I was facing something exceptional. The
memoirs are drafted by an elderly emperor Hadrian for his young friend &ldquo;Mark,&rdquo;
the future Marcus Aurelius. Hadrian does not flinch. He tells of his many great
successes but does not hide his mistakes and weaknesses. The former he points
out so that his protégé can steer clear of them; the latter he investigates,
not without that indulgence that every elder is entitled to.</p>
<p>The emperor writes of practical things: the organization of the state and
turbulent provinces management (he devoted a significant part of his career to
visiting the remote provinces, so much that he was criticized for being too
absent from Rome), the conspiracies he foiled and the problematic management of
the enormous army, with all its quarrelsome commanders and legions. But Hadrian
also tells about his private life: the boundless ambition of his youth, the
passion for Hellenic culture and how it influenced his reign. He writes about
his fleeting loves and the relationship with the young Antinous, his only true
love, tragically lost way too soon. To overcome the trauma of the loss, Hadrian
does what is precluded to ordinary mortals: deifies his beloved. He establishes
a cult of  Antinous, which, surprisingly so in the eyes of modern man,
flourishes everywhere in the vast empire, taking different forms depending on
the receiving religion. Like any ordinary person, the emperor wonders about the
eternal questions that plague humanity. He offers answers to some while others
are left unanswered, impenetrable even to the divine emperor.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" src="/images/memoirs-of-hadrian.jpg#right" alt="Memoirs of Hadrian"  />

The text is compelling, intimate and full of such accurate details that I soon
wondered whether what I was reading was a literary invention or a historical
document. The truth lies somewhere in between. According to the sources,
Hadrian did write an autobiography, but it is lost. The Memoirs is indeed
a work of fiction; the result, however, of meticulous historical research
carried out, between ups and downs, for thirty years. Everything that Hadrian
recounts is historically attested. Where doubts exist, the author chooses the
most reliable historical hypothesis, not failing at times to adjust, rehash, or
add where necessary. The author&rsquo;s notes, included in my edition, are invaluable
in fully understanding and appreciating the amount and quality of work done.
Yourcenar conceived the idea in 1924-25, when she was only 22 years old, only
to publish it in 1951. Nowadays, historical novels are common but not in the
early twentieth century, when the memoir letter form was probably unheard of.
The result is a daring and unconventional work for the time, a high-risk
publication that was instead an immediate success with both the public and the
critics who acclaimed it.</p>
<p>My long-held fears were unfounded after all. Although with some guilty delay,
this book goes straight into my all-time top ten.</p>
<p>See also: <em><a href="/becoming-the-emperor/">Becoming the Emperor</a></em></p>
<p><em>Subscribe to the <a href="https://nicolaiarocci.substack.com">newsletter</a>, the <a href="https://nicolaiarocci.com/index.xml">RSS feed</a>, or follow @<a href="http://twitter.com/nicolaiarocci">nicolaiarocci</a> on Twitter</em></p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Book Review: Lone Rider</title>
      <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/book-review-lone-rider/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 15 Apr 2022 07:05:25 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nicolaiarocci.com/book-review-lone-rider/</guid>
      <description>In 1982, at just twenty-three years old and halfway through her architectural studies, Elspeth Beard left her family and friends in London and set off on a 35,000-mile solo adventure around the world on her 1974 BMW R60/6.
Exhausted by a recent breakup and with only a few savings scraped together from her job in a pub, a tent, a few clothes and some tools, all packed on the back of her bike, she was determined to prove herself.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>In 1982, at just twenty-three years old and halfway through her architectural
studies, Elspeth Beard left her family and friends in London and set off on
a 35,000-mile solo adventure around the world on her 1974 BMW R60/6.</p>
<p>Exhausted by a recent breakup and with only a few savings scraped together from
her job in a pub, a tent, a few clothes and some tools, all packed on the back
of her bike, she was determined to prove herself.</p>
<p>After almost two and a half years, she returned to London, having lost much
weight but wiser by decades. She had ridden through unforgiving landscapes and
war-torn countries and witnessed civil uprisings that forced her to forge
documents. She had fended off multiple sexual attacks, biker gangs, and corrupt
police convinced she was a drug dealer. She had survived life-threatening
illnesses, personal losses, and brutal accidents that left permanent scars and
a black hole in her memory. She had also fallen in love with two very different
men.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" src="/images/lone-rider.jpg#right" alt="Lone Rider"  />

This book is an absorbing account of a true adventure, not just a motorcycle
adventure, lived by a woman of exceptional character, strength, tenacity and
resilience.</p>
<p>Today it seems incredible that at the time, no one was interested in this story
and that thirty years had to pass before it was published. Distance in time is
sometimes felt, especially in the lack of details or how some parts of the
journey are glossed over. Fortunately, Beard kept an accurate diary, on which
she drew heavily. The result is, in any case, 336 compelling pages, well worth
reading.</p>
<p><em>Subscribe to the <a href="https://nicolaiarocci.substack.com">newsletter</a>, the <a href="https://nicolaiarocci.com/index.xml">RSS feed</a>, or follow @<a href="http://twitter.com/nicolaiarocci">nicolaiarocci</a> on Twitter</em></p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Book Review: Roumeli</title>
      <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/book-review-roumeli/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 02 Apr 2022 07:05:25 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nicolaiarocci.com/book-review-roumeli/</guid>
      <description>Roumeli describes Fermor&amp;rsquo;s travels around Northern Greece and Macedonia. He visits secluded and remote areas and describes the rugged countryside and how people of these remote regions live. As he meets Sarakatsan shepherds and spends some time with them, visits the impressive monasteries of Meteora, attempts to track a pair of Byron&amp;rsquo;s slippers in Missolonghi and investigates Kravara and its secret language, he makes acute observations about these communities and their history.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><em>Roumeli</em> describes Fermor&rsquo;s travels around Northern Greece and Macedonia. He
visits secluded and remote areas and describes the rugged countryside and how
people of these remote regions live. As he meets Sarakatsan shepherds and
spends some time with them, visits the impressive monasteries of Meteora,
attempts to track a pair of Byron&rsquo;s slippers in Missolonghi and investigates
Kravara and its secret language, he makes acute observations about these
communities and their history.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" src="/images/rumelia.jpg#right" alt="Roumelia"  />

His prose is rich, and his erudition is immense. His love for this long-lost
world is touchingly apparent. <em>Roumeli</em> is not just travel writing but a moving
celebration of Greece and its culture. Patrick Leigh Fermor is one of my
favorite authors and yet, of all of his books, this is not my favorite<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1</a></sup>.
There&rsquo;s a certain lack of focus (the whole Crete divagation, while poetic and
evocative, has little to do with the context of this book<sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">2</a></sup>), and some
musings on Greeks&rsquo; nature, while interesting, tend to run long.</p>
<p><em>Subscribe to the [newsletter][nl], the [RSS feed][rss], or follow @[nicolaiarocci][tw] on Twitter</em></p>
<div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
<hr>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1">
<p>PLF&rsquo;s <em>Mani: Travels in the Southern Peloponnese</em> and the whole <em>A Time of Gits</em>  trilogy are some of my all-time favorite travel books.
[rss]: <a href="https://nicolaiarocci.com/index.xml">https://nicolaiarocci.com/index.xml</a>
[tw]: <a href="http://twitter.com/nicolaiarocci">http://twitter.com/nicolaiarocci</a>
[nl]: <a href="https://nicolaiarocci.substack.com">https://nicolaiarocci.substack.com</a>&#160;<a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
<li id="fn:2">
<p>On Fermor&rsquo;s activity as a secret agent in Crete during WWII, I greatly appreciated <em>Ill Met by Moonglight: The Abduction of General Kreipe</em>, by W. Stanley Moss.&#160;<a href="#fnref:2" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
</ol>
</div>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Book Review: Thinking Fast and Slow</title>
      <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/book-review-thinking-fast-and-slow/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Mar 2022 07:05:25 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nicolaiarocci.com/book-review-thinking-fast-and-slow/</guid>
      <description>This book stands up to its fame. It&amp;rsquo;s chock-full of precious insights on our decision-making and behavioral processes and how and why we humans are often capable of making informed yet awful decisions. The bad news is that we can hardly avoid most of these biases, no matter how hard we try and even if we know about them. So-called experts in the field are subject to these same biases: their short-term estimates and predictions can even be pretty good, but they will fail miserably in the long term, like any other man or woman.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>This book stands up to its fame. It&rsquo;s chock-full of precious insights on our
decision-making and behavioral processes and how and why we humans are often
capable of making informed yet awful decisions. The bad news is that we can
hardly avoid most of these biases, no matter how hard we try and even if we
know about them. So-called experts in the field are subject to these same
biases: their short-term estimates and predictions can even be pretty good, but
they will fail miserably in the long term, like any other man or woman. There
are so many interesting tidbits in this text that it&rsquo;s overwhelming. Some, if
not most of them, may even fall in the ordinary sense category, but the added
value here is we are being told why they fall in that class. Because I came to
reading it so late (it was published in 2011), this book might be the main
reason why some of these concepts are now common sense.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" src="/images/thinking-fast-and-slow.jpg#right" alt="Thinking Fast and Slow"  />

The text is too long, though. It&rsquo;s almost 700 pages, and I suspect they could
have been half of that without sacrificing content. Kahneman won the Nobel
Prize for his behavioral finance and hedonic psychology research. He spent
a career researching these topics, and most of the biases and behaviors
mentioned in the text are his discoveries (with colleagues.) He tries hard to
be popular and mostly succeeds, especially in the first, second and third
parts, where the juiciest ah-ha moments await the reader. The rest is more
about his prospect theory and behavioral finance; it probably holds the most
relevant conclusions for an informed audience but suffers from repetitions and
perhaps too many examples, riddles and tests.</p>
<p>By pure coincidence, just the other day, 3 Quarks Daily <a href="https://3quarksdaily.com/3quarksdaily/2022/03/daniel-kahneman-thinking-fast-and-slow.html">posted</a> a 2011
Google Talk in which Kahneman was invited to talk about Thinking Fast and Slow.
I found it very good at explaining, let&rsquo;s say, the first part of the book
(System 1 and System 2, their interactions and their influence on everyday
human behavior.) Examples and stories mentioned are from the book. My
suggestion is first to watch the speech. It&rsquo;s 45 minutes well spent, then
decide if you want to invest in the book.</p>

<div style="position: relative; padding-bottom: 56.25%; height: 0; overflow: hidden;">
  <iframe src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/CjVQJdIrDJ0" style="position: absolute; top: 0; left: 0; width: 100%; height: 100%; border:0;" allowfullscreen title="YouTube Video"></iframe>
</div>

<p><em>Subscribe to the <a href="https://nicolaiarocci.substack.com">newsletter</a>, the <a href="https://nicolaiarocci.com/index.xml">RSS feed</a>, or follow @<a href="http://twitter.com/nicolaiarocci">nicolaiarocci</a> on Twitter</em></p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Book Review: Eichmann in Jerusalem. A Report on the Banality of Evil</title>
      <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/book-review-eichmann-in-jerusalem.-a-report-on-the-banality-of-evil/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Feb 2022 07:05:25 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nicolaiarocci.com/book-review-eichmann-in-jerusalem.-a-report-on-the-banality-of-evil/</guid>
      <description>This book is not about the famous, daring, and in some ways fortunate capture of Eichmann in Buenos Aires in 1960, nor about the covert transfer of the Nazi officer to Israel. Instead, the volume recounts the 1961 trial in Jerusalem, which ended with the defendant being sentenced to death. Hannah Arendt followed the trial as a correspondent for The New Yorker. She took notes, studied the papers, and reconstructed the many witnesses&amp;rsquo; personal stories.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>This book is not about the famous, daring, and in some ways fortunate capture
of Eichmann in Buenos Aires in 1960, nor about the covert transfer of the Nazi
officer to Israel. Instead, the volume recounts the 1961 trial in Jerusalem,
which ended with the defendant being sentenced to death. Hannah Arendt followed
the trial as a correspondent for <em>The New Yorker</em>. She took notes, studied the
papers, and reconstructed the many witnesses&rsquo; personal stories. Her work was
first published as articles in <em>The New Yorker</em> and later revised and updated
as a book.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" src="/images/eichmann-in-jerusalem.jpg#right" alt="Eichmann in Jerusalem, a Report on the Banality of Evil"  />

Following the trial hearings, we are taken back to the years of the advent of
Nazism in Germany. The regime first incited and then actively advocated
anti-Semitism, a historically present sentiment in many parts of Europe and
beyond. These are the years of establishing the SS and other Nazi police
forces. Eichmann, penniless and unemployed, managed to join the SS ranks thanks
to an acquaintance. He was appointed to the Jewish emigration office, an
assignment he took seriously. He read books and became an &ldquo;expert on the Jewish
question&rdquo;. Over time, Eichmann career progressed as his office duties evolved,
from emigration to deportation and extermination. However, despite the
undoubted successes, Eichmann never managed to reach the highest levels of the
military hierarchy. He could never get close to his idol, the Führer. For what
reason?</p>
<p>Why couldn&rsquo;t he ever get into Hitler&rsquo;s inner circle? The critical point of
<em>Eichman in Jerusalem</em> is, I think, precisely the answer to this question.
According to Arendt&rsquo;s reconstruction, Eichmann was and always remained
a mediocre man. He was undoubtedly a good bureaucrat, an expert in organization
and logistics, but light years away from the brilliant and appealing person he
always aspired to be. Arendt makes no discount, reporting the many moments
during the process in which Eichmann reveals his true stature.</p>
<p>The banality of evil of the title lies precisely in this aspect: a modest
bureaucrat who merely fulfils his job slavishly, without questioning his role,
as a cog in the machine, can do evil. The Nazi machine exterminated six million
Jews, and the office Eichmann directed was the fulcrum of that tireless
activity. And yet, the man in charge, and with him, his subordinates, for the
most part, were ordinary people who carried out their tasks heads down, no
questions asked. How many Germans (and collaborators in the occupied countries)
did the same thing in those years?</p>
<p>Since its publication, the book has not ceased to raise controversy,
particularly concerning the role of Jewish Councils of Elders (Judenrat),
organizational structures imposed by Nazi Germany. Arendt proposes that they
actively collaborated in drawing up the lists of Jews to be deported. In any
case, <em>Eichmann in Jerusalem</em> is an exceptionally documented and well-argued
historical research. It is worth reading, especially so in our time when the
memory of time passed tends to fade away.</p>
<p><em>Subscribe to the <a href="https://nicolaiarocci.substack.com">newsletter</a>, the <a href="https://nicolaiarocci.com/index.xml">RSS feed</a>, or follow @<a href="http://twitter.com/nicolaiarocci">nicolaiarocci</a> on Twitter</em></p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Book Review: Finnish Fairy Tales</title>
      <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/book-review-finnish-fairy-tales/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 04 Jan 2022 07:05:25 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nicolaiarocci.com/book-review-finnish-fairy-tales/</guid>
      <description>Over the years, Iperborea, one of my favorite Italian publishers, has been publishing an unofficial Nordic Tales series. Their renowned nordic fiction series includes one fairy tale volume per year, usually published in December, just for Christmas. The first book was Lapland Tales in 2014, and then they continued with Danish, Icelandic, Swedish, Faroe, Norwegian, Greenlandic and then Finnish in 2021. I&amp;rsquo;ve been greedily reading each one of them, usually as my last book of the year.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Over the years, Iperborea, one of my favorite Italian publishers, has been
publishing an unofficial Nordic Tales series. Their renowned nordic fiction
series includes one fairy tale volume per year, usually published in December,
just for Christmas. The first book was Lapland Tales in 2014, and then they
continued with Danish, Icelandic, Swedish, Faroe,  Norwegian, Greenlandic and
then Finnish in 2021. I&rsquo;ve been greedily reading each one of them, usually as
my last book of the year. This year I was a little bit late, as <a href="https://nicolaiarocci.com/three-good-books-i-read-in-2021/">reported</a>.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" src="/images/fiabe-finlandesi.jpg#right" alt="Fiabe finlandesi"  />

Until now, 2020&rsquo;s Greenlandic Legends has been my favorite, mainly because it&rsquo;s
partly different from the others, which all share a common Scandinavian
cultural background. In this regard, this year&rsquo;s Finnish Tales is even more
remarkable. Quoting the short, excellent final essay by the translators Giorgia
Ferrari and Sanna Maria Martin<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1</a></sup>:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Within the Nordic panorama, Finland holds a unique position and has a precise
identity: entering Finnish culture means coming into contact with the
Finno-Ugric world, starting from the language, which has nothing to do with
the Scandinavian ones, which are only geographically close. At the same time,
Finland is anything but an island separated from its surroundings: its
particular position between East and West has made it, if anything,
a borderland, a point of intersection between different cultures, enriching
it with influences from both directions. And this can only be evident even in
popular tales.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Indeed, in these tales, you find echoes of myths and tropes from Scandinavian
culture but always intertwined with unique Finnish themes. Notable examples
are:</p>
<ul>
<li>The <em>tietäjä</em>, whose supernatural power arises from great knowledge.</li>
<li>The <em>vetehinen</em>, a male (!!!) water spirit of the forest.</li>
<li>The <em>syöjätär</em>, the devourer, or the &ldquo;wicked mother.&rdquo;</li>
<li>The <em>nimikkopuu</em>, a tree planted on somebody&rsquo;s birth; tied to their destiny</li>
<li>The shamanic rituals, often associated with the use of magical words and songs</li>
</ul>
<p>The principal collector of Finnish folklore was Eero Salmelainen (1830-1867),
who published four seminal titles from which all of the stories in Finnish
Tales are selected. Of course, Grimm&rsquo;s influence is evident in Salmelainen&rsquo;s
work. Remarkably though, Salmelainen started his collection forty years later
than the Grimms. One reason might be that until then (and up until now, I might
add), Finnish folklore has always been hiding in the shadow of Kalevala&rsquo;s
poetic poetry.</p>
<p><em>Subscribe to the [newsletter][nl], the [RSS feed][rss], or follow @[nicolaiarocci][tw] on Twitter</em></p>
<div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
<hr>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1">
<p>Short, informative essays enrich each one of Iperborea&rsquo;s Nordic Tales volumes. These are essential in framing the content within the correct background, outlining the links between Nordic cultures, and revealing the sources. Take the Kalevala. I have had it in my library since many years ago, but I didn&rsquo;t correlate it with Finnish folklore until I saw it mentioned in the essay.
[rss]: <a href="https://nicolaiarocci.com/index.xml">https://nicolaiarocci.com/index.xml</a>
[tw]: <a href="http://twitter.com/nicolaiarocci">http://twitter.com/nicolaiarocci</a>
[nl]: <a href="https://nicolaiarocci.substack.com">https://nicolaiarocci.substack.com</a>&#160;<a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
</ol>
</div>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Book Review: Consider the Lobster</title>
      <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/book-review-consider-the-lobster/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Dec 2021 07:05:25 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nicolaiarocci.com/book-review-consider-the-lobster/</guid>
      <description>I found a Consider the Lobster review on Goodreads that almost precisely matches my thoughts on DFW and the book. Hence, given the lazy Christmas-break mood I am in right now, I am conceding myself the right to copy-paste and edit David&amp;rsquo;s review right away.
I know of nobody else who writes as thoughtfully and intelligently as DFW. That he manages to write so informatively, with humor and genuine wit, on almost any subject under the sun is mind-blowing – it&amp;rsquo;s also why I am willing to forgive his occasional stylistic excesses.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I found a Consider the Lobster <a href="https://www.goodreads.com/review/show/14143044">review</a> on Goodreads that almost precisely
matches my thoughts on DFW and the book. Hence, given the lazy Christmas-break
mood I am in right now, I am conceding myself the right to copy-paste and edit
David&rsquo;s review right away.</p>
<hr>
<p>I know of nobody else who writes as thoughtfully and intelligently as DFW. That
he manages to write so informatively, with humor and genuine wit, on almost any
subject under the sun is mind-blowing – it&rsquo;s also why I am willing to forgive
his occasional stylistic excesses. (Can you spell &lsquo;footnote&rsquo;?) You may not have
a strong interest in lobsters or pornography, but the essays in question are
terrific. The reporting on Ziegler and McCain is outstanding, heartbreakingly
so, because it makes the relative shallowness of most reporting painfully
evident.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" src="/images/consider-the-lobster.jpg#right" alt="Consider the Lobster"  />

Yes, I know all about his weaknesses - the digressions, the rampant footnote
abuse, the flaunting of his extraordinary erudition. I know all this, and
I don&rsquo;t care. Because when he is in top form, there&rsquo;s nobody else I would
instead read. The man is hilarious; I think he&rsquo;s a mensch, and I don&rsquo;t believe
he parades his erudition to prove how smart he is. I think he can&rsquo;t help
himself - it&rsquo;s a consequence of his wide-ranging curiosity. At heart, he&rsquo;s
a geek but a charming, hyper-articulate geek. Who is almost frighteningly
bright.</p>
<hr>
<p>If you have never read DFW, my advice would be to start with his non-fiction,
which is way more accessible than his fiction (with the notable exception of
The Brook of the System, which was my first adored DFW reading.)</p>
<p><em>Subscribe to the <a href="https://nicolaiarocci.substack.com">newsletter</a>, the <a href="https://nicolaiarocci.com/index.xml">RSS feed</a>, or follow @<a href="http://twitter.com/nicolaiarocci">nicolaiarocci</a> on Twitter</em></p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Book Review: About the Meaning of Life</title>
      <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/book-review-about-the-meaning-of-life/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 26 Dec 2021 07:05:25 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nicolaiarocci.com/book-review-about-the-meaning-of-life/</guid>
      <description>I&amp;rsquo;m not a regular philosophy reader, much less of self-improvement guides. I&amp;rsquo;m wary of the latter and too ignorant for the former. Yet, theologian Vito Mancuso has intrigued me for some time. I followed his podcast on the &amp;ldquo;Four Masters of Life&amp;rdquo;1 and found it excellent. In it, Mancuso discusses his four tutelary deities: &amp;ldquo;Socrates, the educator. Buddha, the physician. Confucius, the politician. Jesus, the prophet.&amp;rdquo; I also listened to some TV interviews where I always found him fascinating.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I&rsquo;m not a regular philosophy reader, much less of self-improvement guides. I&rsquo;m
wary of the latter and too ignorant for the former. Yet, theologian Vito
Mancuso has intrigued me for some time. I followed his podcast on the &ldquo;Four
Masters of Life&rdquo;<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1</a></sup> and found it excellent. In it, Mancuso discusses his four
tutelary deities: &ldquo;Socrates, the educator. Buddha, the physician. Confucius,
the politician. Jesus, the prophet.&rdquo; I also listened to some TV interviews
where I always found him fascinating. In short, there was enough to make me
decide to read some of his work. From the back cover of the book:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>We know perfectly well what we want to have - wealth, pleasure, power - but
we no longer know who we want to be. In the severe crisis in which we are
immersed, we continually need adversaries to define our identities. We often
find ourselves, enemies, even of ourselves, in a sort of permanent inner war.
The philosophy of Vito Mancuso is a precious anchor in these difficult times:
renewing in us the desire for ancient reflections, it shows us the way to go
back to the deep roots of our consciousness and teaches us how the meaning
and direction of our life on this Earth must be rebuilt in small steps, day
by day, in the awareness that we are in the presence of something more
important than ourselves. Only in this way will we enter into harmony with
the logic that determines our path and love that natural simplicity within us
is the real secret to a worthy life, a life worth living, an authentic life.</p>
</blockquote>
<p><img loading="lazy" src="/images/a-proposito-del-senso-della-vita.jpg#right" alt="A proposito del senso della vita"  />

Ambitious, to say the least, especially considering that we are talking about
a short essay of a hundred pages at most. In the preface, we learn that the
content of this book is nothing more than the revised and expanded transcript
of a speech given by Mancuso during a summer event at a city library. Yet, we
should not be misled. About the Meaning of Life is not superficial. Instead, it
is a well-exposed and reasoned synthesis of Vito Mancuso&rsquo;s general thought on
the meaning of life, a theme to which the author has dedicated much of his
work. Mancuso&rsquo;s philosophy is in some ways original, especially in its
courageous detachment from the dominant Western Catholic doctrine from which he
comes (and to which he tends to return.)<sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">2</a></sup> The in-depth and never prejudicially
critical study of alternative philosophies, like those of the far East, is
evident and leaves its mark. The writing is always fluent, the reading pleasant
and rarely tricky. On rare occasions when we feel the lack of footholds, the
footnotes (pun intended) aid with valuable suggestions for further study. Yes,
a short text, but with dense content and lots of food for thought. It deserves
more readings. Some of Mancuso&rsquo;s major works, like the Four Masters of Life
mentioned above, are certainly recommended for a deeper investigation<sup id="fnref:3"><a href="#fn:3" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">3</a></sup>.</p>
<p><em>Subscribe to the [newsletter][nl], the [RSS feed][rss], or follow @[nicolaiarocci][tw] on Twitter</em></p>
<div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
<hr>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1">
<p>The first episode, <em>Socrates</em>, is available <a href="https://www.raiplaysound.it/audio/2020/11/quotChe-cosapos195168-un-maestro-I-quattro-cardini-della-spiritualit195160quot-con--Vito-Mancuso---1-puntata---Socrate-17ae3281-4536-4ee1-be21-248b347e8849.html">here</a> (Italian)&#160;<a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
<li id="fn:2">
<p>Further research reveals that his line of thought has received some <a href="https://it.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vito_Mancuso#Critiche">relevant criticism</a>, in the catholic circles especially.&#160;<a href="#fnref:2" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
<li id="fn:3">
<p>Unfortunately, I am not aware of English editions of Mancuso&rsquo;s works.
[rss]: <a href="https://nicolaiarocci.com/index.xml">https://nicolaiarocci.com/index.xml</a>
[tw]: <a href="http://twitter.com/nicolaiarocci">http://twitter.com/nicolaiarocci</a>
[nl]: <a href="https://nicolaiarocci.substack.com">https://nicolaiarocci.substack.com</a>&#160;<a href="#fnref:3" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
</ol>
</div>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Book Review: A useless man</title>
      <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/book-review-a-useless-man/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 04 Dec 2021 07:05:25 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nicolaiarocci.com/book-review-a-useless-man/</guid>
      <description>Sait Faik Abasıyanık is an acclaimed Turkish storyteller. A useless man is a collection of short stories that spans nearly two decades of the author&amp;rsquo;s output, offering a glimpse into his imaginative and troubled mind. His overflowing love for others (even sensual, with a preference for street kids) combined with a &amp;ldquo;mal de vivre&amp;rdquo; that pushes him towards self-destruction are apparent.
His passion for the most popular areas of Istanbul and, in contrast, the atavistic nostalgia for the simple life of the nearby fishermen islets exudes from these stories, which often run similar one after another.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Sait Faik Abasıyanık is an acclaimed Turkish storyteller. <em>A useless man</em> is
a collection of short stories that spans nearly two decades of the author&rsquo;s
output, offering a glimpse into his imaginative and troubled mind. His
overflowing love for others (even sensual, with a preference for street kids)
combined with a &ldquo;mal de vivre&rdquo; that pushes him towards self-destruction are
apparent.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" src="/images/a-useless-man.jpg#right" alt="A useless man"  />

His passion for the most popular areas of Istanbul and, in contrast, the
atavistic nostalgia for the simple life of the nearby fishermen islets exudes
from these stories, which often run similar one after another. The composition
is sometimes complex, making the text hard to parse and comprehend. Several
novels are noteworthy, though, especially those narrated in third-person, where
the narrator is not involved. The author is holding back his poetic prowess and
the resulting text is more linear. Notable examples are <em>The samovar</em>, on the
elaboration of mourning, and <em>A story for two</em>, a touching story of friendship
between a bird and a fisherman. Some first-person ones are exceptional, too.
For example, <em>Milk</em> is Sait Faik&rsquo;s worthy tribute to Proust&rsquo;s madeleine. One
short story on the protagonist&rsquo;s struggle with a street kid was profoundly
touching.</p>
<p>I bought this book because I wanted to know more about Istanbul, a city I know
little or nothing about, and its people. I am only partially satisfied. Reading
it, I realized that the author was, of course,  not addressing the foreign
reader at all. He was writing, of course, for his people, the citizens of
Istanbul, and himself.</p>
<p><em>Subscribe to the <a href="https://nicolaiarocci.substack.com">newsletter</a>, the <a href="https://nicolaiarocci.com/index.xml">RSS feed</a>, or follow @<a href="http://twitter.com/nicolaiarocci">nicolaiarocci</a> on Twitter</em></p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Book Review: Endurance, Shackleton&#39;s Incredible Voyage</title>
      <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/book-review-endurance-shackletons-incredible-voyage/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 28 Nov 2021 07:05:25 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nicolaiarocci.com/book-review-endurance-shackletons-incredible-voyage/</guid>
      <description>Of all the stories of maritime adventures I&amp;rsquo;ve read, that of the Endurance, masterfully told by Alfred Lansing in this book, is the most incredible and shocking. Unbelievable to say, given the premise (a crew of 28 men stranded on the Antarctic pack, camped on floating slabs of ice hundreds of miles from any human settlement, at the gates of the Antarctic winter), but the story does not end in tragedy.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Of all the stories of maritime adventures I&rsquo;ve read, that of the Endurance,
masterfully told by Alfred Lansing in this book, is the most incredible and
shocking. Unbelievable to say, given the premise (a crew of 28 men stranded on
the Antarctic pack, camped on floating slabs of ice hundreds of miles from any
human settlement, at the gates of the Antarctic winter), but the story does not
end in tragedy. The original expedition failed, but what followed the capture
of Endurance (never was the name of a ship more prophetic) by the Antarctic ice
borders on the impossible, if not the miraculous.</p>
<p>The merits of the expedition leader, Sir Ernest Shackleton, are, of course,
spectacular. Every decision he made and his care in leading the crew during
that year and a half of unspeakable suffering, sacrifice and hardship led them
all to safety. There was no shortage of hotheads and slackers, which made the
successful outcome even more impressive. Shackleton himself was not a saint.
For the sake of fame, success and money, he planned an expedition that had very
little chance of success, in which death was by far the most probable result.
And yet, he planned every detail with great care, never doubting the final
victory. More than anything else, what is surprising in this story is that no
saviour finally came to rescue the crew. They saved themselves. After more than
a year camped on drifting ice floes, driven by sea currents and Antarctic
winds, they finally landed on the deserted and unforgiving Elephant isle.
Shackleton once again had to take to the sea, leaving most of his men behind,
to cross the terrible Drake Channel on little more than an open lifeboat. This
one feature alone, the victorious crossing of the world-renown troubled waters
of Drake Channel on a lifeboat, was something never attempted before, nor ever
repeated afterwards, and would have been enough for history books. Once
miraculously landed in South Georgia, Shackleton and his men were not done yet.
They had to cross snow-capped mountains never before touched by man to reach an
outpost of whale fishers and finally set sail in a ship to return to retrieve
the men marooned on Elephant Island.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" src="/images/endurance.jpg#right" alt="Endurance book cover"  />

Every moment of this story feels like an epic, fictional movie, but it&rsquo;s not.
It is reality as experienced firsthand by actual human beings. Alfred Lansing
has reconstructed all these events with great care, drawing mainly on the many
diaries kept by the crew, Shackleton himself included, and interviewing the few
survivors still alive. Lansing&rsquo;s work is precise, methodical, careful. Still,
the result is always smooth and at the same time dry, never yielding to
hyperbole or exaltation, always close to the facts, which on the other hand,
certainly do not need enrichment. A fantastic story, beautifully told.</p>
<p><em>Subscribe to the <a href="https://nicolaiarocci.substack.com">newsletter</a>, the <a href="https://nicolaiarocci.com/index.xml">RSS feed</a>, or follow @<a href="http://twitter.com/nicolaiarocci">nicolaiarocci</a> on Twitter</em></p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Book Review: Mathematics is politics</title>
      <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/book-review-mathematics-is-politics/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 25 Nov 2021 07:05:25 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nicolaiarocci.com/book-review-mathematics-is-politics/</guid>
      <description>Mathematics as the study of relationships: in this aspect lies the similarity and affinity with politics. And then the need in both cases to proceed with stubbornness and trust, without fearing error which, as in all difficult things, is not only lying in wait but inherent, and often, when it is discovered, it is the stimulus and engine of new successes and goals. Hence the need to respect rules and (not or, mind you) the compelling need for revolutions.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Mathematics as the study of relationships: in this aspect lies the similarity
and affinity with politics. And then the need in both cases to proceed with
stubbornness and trust, without fearing error which, as in all difficult
things, is not only lying in wait but inherent, and often, when it is
discovered, it is the stimulus and engine of new successes and goals. Hence the
need to respect rules and (not or, mind you) the compelling need for
revolutions. The parallel narration of the author&rsquo;s life and the change, over
the years, of her own beliefs and points of view, makes this short essay more
credible and streamlines the story.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Mathematics was my apprenticeship to revolution because it taught me to
distrust absolute truths and unquestionable authorities. Democracy and
mathematics, from a political point of view, are similar: like all creative
processes, they can&rsquo;t stand remaining unchanged.</p>
</blockquote>
<p><img loading="lazy" src="/images/matematica-politica.jpg#right" alt="La matematica è politica"  />

Not a book for everyone, perhaps, but suitable to those who like to think and
be challenged with ideas. Background theme to which I am susceptible: the
necessity for school to illuminate our existences. I wouldn&rsquo;t say I liked the
frequent references to contingent situations in Italian politics. I bought an
short essay on the interconnections between mathematics and politics; I expect
it to make me fly high, far away from the quarrels and events of daily
politics. Also, sometimes the similarities between the two fields seem a bit
too far fetched.</p>
<p>I don&rsquo;t think this book is currently available in English. I read it in the
original Italian edition.</p>
<p><em>Subscribe to the <a href="https://nicolaiarocci.substack.com">newsletter</a>, the <a href="https://nicolaiarocci.com/index.xml">RSS feed</a>, or follow @<a href="http://twitter.com/nicolaiarocci">nicolaiarocci</a> on Twitter</em></p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Book Review: King and Emperor, A New Life of Charlemagne</title>
      <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/book-review-king-and-emperor-a-new-life-of-charlemagne/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 31 Oct 2021 07:05:25 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nicolaiarocci.com/book-review-king-and-emperor-a-new-life-of-charlemagne/</guid>
      <description>In this scholarly biography by Janet L. Nelson, Charlemagne is stripped back from the years of mythologizing and idolizing that have occurred since his death. He is presented as distinctly human, and this book is the first time I have felt I could reasonably understand Charlemagne as the man he was, not the man he has since been painted to be. Moreover, Nelson is excellent in her discussions of Charlemagne&amp;rsquo;s wives and their roles.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>In this scholarly biography by Janet L. Nelson, Charlemagne is stripped back
from the years of mythologizing and idolizing that have occurred since his
death. He is presented as distinctly human, and this book is the first time
I have felt I could reasonably understand Charlemagne as the man he was, not
the man he has since been painted to be. Moreover, Nelson is excellent in her
discussions of Charlemagne&rsquo;s wives and their roles. For example, the
commonplace assumption that Fastrada was a cruel person is questioned, and she
emerges as a capable companion and queen instead.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" src="/images/king-and-emperor.jpg#right" alt="Kind and Emperor: A New Life of Charlemagne"  />

Nelson is firm in her dissection of the source material. However, it can be
a challenge to weave critical discussion of sources and fluid narrative, and at
times this book leans a little on the dry side. Nelson does not speculate; she
instead focuses on what we know or can be reasonably inferred from the sources.
The downside is that some of the more exciting episodes from Charlemagne&rsquo;s life
are glossed over: the 792AD rebellion of Charlemagne&rsquo;s eldest son, Pippin,
receives only three pages of discussion, whereas Charlemagne&rsquo;s canal-building
project, which follows, receives double that. Personally, as a general reader
rather than a historian, I would have preferred more on the &ldquo;interesting bits&rdquo;
of Charlemagne&rsquo;s reign, but a more academic reader may not mind.</p>
<p>Overall, this is an excellent biography, and I would recommend it to an
informed reader. The scholarly attention to sources might deter the casual
reader, but the motivated ones will take profit from the effort.</p>
<p><em>Subscribe to the <a href="https://nicolaiarocci.substack.com">newsletter</a>, the <a href="https://nicolaiarocci.com/index.xml">RSS feed</a>, or follow @<a href="http://twitter.com/nicolaiarocci">nicolaiarocci</a> on Twitter</em></p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Book Review: Language of the Spirit, An Introduction to Classical Music</title>
      <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/book-review-language-of-the-spirit-an-introduction-to-classical-music/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 Oct 2021 07:05:25 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nicolaiarocci.com/book-review-language-of-the-spirit-an-introduction-to-classical-music/</guid>
      <description>In this introduction to classical music, Jan Swafford explains the different musical periods and their differences. Each period has its introductory chapter, followed by chapters dedicated to the most influential composers of the era. The choice is comprehensive and well cared for, with the most relevant names well-investigated both in biography and works. For each composer, Swafford also offers some listening suggestions. Biographies thicken as we get into the contemporary era.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>In this introduction to classical music, Jan Swafford explains the different
musical periods and their differences. Each period has its introductory
chapter, followed by chapters dedicated to the most influential composers of
the era. The choice is comprehensive and well cared for, with the most relevant
names well-investigated both in biography and works. For each composer,
Swafford also offers some listening suggestions. Biographies thicken as we get
into the contemporary era. Here, some are limited to just a page or two while
others, obviously those of the author&rsquo;s preferred composers, remain as thorough
as those of the older periods.</p>
<p>The introductory chapters to various musical eras (Baroque, Classical,
Romantic, Modernism and beyond) were, for me, the most interesting ones. In
these chapters, Swafford explains the changes in society, technology and taste
that influenced the musical styles, themselves a revelation of the spirit of
the time. In this sense, Language of the Spirit is not just a classical music
book but also a historical essay, often sharp and full of intriguing
information on the periods crossed.</p>
<p>The author&rsquo;s effort in using simple language, understandable even to the
uninitiated, is evident, and the goal is well achieved, for the most part.
Sometimes, however, albeit very rarely, it goes into the technical, where
someone like me, who lacks a solid background, might struggle.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" src="/images/language-of-the-spirit.jpg#right" alt="Language of the Spirit: An Introduction to Classical Music"  />

The recommended listenings are excellent. For every single one, I wanted to
stop reading and listen to it. That&rsquo;s the approach recommended by the author,
but I never managed, too eager to finish the chapter. I then tried to make
a Spotify playlist out of them, failing miserably because of my pedantry;
I only wanted the suggested executions, often missing on Spotify.</p>
<p>Language of the Spirit is a recommended introduction to classical music and its
history. It allows the reader to collect a phenomenal list of composers and
their works while, at the same time, delving into the momentous changes faced
by (mainly European) society over the last few centuries.</p>
<p><em>Subscribe to the <a href="https://nicolaiarocci.substack.com">newsletter</a>, the <a href="https://nicolaiarocci.com/index.xml">RSS feed</a>, or follow @<a href="http://twitter.com/nicolaiarocci">nicolaiarocci</a> on Twitter</em></p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Book Review: Nausea</title>
      <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/book-review-nausea/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Sep 2021 07:05:25 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nicolaiarocci.com/book-review-nausea/</guid>
      <description>Antoine Roquentin, the protagonist of the novel, is a former adventurer who has been living for three years in Bouville, a fictional French seaport town, researching the life of an 18th-century diplomat. During his previous life around the world, Antoine has seen many places, met many interesting people, done exciting things. For the last three years, however, he&amp;rsquo;s been alone in Bouville. He has no friends and no desire to make some or meet anyone.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Antoine Roquentin, the protagonist of the novel, is a former adventurer who has
been living for three years in Bouville, a fictional French seaport town,
researching the life of an 18th-century diplomat. During his previous life
around the world, Antoine has seen many places, met many interesting people,
done exciting things. For the last three years, however, he&rsquo;s been alone in
Bouville. He has no friends and no desire to make some or meet anyone. He&rsquo;s
interested in nothing, not even in his work that he keeps neglecting. His days
are mostly spent walking around town, listening to conversations and observing
people around him. A &ldquo;sweeting sickness&rdquo; he calls nausea increasingly impinges
on almost everything he does and enjoys.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Something has happened to me, I can&rsquo;t doubt it any more. It came as an
illness does, not like an ordinary certainty, not like anything evident. It
came cunningly, little by little; I felt a little strange, a little put out,
that&rsquo;s all. Once established it never moved, it stayed quiet, and I was able
to persuade myself that nothing was the matter with me, that it was a false
alarm. And now, it&rsquo;s blossoming.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>He has a relationship with a woman, but it is exclusively carnal: the two
exchange almost no words. Selt-Taught Man, an individual who spends his time at
the local library reading all books in alphabetical order, is one of his few
acquaintances. When Self-Taught Man invites Antoine for lunch, he notes on his
diary: &ldquo;I had as much desire to eat with him as I had to hang myself.&rdquo; Antoine
has no interest in relationships. They take too much effort.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>When you live alone you no longer know what it is to tell a story: the
plausible disappears at the same time as the friends.</p>
</blockquote>
<p><img loading="lazy" src="/images/nausea.jpg#right" alt="Nausea, by Jean Paul Sartre"  />

Antoine feels like he never lived but only existed. These days, we would
probably call Antoine&rsquo;s sickness with a different name, depression maybe. If
you ever felt like Antoine, Nausea is going to be a difficult read. If you
didn&rsquo;t, I suspect it will be hard for you to feel any sympathy for the
protagonist. Sartre writes beautifully, with razor-sharp precision. Despite his
attempts to refuse it, he won the Nobel Prize in Literature in 1964. Nausea was
Sartre&rsquo;s debut novel, and he always considered it his best fictional work.
Nausea, by Jean-Paul Sartre, is a challenging but rewarding read. I think
Sartre goes straight amongst the masters at describing the human condition.</p>
<p><em>Subscribe to the <a href="https://nicolaiarocci.substack.com">newsletter</a>, the <a href="https://nicolaiarocci.com/index.xml">RSS feed</a>, or follow @<a href="http://twitter.com/nicolaiarocci">nicolaiarocci</a> on Twitter</em></p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Book Review: Proud tobea Flyer</title>
      <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/book-review-proud-tobea-flyer/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 28 Aug 2021 07:05:25 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nicolaiarocci.com/book-review-proud-tobea-flyer/</guid>
      <description>I happened across this book by pure chance. After having ice cream in our favourite place in Milano Marittima, my wife and I visited a small street market with all kinds of booths. Of course, there was a used book stand toward which I immediately gravitated. A quick scan revealed nothing of interest, so I moved along. But Serena, who arrived at the booth moments after I left, knew more. A simple, no-frills, cardboard-covered book which carried a giant PROUD 2BEA FLYER title on the spine caught her attention.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I happened across this book by pure chance. After having ice cream in our
favourite place in Milano Marittima, my wife and I visited a small street
market with all kinds of booths. Of course, there was a used book stand toward
which I immediately gravitated. A quick scan revealed nothing of interest, so
I moved along. But Serena, who arrived at the booth moments after I left, knew
more. A simple, no-frills, cardboard-covered book which carried a giant PROUD
2BEA FLYER title on the spine caught her attention. As she opened it and
flipped through the pages, she immediately knew this was a unique item I would
love to have, so she bought it (for cheap!) along with another one, then let it
slip into a shopping bag, and then reached an unaware me.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" src="/images/proudtobeaflyer1.jpg#right" alt="Proud 2bea flyer sample 1"  />

When I spotted the book lying in the bag, I inquired about it. Serena took it
out of the bag and handed it over to me with a smile. Imagine my surprise,
amazement and gratitude when I started browsing through hundreds of beautiful
works of art, all in the form of club flyers from all ages and musical genres.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>In what can best be described a well of hip Club Culture Graphics, Proud
2 B a Flyer rounds up the most exciting party announcements made for the
street. Before the explosion of popular musical forms in the past 40 years
art associated with music has been in corporate hands, with music companies
and commercial artists, but the club flyer has changed all that. The
evolution of the club flyer mirrors the musical movements that have used its
simple direct from to capture the imagination of their audiences. The early
techno scene employed flyers to great effect and diverse musical scenes
caught on quickly. Proud 2BEA Flyer brilliantly documents the flyer stylings
of the electronica scene and also includes special sections featuring Jazz,
Hip Hop and Brazilian music. Other fascinating selections are found in
chapters such as Drawing, Series, Unusual Shapes and Regular Nights. (<a href="https://www.hoepli.it/libro/proud-2bea-flyer/9788886416474.html">source</a>)</p>
</blockquote>
<p><img loading="lazy" src="/images/proudtobeaflyer2.jpg#right" alt="Proud 2bea flyer sample 2"  />

And indeed, this is an excellent collection of inspiring, mesmerizing works<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1</a></sup>.
No text, just flyers. I have never been much of a  clubbing person, but
I always followed the music, of course, and was fascinated by the graphical
world around it. This book brings back memories of an age now gone when there
were no smartphones, and you only happened to know about an event when and if
you were lucky enough to be in the right place at the right time, to have
a chance to come across one of these street flyers.</p>
<p><em>Subscribe to the [newsletter][nl], the [RSS feed][rss], or follow @[nicolaiarocci][tw] on Twitter</em></p>
<div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
<hr>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1">
<p>I am sure my friend <a href="https://emmaboshi.net/">Emmaboshi</a> would love this special item. Some research suggests that the author, Matteo Sola, might be from Bologna, the same place where Emma practices his art, so maybe he knows about this book, or perhaps personally knows the author.
[rss]: <a href="https://nicolaiarocci.com/index.xml">https://nicolaiarocci.com/index.xml</a>
[tw]: <a href="http://twitter.com/nicolaiarocci">http://twitter.com/nicolaiarocci</a>
[nl]: <a href="https://nicolaiarocci.substack.com">https://nicolaiarocci.substack.com</a>&#160;<a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
</ol>
</div>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Book Review: Nomadland</title>
      <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/book-review-nomadland/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 21 Aug 2021 07:05:25 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nicolaiarocci.com/book-review-nomadland/</guid>
      <description>Some call them homeless. The new nomads refer to themselves as &amp;lsquo;houseless&amp;rsquo;. Many took to the road after their savings were obliterated by the Great Recession. To keep their gas tanks and bellies full, they work long hours at hard, physical jobs. In a time of flat wages and rising housing costs, they have unshackled themselves from rent and mortgages as a way to get by. They are surviving America.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<blockquote>
<p>Some call them homeless. The new nomads refer to themselves as &lsquo;houseless&rsquo;.
Many took to the road after their savings were obliterated by the Great
Recession. To keep their gas tanks and bellies full, they work long hours at
hard, physical jobs. In a time of flat wages and rising housing costs, they
have unshackled themselves from rent and mortgages as a way to get by. They
are surviving America.</p>
</blockquote>
<p><img loading="lazy" src="/images/nomadland_book_cover.jpg#right" alt="Nomadland book cover"  />

Jessica Bruder is a journalist. For three years, she followed the lives of
a group of nomads who live in their RVs or even in their cars, moving from one
seasonal work to the next in their pursuit to survive the collapse of their own
personal American Dream. Her writing is dry, concise, with little room for
personal feelings or ramblings, to the point that, at times, she sounds
distant, almost detached from the events being told. That isn&rsquo;t the case, as
you can tell by the second half of the book when she finally decides to take
the plunge and get herself a van to live herself the &ldquo;workcamper&rdquo; life. That is
a tipping point in the book. The author becomes the main character, the story
is personal, and the reader is more involved.</p>
<p>Bruder interviews many folks and followed a few of them in detail. Linda May,
amongst others, is the centrepiece of the story. Linda was 62 when she took
social security and was forced into living in a van. Most people living the
&ldquo;workcamper&rdquo; life are in what would be their retirement age. They are in their
60s, 70s and sometimes even 80s. Yet, they work very hard at their seasonal
jobs, like at Amazon warehouses as inventory scanners or in Minnesota and North
Dakota, for the seasonal harvest of sugar beets. These work experiences are
depicted with great detail. Bruder herself walked the plank and experienced how
demanding these assignments are on the body and the spirit (Amazon provides
painkillers to their aged employees). Despite all the difficulties, these
people carry on with great dignity and, often, upbeat attitude, well
represented by Linda, a lovely elderly woman.</p>
<p>I had no idea that the &ldquo;workcampers&rdquo; subculture existed in the USA. As someone
who has always been mildly fascinated by the RV life (like many others, we
sometimes fantasize about travelling the world in a camper when we retire),
I admit I was pretty shocked by this work, an engaging and very unsettling
read. I am grateful to Bruder for her hard-earned report.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>At one time there was a social contract that if you played by the rules (went
to school, got a job, and worked hard) everything would be fine. That’s no
longer true today. You can do everything right, just the way society wants
you to do it, and still end up broke, alone, and homeless.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>PS. By pure coincidence, I came across the awarded Nomandland movie only a few days
after finishing the book. It was great. At first, I was startled by the acting
of some roles. Then, by the final credits, I realized that it wasn&rsquo;t
professional actors who played those roles. It was the actual persons from the
book, Linda May included, who played themselves.</p>
<p><em>Subscribe to the <a href="https://nicolaiarocci.substack.com">newsletter</a>, the <a href="https://nicolaiarocci.com/index.xml">RSS feed</a>, or follow @<a href="http://twitter.com/nicolaiarocci">nicolaiarocci</a> on Twitter</em></p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Book Review. Eight Days in May: The Final Collapse of the Third Reich</title>
      <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/book-review.-eight-days-in-may-the-final-collapse-of-the-third-reich/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 18 Jul 2021 07:05:25 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nicolaiarocci.com/book-review.-eight-days-in-may-the-final-collapse-of-the-third-reich/</guid>
      <description>Volker Ullrich&amp;rsquo;s Eight Days in May describes the period from April 30, 1945, the day of Hitler&amp;rsquo;s suicide, to May 8, the day of signing the German capitulation, with significant jumps backwards in time and some hops in the future. We&amp;rsquo;re covering only eight days, and the dictator dies on day one. What essential events might ever have happened in such a short period? Well, many pivotal ones, as this well-researched work shows us.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Volker Ullrich&rsquo;s Eight Days in May describes the period from April 30, 1945,
the day of Hitler&rsquo;s suicide, to May 8, the day of signing the German
capitulation, with significant jumps backwards in time and some hops in the
future. We&rsquo;re covering only eight days, and the dictator dies on day one. What
essential events might ever have happened in such a short period? Well, many
pivotal ones, as this well-researched work shows us.</p>
<p>The book is merciless towards Hitler&rsquo;s heirs and not accommodating at all
towards Germans of that age in general. Reading the behaviors and things said
in those days is gruesome. Under track are the horrible consequences of war and
concentration camps. The resulting picture is that of the supreme horrors and
mistakes that humanity can reach.</p>
<p>The text focuses on the protagonists of those days, the Nazi hierarchs (not
just the most infamously well known) and their Allies and Red Army
counterparts. There are few notable exceptions, like the story of Marlene
Dietrich, already a Hollywood star, who served as an American army officer and
returned to Germany to look for her sister lost in the fog of war. To her
dismay, she found that her sister had prospered, cooperating and taking advance
of the Nazi regime. Marlene bought her sisters&rsquo; silence, and for the rest of
her life, fiercely negated the very own existence of a sister.</p>
<p>I found the part on the German population and its shocked, instinctive reaction
to the regime&rsquo;s fall particularly informative. The immediate turncoat of most,
along with the lying denial of knowing anything about the atrocities.The
disturbing (George Orwell&rsquo;s word), immediate sympathy for the Allies. Also, the
eulogy for the few who courageously conducted a desperate, clandestine and
seemingly hopeless resistance within the Reich. It is especially relevant that
the author is German.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" src="/images/eight-days-in-may.jpg#right" alt="Eight Days in May book cover"  />

This book leaves me stunned. It is always painful to read about that historical
period. The millions of deaths. The suffering. The atrocities. We need to keep
going back, walk the way over and over, never to forget, never to repeat. To
that end, Eight Days in May is a book everyone should read.</p>
<p>By May 8, 1945, Germany was a humiliated, devastated country. Most major cities
were annihilated, the economy had collapsed, and millions of people were
reduced to hunger. The contrast with today&rsquo;s Germany is mind-blowing. With the
help of the winning countries, sure, but predominantly and undoubtedly thanks
to grit and desire for rebirth, Germany resurged from the catastrophe as
a modern country and a sought-out model for democracy, economy, justice, and
reception of diverse cultures.</p>
<p><em>Subscribe to the <a href="https://nicolaiarocci.substack.com">newsletter</a>, the <a href="https://nicolaiarocci.com/index.xml">RSS feed</a>, or follow @<a href="http://twitter.com/nicolaiarocci">nicolaiarocci</a> on Twitter</em></p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Book Review: Power to the Words</title>
      <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/book-review-power-to-the-words/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 09 Jul 2021 07:05:25 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nicolaiarocci.com/book-review-power-to-the-words/</guid>
      <description>Vera Gheno&amp;rsquo;s &amp;ldquo;Potere alle Parole&amp;rdquo; (Power to the Words) is an essay on the importance of appropriate use of the (Italian) language, not just in written works but also and predominately in everyday life.
What would we think of a person who, having a vast wardrobe of beautiful clothes, always wore the same suit out of laziness? These situations appear unlikely; yet, they are examples of the attitude that many have towards their language: they have access to an immense, incalculable patrimony, which out of indolence, or fear, or inexperience, they use partially.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Vera Gheno&rsquo;s &ldquo;Potere alle Parole&rdquo; (Power to the Words) is an essay on the
importance of appropriate use of the (Italian) language, not just in written
works but also and predominately in everyday life.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>What would we think of a person who, having a vast wardrobe of beautiful
clothes, always wore the same suit out of laziness? These situations appear
unlikely; yet, they are examples of the attitude that many have towards their
language: they have access to an immense, incalculable patrimony, which out
of indolence, or fear, or inexperience, they use partially. Even if the
Italian does not need to be saved or preserved, we should love it more
because it is a magnificent instrument. It is a shame to limit ourselves to
only a superficial frequentation.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Vera Gheno is a sociolinguist. She teaches at the Universities of Florence and
Siena. She collaborates with the &ldquo;Accademia della Crusca&rdquo;, the most important
research institution of the Italian language and the oldest linguistic academy
in the world. She is also a phenomenal popularizer. I am sure that some
concepts and notions expressed here are well known to the knowledgeable person,
but this book is not targeted to that kind of reader. I think this work is
purposedly aiming at the general public.Yet, I suspect it would remain
enjoyable to those in the field mainly thanks to its always fresh and
entertaining style.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" src="/images/potere-alle-parole.jpg#right" alt="Potere alle Parole book cover"  />

One of the many takeaways is that languages change, evolve, and constantly
adapt over time. Hence there is no standard, norm, or canon set in stone. New
words are minted continuously. At the same time, some others decay and slowly
disappear. Words initially borrowed from foreign languages (English, yes, but
also French, and many other unexpected ones, like Hungarian) enter the
dictionary to become part of the norm. We old farts should not be so quick to
condemn our kids&rsquo; slang: some of their jargon will soon be forgotten, some will
join the canon. The same happened, of course, in our time and forever before.</p>
<p><em>Subscribe to the <a href="https://nicolaiarocci.substack.com">newsletter</a>, the <a href="https://nicolaiarocci.com/index.xml">RSS feed</a>, or follow @<a href="http://twitter.com/nicolaiarocci">nicolaiarocci</a> on Twitter</em></p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Book Review: Alpi Ribelli: Storie di montagna, resistenza e utopia</title>
      <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/book-review-alpi-ribelli-storie-di-montagna-resistenza-e-utopia/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 05 Jun 2021 07:05:25 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nicolaiarocci.com/book-review-alpi-ribelli-storie-di-montagna-resistenza-e-utopia/</guid>
      <description>The idea behind this book is fascinating. As the subtitle suggests, the book collects stories of rebel mountaineers of all kinds. Some chose to disobey orders; others built refuges of resistance, outposts of autonomy and laboratories of social innovation.
The collection is rich and varied. We go from the heretics who went with Fra Dolcino to the partisans who stopped the Nazi fascists in the mountains of Cuneo and Belluno, up to the contemporary movements against the high-speed train in the Susa Valley.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The idea behind this book is fascinating. As the subtitle suggests, the book
collects stories of rebel mountaineers of all kinds. Some chose to disobey
orders; others built refuges of resistance, outposts of autonomy and
laboratories of social innovation.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" src="/images/alpi-ribelli-book-cover.jpeg#right" alt="Alpi Ribelli book cover"  />

The collection is rich and varied. We go from the heretics who went with Fra
Dolcino to the partisans who stopped the Nazi fascists in the mountains of
Cuneo and Belluno, up to the contemporary movements against the high-speed
train in the Susa Valley. Some high-profile mountain climbers are present as
well. Tita Piaz, the Dolomiti Devil; the Nuovo Mattino climbers who, inspired
by the revolution going in Yosemite , let go of the classic &ldquo;fight with the
Alp&rdquo; approach to mountain climbing; the very notable (and totally unknown to
me) story of Guido Rossa, worker, trade unionist, and fantastic rock climber.
The Italian Alpine Club internal struggle from which the Mountain Wilderness
association originated.</p>
<p>Enrico Camanni, the author, is essentially a journalist, and it shows. I know
him since the mid-90s when he was the editorial director of the then best
mountain magazine, Alp. I might be wrong, but I suspect that this work is
mainly composed of articles previously written for magazines and other works,
here edited and enriched. That is not necessarily a negative, but I find the
prose sometimes short-lived, other times emphatic, erratic in some ways.</p>
<p>Overall a good book. I appreciated some reflections and considerations,
especially those around the now unbreakable, intertwined bonds between the
lowlands and the highlands.</p>
<p><em>Subscribe to the <a href="https://nicolaiarocci.substack.com">newsletter</a>, the <a href="https://nicolaiarocci.com/index.xml">RSS feed</a>, or follow @<a href="http://twitter.com/nicolaiarocci">nicolaiarocci</a> on Twitter</em></p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Book Review: The Voice of the Sirens. The Greeks and the art of persuasion</title>
      <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/book-review-the-voice-of-the-sirens.-the-greeks-and-the-art-of-persuasion/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 15 May 2021 07:05:25 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nicolaiarocci.com/book-review-the-voice-of-the-sirens.-the-greeks-and-the-art-of-persuasion/</guid>
      <description>According to a famous and fortunate Homeric expression, words are winged, not so much like birds but rather like arrows, which cut the air quickly to go straight to the target and break through the listener&amp;rsquo;s heart. The Greeks have always known that the word is used to convince and show truth and correctness. But they also know that it has a magical force in it: it can turn into a spell, capable of dominating and dragging the listener&amp;rsquo;s soul; to bewitch like music and to heal like medicine; but, above all, to deceive and mislead.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<blockquote>
<p>According to a famous and fortunate Homeric expression, words are winged, not
so much like birds but rather like arrows, which cut the air quickly to go
straight to the target and break through the listener&rsquo;s heart. The Greeks
have always known that the word is used to convince and show truth and
correctness. But they also know that it has a magical force in it: it can
turn into a spell, capable of dominating and dragging the listener&rsquo;s soul; to
bewitch like music and to heal like medicine; but, above all, to deceive and
mislead.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>Laura Pepe teaches ancient greek law at the University of Milan. In her career,
she published many academic works and also scientific divulgation books. The
Voice of the Sirens falls in the latter category.</p>
<p>For the ancients, the Sirens were horrifying monsters, half birds and half
women. Yet, they had something that made them irresistible: the voice,
persuasive and captivating. In this book, along with other similar mythological
figures such as Circe, Calypso and Elena, Sirens are protagonists of a journey
that starts from Homer and focuses on the Athens of the 5th century. Athens,
the city of democracy and, even before that, of the word. Retracing
little-known stories and famous passages of prose and poetry, Professor Pepe
investigates the incredible potential of <em>peithó</em>, persuasion, the word that
both seduces and convinces.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" src="/images/la-voce-delle-sirene.jpg#right" alt="La Voce delle Sirene"  />

The word, the most powerful sovereign, can carry out the most divine deeds: it
knows how to convince the true and the just, but it can also deceive and
mislead. Pepe shows its strengths by looking at the protagonists of politics
who address people gathered in assembly, and then at accusers and accused, who
work hard to convince the court&rsquo;s judges. Finally, she looks at the masters of
persuasion, the sophists, who were also active in 5th century Athens.</p>
<p>Professor Pepe does a great job at reminding us how and why Ancient Greece</p>
<ul>
<li>between history, myth, poems and philosophy - has shaped our way of thinking
and dealing with the world. In almost thousands of years, we have significantly
progressed in many incredible ways. Yet the mechanisms that drive modern
societies have evolved only marginally and, what&rsquo;s humbling, the fundamental
questions raised by the great minds of that age remain unanswered<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1</a></sup>.</li>
</ul>
<p><em>Subscribe to the [newsletter][nl], the [RSS feed][rss], or follow @[nicolaiarocci][tw] on Twitter</em></p>
<div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
<hr>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1">
<p>Unfortunately, I am not aware of any international edition currently available for this book. It deserves one.
[rss]: <a href="https://nicolaiarocci.com/index.xml">https://nicolaiarocci.com/index.xml</a>
[tw]: <a href="http://twitter.com/nicolaiarocci">http://twitter.com/nicolaiarocci</a>
[nl]: <a href="https://nicolaiarocci.substack.com">https://nicolaiarocci.substack.com</a>&#160;<a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
</ol>
</div>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Book Review: One Man Caravan</title>
      <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/book-review-one-man-caravan/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 02 May 2021 07:05:25 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nicolaiarocci.com/book-review-one-man-caravan/</guid>
      <description>Robert Edison Fulton was the first solo round-the-world motorcycle tourer. He made his worldwide trip on a two-cylinder Douglas motorcycle between July 1932 and December 1933, more or less 90 years ago. On his way from London to the colonial Middle East, Fulton crossed Nazi Germany. Some of the countries and places he passed do not exist anymore. Most have changed dramatically; others, not so much. I suspect, for example, that his adventures in Syria, Afghanistan, or at the Indian-Pakistani borders might have been written today.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Robert Edison Fulton was the first solo round-the-world motorcycle tourer. He
made his worldwide trip on a two-cylinder Douglas motorcycle between July 1932
and December 1933, more or less 90 years ago. On his way from London to the
colonial Middle East, Fulton crossed Nazi Germany. Some of the countries and
places he passed do not exist anymore. Most have changed dramatically; others,
not so much.  I suspect, for example, that his adventures in Syria,
Afghanistan, or at the Indian-Pakistani borders might have been written today.</p>
<p>Fulton was in his early twenties when he started his journey. The book was
published only a few years later, in 1937. Stories were still fresh and not
conditioned by the passing age. That is important because within the next
decade the world would change forever. Take Japan. There he is greeted by
a flock of enthusiast, merry motorcyclists who will accompany him across the
country, celebrating the strong bond between the United States and the Rising
Sun. In few years, the same situation will be inconceivable.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" src="/images/one-man-caravan.jpg#right" alt="One Man Caravan book cover"  />

This book is not your typical motorcycle log. It is about stories, people, and
societies more than routes, timetables, and usual motorcycle porn. The Author
might happily skip thousands of miles across some undoubtedly incredible
terrain just because he feels the urge to tell about that memorable encounter
he had in Teheran or Tokyo or that otherwise small insignificant Malaysian
village.</p>
<p>The tone is often naive and amusing. Even dramatic events are often narrated in
a light, entertaining fashion. But make no mistake, this was a genuine
adventure, filled with thrilling and dangerous moments. It is somewhat
startling that the Author could cross so many God-forsaken places only to get
his bike stolen when he was back home in New York. Thankfully he got it back
one week later.</p>
<p>In few occurrences, a colonial attitude surfaces. That might sound jarring to
the modern educated reader, but we have to put it all in context. After all, in
1932, Fulton was the offspring of a wealthy American family. He was studying in
London when he left to explore the world in reply to a dare. Given the premise,
I think he instead emerges as a curious, unassuming person who is willing to
learn, understand and, of course, explore.</p>
<p>In the same years, Patrick Leigh Fermor, another young student, embarked on
a similar journey. He went all the way across Europe down to Constantinople, on
foot. Leigh Fermor memories are also available for your reading pleasure in
a remarkable three-book series<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1</a></sup>. Together, the stories of these two fearless
authors draw a great picture of an age when the world was still enormous and
divided into many diverse, often isolated cultures and societies.</p>
<p><em>Subscribe to the [newsletter][nl], the [RSS feed][rss], or follow @[nicolaiarocci][tw] on Twitter</em></p>
<div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
<hr>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1">
<p>First one being <em>A Time of Gifts: On Foot to Constantinople: from the Hook of Holland to the Middle Danube</em>. Browse some of his books in my <a href="/books-i-have-read">reading list</a>.
[rss]: <a href="https://nicolaiarocci.com/index.xml">https://nicolaiarocci.com/index.xml</a>
[tw]: <a href="http://twitter.com/nicolaiarocci">http://twitter.com/nicolaiarocci</a>
[nl]: <a href="https://nicolaiarocci.substack.com">https://nicolaiarocci.substack.com</a>&#160;<a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
</ol>
</div>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Book Review: The Silence, A Novel</title>
      <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/book-review-the-silence-a-novel/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 11 Apr 2021 07:05:25 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nicolaiarocci.com/book-review-the-silence-a-novel/</guid>
      <description>It is Super Bowl Sunday in the year 2022. Five people, dinner, an apartment on the east side of Manhattan. The retired physics professor and her husband and her former student waiting for the couple who will join them from what becomes a dramatic flight from Paris. The conversation ranges from a survey telescope in North-central Chile to a favorite brand of bourbon to Einstein’s 1912 Manuscript on the Special Theory of Relativity.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<blockquote>
<p>It is Super Bowl Sunday in the year 2022. Five people, dinner, an apartment
on the east side of Manhattan. The retired physics professor and her husband
and her former student waiting for the couple who will join them from what
becomes a dramatic flight from Paris. The conversation ranges from a survey
telescope in North-central Chile to a favorite brand of bourbon to Einstein’s
1912 Manuscript on the Special Theory of Relativity. Then something happens
and the digital connections that have transformed our lives are severed. What
follows is a dazzling and profoundly moving conversation about what makes us
human.</p>
</blockquote>
<p><img loading="lazy" src="/images/the-silence.jpg#right" alt="The Silence (book cover)"  />

What happens when our technology suddenly abandons us? In this novella, DeLillo
explores the immediate consequences of such an event. It&rsquo;s a brief exploration,
though. We don&rsquo;t get to go too far into the story. The book ends abruptly, and
we&rsquo;re left stranded there, pondering and wondering. I imagine this is
intentional. Upon reflection, I concede the author&rsquo;s goal is achieved, but
I have to say, my immediate feeling is unfinished work.</p>
<p>The writing meets DeLillo&rsquo;s high standards. If you&rsquo;ve read him before, you&rsquo;ll
recognize his peculiar style at first sight. The idea is also good, albeit not
super-original.</p>
<p>I found The Silence to be good, but not as good as I expected. After reading
Underworld, the bar is set pretty damn high. Anything from DeLillo should
pertain to the mind-boggling department. This novel fits more in the ok
department. It could serve as a great, gentle introduction to DeLillo, though,
as his other works can indeed be intimidating.</p>
<p><em>Subscribe to the <a href="https://nicolaiarocci.substack.com">newsletter</a>, the <a href="https://nicolaiarocci.com/index.xml">RSS feed</a>, or follow @<a href="http://twitter.com/nicolaiarocci">nicolaiarocci</a> on Twitter</em></p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Book Review: In the Heart of the Sea, The Tragedy of the Waleship Essex</title>
      <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/book-review-in-the-heart-of-the-sea-the-tragedy-of-the-waleship-essex/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 02 Apr 2021 07:05:25 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nicolaiarocci.com/book-review-in-the-heart-of-the-sea-the-tragedy-of-the-waleship-essex/</guid>
      <description>While reading Erebus, The Story of a Ship, my attention was caught by a brief mention of the Whaleship Essex. Being the sucker that I am for exploration and dramatic adventure stories from the early days, I researched it, only to surface with Nathaniel Philbricks&amp;rsquo; In The Heart of the Sea in my hands.
In the Heart of the Sea brings to new life the incredible story of the wreck of the whaleship Essex - an event as mythic in its own century as the Titanic disaster in ours, and the inspiration for the climax of Moby-Dick.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>While reading <a href="/book-review-erebus-the-story-of-a-ship/">Erebus, The Story of a Ship</a>, my attention was caught by
a brief mention of the Whaleship Essex.  Being the sucker that I am for
exploration and dramatic adventure stories from the early days, I researched
it, only to surface with Nathaniel Philbricks&rsquo; In The Heart of the Sea in my
hands.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>In the Heart of the Sea brings to new life the incredible story of the wreck
of the whaleship Essex - an event as mythic in its own century as the Titanic
disaster in ours, and the inspiration for the climax of Moby-Dick. In
a harrowing page-turner, Nathaniel Philbrick restores this epic story to its
rightful place in American history.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>In The Heart of the Sea is a nonfiction work. By telling the story of the Essex
Whaleship&rsquo;s final voyage, it successfully brings back the difficult, dangerous,
and adventurous lives of the 19th-century whalers.</p>
<p>The book is organized into four main parts. In the first part, the author
recounts Nantucket&rsquo;s culture and it&rsquo;s people way of life. The isle of Nantucket
was the then flourishing world capital of the whale-hunting industry.  It is
difficult for a modern-world citizen to conceive how big a deal the
whale-hunting industry was back then. Just think that, back then, all the
street lamps and most common lamps were burning - you guessed it - whale oil.</p>
<p>In the second part, we follow the Whaleship Essex and its crew as they hunt
sperm whales across the Atlantic Ocean and the Pacific. This is where we learn
what living the whale-hunter life on board an 18th-century ship was like, and
let me tell you, it wasn&rsquo;t pretty. We also get to know most crew members,
starting from Captain George Pollard Jr. and First Mate Owen Chase. They
will both have a prominent role in the events that will follow.</p>
<p>The third part is the earth of the story. Essex&rsquo;s wreck was caused by an
enraged sperm whale. After the disaster, the crew then had to go through
a dramatic ordeal. They were alone, on three tiny whaleboats in the middle of
the Pacific, 3.700km west of South America, with scarce food and water.  The
choices they made at that moment were crucial. Unfortunately, they weren&rsquo;t
the right ones. I think this is an essential point in the story. Ignorance, and
superstitions, induced the survivors to make the wrong call on their next move,
which led to terrible, unbearable consequences.</p>
<p>The fourth part follows the survivors as they come back to the isle and then
spend the rest of their lives struggling to arrive at peace with the events
they lived and the actions they were forced to commit during their 1820 ordeal
(Philbrick just <em>loves</em> using this world, &ldquo;ordeal&rdquo;.)</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" src="/images/in-the-heart-of-the-sea.jpg#right" alt="In the Heart of the Sea (book cover)"  />

I thoroughly enjoyed this book. Philbrick did a great job reconstructing and
then telling the events in a fascinating, engaging way. Not that the story
needed embellishments, really. Having read the account of the disaster compiled
by First Mate Owen Chase, Hermann Melville used it as inspiration for his
Moby-Dick. Philbrick actually tries to reconstruct Melville&rsquo;s encounters with
both Captain Pollard and First Mate Chase. I appreciate how the author always
informs the reader when he&rsquo;s entering speculation territory.</p>
<p><em>Subscribe to the <a href="https://nicolaiarocci.substack.com">newsletter</a>, the <a href="https://nicolaiarocci.com/index.xml">RSS feed</a>, or follow @<a href="http://twitter.com/nicolaiarocci">nicolaiarocci</a> on Twitter</em></p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Book Review: Materada</title>
      <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/book-review-materada/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 19 Mar 2021 07:05:25 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nicolaiarocci.com/book-review-materada/</guid>
      <description>I am very ignorant about the Istrian Peninsula&amp;rsquo;s history, a gap I always wanted to fill. After some research, Fulvio Tomizza&amp;rsquo;s book, Materada, surfaced as a good fit to fill this gap. It&amp;rsquo;s a semi-biographic historical novel set in the Istria of the author&amp;rsquo;s youth. Fulvio Tomizza was born in Giurizzani di Materada, Istria, in 1935. He had to go through all the torments caused in that disputed area by Fascism first (forced Italianization, cultural suppression), and then by the Second World War and the terrible events that followed: the Foibe massacres and the Istrian-Dalmatian exodus.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I am very ignorant about the Istrian Peninsula&rsquo;s history, a gap I always wanted
to fill. After some research, Fulvio Tomizza&rsquo;s book, Materada, surfaced as
a good fit to fill this gap. It&rsquo;s a semi-biographic historical novel set in the
Istria of the author&rsquo;s youth. Fulvio Tomizza was born in Giurizzani di
Materada, Istria, in 1935. He had to go through all the torments caused in that
disputed area by Fascism first (forced Italianization, cultural suppression),
and then by the Second World War and the terrible events that followed: the
Foibe massacres and the Istrian-Dalmatian exodus.</p>
<p>In the spring of 1955, in the countryside around the village of Materada,
Francesco Koslovic &ndash;even his name straddles two cultures&ndash; world is falling
apart. Following the Paris Peace Treaties of 1947, Istrian-Italians and
Dalmatian-Italians, who have long and peacefully inhabited the area with
Croatian and Slovene communities, have to choose. Abandon their homes and
the hard-worked atavistic land, migrate to Italy, become Italian, or stay in
a now-hostile territory. Francesco and his brother have to make the call with
their families. They had a portion of their land confiscated by the Yugoslavian
regime. They know the situation is dire. But this is their promised land.  As
they procrastinate and time goes by, most farmers around them, the friends who
make their community, slowly but inevitably leave along with their families.
The sense of abandonment is palpable.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" src="/images/materada.jpg#right" alt="Materada, by Fulvio Tomizza (book cover)"  />

This novel tells the experience the author had to experience himself, along
with his own family. He moved to Trieste in 1954. Throughout his whole life,
however, he kept going back to Materada, to his roots. Writing this tale must
have been a cathartic effort. Initially, I had a hard time connecting with the
story. That happened, I think, <em>precisely</em> because of my ignorance about
surrounding historical events. Materada was a great, painful, worthwhile read.</p>
<p><em>Subscribe to the <a href="https://nicolaiarocci.substack.com">newsletter</a>, the <a href="https://nicolaiarocci.com/index.xml">RSS feed</a>, or follow @<a href="http://twitter.com/nicolaiarocci">nicolaiarocci</a> on Twitter</em></p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Book Review: The Library at Night</title>
      <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/book-review-the-library-at-night/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 06 Mar 2021 07:05:25 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nicolaiarocci.com/book-review-the-library-at-night/</guid>
      <description>As any other bookworm worth its salt, I digested a generous amount of books on books and the history of libraries. Alberto Manguel&amp;rsquo;s The Library at Night was last, and that is a pity. It probably arrived just a little too late on my shelves. I wish I found it at the beginning of my reading journey when my enthusiasm for libraries and their contents was pristine.
Manguel&amp;rsquo;s writing is mesmerizing and capable.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>As any other bookworm worth its salt, I digested a generous amount of books on
books and the history of libraries. Alberto Manguel&rsquo;s The Library at Night was
last, and that is a pity. It probably arrived just a little too late on my
shelves. I wish I found it at the beginning of my reading journey when my
enthusiasm for libraries and their contents was pristine.</p>
<p>Manguel&rsquo;s writing is mesmerizing and capable. The lover of libraries and their
books (in that order because this text is more about libraries than the books
they contain) will undoubtedly fall into the rabbit hole and devour this book.
Check this out:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>But at night, when the library lamps are lit, the outside world disappears
and nothing but this space of books remains in existence. To someone standing
outside, in the garden, the library at night appears like a vast vessel of
some sort, like that strange Chinese villa that, in 1888, the capricious
Empress Cixi caused to be built in the shape of a ship marooned in a garden
lake of her Summer Palace. In the dark, with the windows lit and the rows of
books glittering, the library is a closed space, a universe of self-serving
rules that pretend to replace or translate those of the shapeless universe
beyond.</p>
</blockquote>
<p><img loading="lazy" src="/images/the_library_at_night.jpg#right" alt="The Library at Night (book cover)"  />

This book is a treasure chest filled with remarkable, carefully crafted gems.
With books like this one, I feel bad for not taking notes as I read. Each
chapter is on a topic: the library as power, as order, shape, shadow, mind,
workshop, and the list goes on. Some are more exciting than others, but overall
the selection is rich, varied, and original enough to keep the reader
entertained all along. The author&rsquo;s library, assembled during his whole life,
spent a &ldquo;professional reader&rdquo; (not kidding, as a teenager, he was reading books
for a now-blind Jorge Luis Borges) and collecting books all-along while moving
across three continents, is the recurring theme. One way or another, you&rsquo;ll
find it mentioned in every chapter, and for good reasons, because it must have
been formidable<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote-ref" role="doc-noteref">1</a></sup>.</p>
<p>The text mentions a remarkable number of ancient and modern authors with their
works. The author shows his culture, but not in a pedantic or annoying way. One
chapter is about the advent of digital libraries. I share his preference for
the printed form. He goes a great length into explaining why old school is
better, and I tend to agree with most of his reasoning. I think, however, that
he is too dismissive of the digital form. It brings so many previously
unthinkable features. He acknowledges some. It has always been my dream to own
both forms of all my books: printed and digital. If there were one service that
allowed me to buy both at once, at the same price, I would be all-in.</p>
<p>Last but not least, my favorite quote from the book:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Immensely generous, my books make no demands on me but offer all kind of
illuminations.</p>
</blockquote>
<p><em>Subscribe to the <a href="https://nicolaiarocci.substack.com">newsletter</a>, the <a href="https://nicolaiarocci.com/index.xml">RSS feed</a>, or follow @<a href="http://twitter.com/nicolaiarocci">nicolaiarocci</a> on Twitter</em></p>
<div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes">
<hr>
<ol>
<li id="fn:1">
<p><strong>Spoiler alert</strong>. I researched into the matter. It turns out that Manguel&rsquo;s library counted 40,000 titles. In 2020, he <a href="https://www.theglobeandmail.com/arts/books/article-alberto-manguel-to-donate-40000-works-to-lisbons-centre-for-research/">donated them all</a> to Lisbon&rsquo;s Centre for Research into the History of Reading.&#160;<a href="#fnref:1" class="footnote-backref" role="doc-backlink">&#x21a9;&#xfe0e;</a></p>
</li>
</ol>
</div>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Book Review: We Have Always Lived in the Castle</title>
      <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/book-review-we-have-always-lived-in-the-castle/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 18 Feb 2021 07:05:25 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nicolaiarocci.com/book-review-we-have-always-lived-in-the-castle/</guid>
      <description>I came back to reading Shirley Jackson almost by coincidence. I had just finished watching The Haunting of Hill House, and, as I always do with stuff that tickles my curiosity, I was doing a little research on it. That&amp;rsquo;s how I learned that the TV Series is loosely based on a novel by the same name written by&amp;hellip; Shirley Jackson.
Still imbued by the TV Series&amp;rsquo;s atmospheres, now knowing about its connection with Jackson, I was ready for another dive into her literature of psychological suspense and terror.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I came back to reading Shirley Jackson almost by coincidence. I had just
finished watching The Haunting of Hill House, and, as I always do with stuff
that tickles my curiosity, I was doing a little research on it. That&rsquo;s how
I learned that the TV Series is loosely based on a novel by the same name
written by&hellip; Shirley Jackson.</p>
<p>Still imbued by the TV Series&rsquo;s atmospheres, now knowing about its connection
with Jackson, I was ready for another dive into her literature of psychological
suspense and terror. Terror, not horror. Because one thing to appreciate in
Jackson&rsquo;s writing is that she relies on the former rather than the latter. To
elicit emotion in the reader, she uses the tension between characters&rsquo; psyches
and the complex relationships between mysterious events. Stephen King opens his
own novel, Firestarter, with this dedication: &ldquo;In memory of Shirley Jackson,
who never needed to raise her voice.&rdquo;</p>
<p>We Have Always Lived in the Castle is a masterpiece. Let&rsquo;s just marvel for
a moment at the mastery of the incipit:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>My name is Mary Katherine Blackwood. I am eighteen years old, and I live with
my sister Constance. I have often thought that with any luck at all, I could
have been born a werewolf, because the two middle fingers on both my hands
are the same length, but I have had to be content with what I had. I dislike
washing myself, and dogs, and noise. I like my sister Constance, and Richard
Plantagenet, and Amanita phalloides, the death-cup mushroom. Everyone else in
my family is dead.</p>
</blockquote>
<p><img loading="lazy" src="/images/we_have_always_lived_in_the_castle.jpg#right" alt="We Have Always Lived in the Castle(book cover)"  />

Tone and pace are subtly, masterfully set right there in the opening paragraph.
The main character is already outlined. In hindsight, by the end of the book,
we can tell that we were hinted at a lot more than we initially thought. As
I was reading, I could not help but think how clear and terse Jackson&rsquo;s prose
is. Only apparently simple, it draws scenes and characters with gem-cut
precision. The unsaid does matter.</p>
<p>As Jonathan Lethem once noted, all of Jackson&rsquo;s work creates an atmosphere of
strangeness and contact with a vast intimacy with everyday evil&hellip; and how that
intimacy affects a village, a family, a self. This is, in fact, true for all
the three Jacksons&rsquo; works I read. Another common theme is the persecution of
people who exhibit &ldquo;otherness&rdquo; or become outsiders in small communities, like
those found in remote villages. This mirrors the author&rsquo;s own experience. When
she moved with her husband from New York to a small, rural Vermont village,
they were isolated and ostracized by the local community. According to Letham,
mainly because of anti-Semitism and anti-intellectualism.</p>
<p>In We Have Always Lived in the Castle, however, there is room for love and
devotion. Only, they are probably extreme or distorted in sinister and
remarkable ways.</p>
<p>This book is brilliant because it takes the canonical witch/haunted house theme
and flips it over, instantly reversing the perspective. The story is told from
within the house. Village folks are the bad guys. Those who seem to be
motivated by good intentions are only fulfilling their own ego or striving to
behave with good manners, as society expects them to do. We cannot help but
feel at least a drop of compassion and sympathy for the devil.</p>
<p><em>Subscribe to the <a href="https://nicolaiarocci.substack.com">newsletter</a>, the <a href="https://nicolaiarocci.com/index.xml">RSS feed</a>, or follow @<a href="http://twitter.com/nicolaiarocci">nicolaiarocci</a> on Twitter</em></p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Book Review: The Water Dancer</title>
      <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/book-review-the-water-dancer/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 06 Feb 2021 07:05:25 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nicolaiarocci.com/book-review-the-water-dancer/</guid>
      <description>The Water Dancer is the debut novel for Ta-Nehisi Coates, an author and journalist best known for his nonfiction works. Set in a slave plantation located in pre-civil war Virginia, this is a bold and ambitious story about slavery. From the editor website:
Young Hiram Walker was born into bondage. When his mother was sold away, Hiram was robbed of all memory of her—but was gifted with a mysterious power. Years later, when Hiram almost drowns in a river, that same power saves his life.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The Water Dancer is the debut novel for Ta-Nehisi Coates, an author and
journalist best known for his nonfiction works. Set in a slave plantation
located in pre-civil war Virginia, this is a bold and ambitious story about
slavery. From the editor <a href="https://www.penguinrandomhouse.com/books/550171/the-water-dancer-by-ta-nehisi-coates/">website</a>:</p>
<blockquote>
<p>Young Hiram Walker was born into bondage. When his mother was sold away,
Hiram was robbed of all memory of her—but was gifted with a mysterious power.
Years later, when Hiram almost drowns in a river, that same power saves his
life. This brush with death births an urgency in Hiram and a daring scheme:
to escape from the only home he’s ever known.</p>
</blockquote>
<p><img loading="lazy" src="/images/water_dancer_cover.jpg#right" alt="The Water Dancer, book cover"  />

Given the premise, one might expect an action-packed escape story. Instead, the
rhythm is deliberately slow-paced, and the tone is quiet. In fact, some
reviewers find the book a little slow. I disagree. It&rsquo;s calm, yes, but
definitely not slow. Hiram Walker, the main character, has this quiet attitude.
Because he is the narrator, we see the world from his own perspective.</p>
<p>Coates prose is excellent if sometimes a little meandering. Several times while
reading, I was brought back to scenes from Quentin Tarantino&rsquo;s Django
Unchained. Mind you, this novel is nothing at all like Django. There is
violence, and brutality too, but they stay under trace. Yet, somehow this novel
manages to validate the movie&rsquo;s events; it makes them very believable.</p>
<p>I was a little disconcerted when supernatural elements started pouring into the
story. The plot deviating from the historic genre into what, fantasy? Then it
landed on me. This work is obviously the result of long and passionate
research. If fantastical elements are introduced, it must be because they fit
with the story somehow. A little research reveals that, indeed, that is the
case. Myths of slaves escaping their condition by magic means or powerful
ritual songs were deep-rooted within their culture. In this novel, legend
becomes reality. What I initially found to be jarring turns out to be the
perfect plot-twist, the expedient that allows the story to unfold.</p>
<p>The Underground Railroad, the network of secret routes and safe houses used by
the enslaved to escape into the free states of the North, is a fascinating
subject. I did not know about it, and I am grateful to this book for teaching
me.</p>
<p>I think this book does an excellent job at recounting slavery from the enslaved
(or the Tasked, as the author calls them) viewpoint and their culture.</p>
<p><em>Subscribe to the <a href="https://nicolaiarocci.substack.com">newsletter</a>, the <a href="https://nicolaiarocci.com/index.xml">RSS feed</a>, or follow @<a href="http://twitter.com/nicolaiarocci">nicolaiarocci</a> on Twitter</em></p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Book Review: Erebus, The Story of a Ship</title>
      <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/book-review-erebus-the-story-of-a-ship/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 Jan 2021 07:05:25 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nicolaiarocci.com/book-review-erebus-the-story-of-a-ship/</guid>
      <description>I finished reading Erebus: The Story of a Ship by Michael Palin, an excellent book on the dramatic adventures of the HMS Erebus with her sister ship, the HMS Terror, first in James Clark Ross&amp;rsquo;s Antarctic expedition of 1839-43, and then during Franklin’s ill-fated Arctic expedition in search of the Northwest Passage. I knew Michael Palin as a member of the Monty Python comedy group. As it turns out, since 1980, he has also made many travel documentaries and books.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>I finished reading <em>Erebus: The Story of a Ship</em> by Michael Palin, an excellent
book on the dramatic adventures of the HMS Erebus with her sister ship, the HMS
Terror, first in James Clark Ross&rsquo;s Antarctic expedition of 1839-43, and then
during Franklin’s ill-fated Arctic expedition in search of the Northwest
Passage. I knew Michael Palin as a member of the Monty Python comedy group. As
it turns out, since 1980, he has also made many travel documentaries and books.</p>
<p>I first became interested in these two ships’ Arctic adventure after watching
the fictionalized TV series <em>The Terror</em> with my son Marco. As a former navy
sailor myself, I appreciated how they realistically reconstructed the
claustrophobic every-day life on board the Victorian age ships. However, I did
not enjoy how the script soon took part from the real events, turning the story
into something closer to Jurassic Park, and that’s where I stopped watching the
series.</p>
<p><img loading="lazy" src="/images/erebus_cover.jpg#right" alt="Erebus: The Story of a Ship (book cover)"  />

This book, instead, is incredibly well-researched and written. To help tell the
story, Palin has traveled to various locations across the world – Tasmania, the
Falklands, the Canadian Arctic – to search for local information and experience
the terrain and the conditions that would have confronted the Erebus and her
crew. For anyone interested in history, exploration and heroic tales, this is
a book for you.</p>
<p><em>Enjoyed this post? Subscribe to the <a href="https://nicolaiarocci.substack.com">newsletter</a> or follow @<a href="http://twitter.com/nicolaiarocci">nicolaiarocci</a> on Twitter.</em></p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
