<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
  <channel>
    <title>elon on Nicola Iarocci</title>
    <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/tags/elon/</link>
    <description>Recent content in elon on Nicola Iarocci</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <copyright>Produced / Written / Maintained by [Nicola Iarocci](/) since 2010</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 29 Oct 2022 07:05:25 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://nicolaiarocci.com/tags/elon/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Welcome to hell, Elon</title>
      <link>https://nicolaiarocci.com/welcome-to-hell-elon/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 29 Oct 2022 07:05:25 +0100</pubDate>
      <guid>https://nicolaiarocci.com/welcome-to-hell-elon/</guid>
      <description>As someone who&amp;rsquo;s been on board with Twitter since 2009, I have to admit that I&amp;rsquo;m very concerned with recent developments. I admire and respect Elon Musk for his companies&amp;rsquo; achievements, especially in space and electric movement industries, but the man himself, holy cow, what a drag.
On The Verge, Nilay Patel&amp;rsquo;s brutal piece on the recent Twitter acquisition is chock-full of brilliant insights on what it takes to run a modern commercial social service.</description>
      <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>As someone who&rsquo;s been on board with Twitter since 2009, I have to admit that
I&rsquo;m <em>very</em> concerned with recent developments. I admire and respect Elon Musk
for his companies&rsquo; achievements, especially in space and electric movement
industries, but the man himself, holy cow, what a drag.</p>
<p>On The Verge, Nilay Patel&rsquo;s brutal piece on the recent Twitter acquisition is
chock-full of brilliant insights on what it takes to run a modern commercial
social service.</p>
<blockquote>
<p>You fucked up real good, kiddo. Twitter is a disaster clown car company that
is successful despite itself, and there is no possible way to grow users and
revenue without making a series of enormous compromises that will ultimately
destroy your reputation and possibly cause grievous damage to your other
companies.</p>
</blockquote>
<blockquote>
<p>I say this with utter confidence because the problems with Twitter are not
engineering problems. They are political problems. Twitter, the company,
makes very little interesting technology; the tech stack is not the valuable
asset. The asset is the user base: hopelessly addicted politicians,
reporters, celebrities, and other people who should know better but keep
posting anyway. You! You, Elon Musk, are addicted to Twitter. You’re the
asset. You just bought yourself for $44 billion dollars.</p>
</blockquote>
<p>More <a href="https://www.theverge.com/2022/10/28/23428132/elon-musk-twitter-acquisition-problems-speech-moderation">here</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
